<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<document-metadata version="1.0" xmlns="http://breeze.macromedia.com/">
	<document-info>
		<title>7.3 Wet Pelletization Part 1 </title>
		<summary></summary>
		<author/>
		<keywords/>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000001.jpg"/>
		<view-link href="/viewer.swf?slide={{position}}" href-html5="/" href-swf="/viewer.swf?slide={{position}}"/>
	</document-info>
	<section type="slide" position="1" xmlns="">
		<title>7.3. Wet Pelletization</title>
		<content>7.3. Wet Pelletization Part 1 </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;This is the module 7.3. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Wet Pelletization:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; Part 1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;In wet &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;pelletization&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;, the powder carbon black is converted to pellets by the process of tumble agglomeration with water in a pin pelletizer.  The water coalesces the carbon black into wet nuclei, these nuclei are &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;densified&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; by collisions with the pins, other nuclei and the walls of the pelletizer.  Round agglomerates are formed by tumble agglomeration on the inner surface of the cylindrical shell of the pelletizer.  This occurs at a very high rate in comparison to dry &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;pelletization&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;. This mechanism of agglomeration was discussed in the section on &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;pelletization&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; theory.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000001.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="2" xmlns="">
		<title>Wet Pelletization Uses</title>
		<content>Aggressive mixing is available to disperse pellets such as in rubber production Transport to the customer is in bulk containers Advantage: Harder pellets allow for rough handling without significant deterioration Disadvantage: Energy is required to dry the carbon black Wet Pelletization Uses </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Wet pellets are used in customer applications where aggressive mixing equipment is available to disperse the harder pellets such as in rubber production for tire manufacture and mechanical rubber goods.  Also, these pellets are used where transport to the customer is primarily in bulk containers such as bulk bags where the harder pellets are more resistant to attrition and deterioration.   Most rubber grade carbon black production units in the carbon black industry use wet pelletization for pelletizing carbon black.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The primary advantage of wet pellets is that the harder pellets allow them to be handled in bulk  and unloaded with pneumatic systems or mechanical systems without significant pellet deterioration.  This usually means that the cost of transport for the customer is lower.  One of the primary disadvantages of wet pelletization is that energy is required to dry the carbon black after pelletization. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000002.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="3" xmlns="">
		<title>Wet Pelletization Process</title>
		<content>   Wet Pelletizer            Dryer Drum  Wet Pelletizer   Dried Pellets Volumetric Feeder   Gases to Filter   Water and Binder Surge Bin/Agitator Rotary Dryer     Rotary Valve Pelletizer Pin Shaft Top of Surge Bin with Agitator Front of Dryer and Combustor Controls and Instrumentation Wet Pelletization Process </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Our wet pelletizing process is composed of the following equipment:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;A surge bin with an agitator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;A powder feed device to the wet pelletizer such as a rotary valve.  A horizontal screw conveyor can be installed after this rotary valve to stabilize the powder flow.  This screw conveyor may be required if the densities of the powder vary considerably.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;A wet pelletizer sometimes called a pin pelletizer or pin mixer.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;A dryer to dry the carbon black wet pellets after the pelletization process.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Controls and instrumentation for the operator to control the pelletization process. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000003.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="4" xmlns="">
		<title>Wet Pelletization Process</title>
		<content>Wet Pelletization Process              Dryer Drum Wet Pelletizer   Dried Pellets Volumetric Feeder   Gases to Filter  Rotary Dryer     Carbon Black Powder  from Reactor Carbon Black Powder from Dryer Drum,  Vacuum Sources, Reprocessing  Surge Bin/Agitator Water and Binder   </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;In the wet pelletization process, carbon black powder from the production unit is conveyed to a surge bin.  The surge bin is a small cylindrical tank with an agitator.  The surge bin serves as a buffer of carbon black flow from the process unit and is important in maintaining stability of residence time in the pelletization process.  Other carbon black powders from vacuum systems in the plant, from reprocessing carbon black and from the dryer exhaust gases are also returned to be re-pelletized via auxiliary filters upstream of the surge bin.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;A volumetric feed device regulates the flow of the powder carbon black from the surge bin into the wet pelletizer.  A screw conveyor may be included in the process after the surge bin to stabilize the flow of carbon black, especially if the powder densities of the carbon black products vary considerably in the process.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;In the wet pelletizer, water containing pelletizing binder or other additives is mixed with the carbon black powder using pins set in a helical arrangement on a shaft turning at speeds ranging from about to 400 up to 750 rpm.  The speed of the pelletizer is generally set by a variable frequency, motor drive and is controlled at a fixed speed for each individual product as determined by a balance between the amount of structure reduction required on the pellets and the pellet quality desired.  The water rate to the carbon black pelletizer is set by maintaining a power setting on the motor to the pelletizer. The percent water on the wet pellets is directly related to the structure of the carbon black and ranges from about 40% to over 55% of the total wet pellet.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The powder forms nuclei with the water and these nuclei are densified and further agglomerated in the pelletizer.  The residence time in the pelletizer is typically less than 30 seconds.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The resulting wet pellets are discharged from the pelletizer into a dryer.  Drying is a very important step in the wet pelletization process and will be covered separately by another session of this training program.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;After drying, the dried pellet has less than 1% water.  This final product may be cooled during transport to bulk storage and prior to packaging.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000004.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="5" xmlns="">
		<title>Pelletizer Controls</title>
		<content> Pelletizer Controls               </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;This is a process and instrumentation diagram of the wet pelletizer control system.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The surge bin is equipped with a level indicator so the amount of carbon black in the surge bin can be monitored at all times.  Preferably, this is a weigh cell type device that can weigh the contents of the surge bin.   Also, the pressure inside the surge bin and the temperature of the contents in the surge bin should be monitored. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The powder feeding device from the surge bin has a variable speed drive so the flow of carbon black can be controlled.  In some installations the variable speed drive is put in a control loop that controls the level in the surge bin.  This can only be done if the carbon black flow to the surge bin is fairly consistent.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The pelletizer is shown heated by a steam system that provides steam to the shell of the pelletizer.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Also, a steam heater is provided to heat the water going to the pelletizer.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The steam condensate from both the pelletizer jacket and the water heater is returned to the boiler.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Some pelletizers are heated by a hot water system.  The steam or hot water is used to prevent carbon black from caking on the inside surfaces of the pelletizer and disrupting the pelletization.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The flow of water to the pelletizer is controlled by the motor power on the pelletizer motor.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Any additives are mixed into the pelletizer water using a ratio control device that regulates the flow of these additives based on the water flow to the pelletizer.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;An in-line mixer is provided to assure that the additives are uniformly mixed in the water to the pelletizer.  If only a binder is used in the product, a conductivity meter can be installed downstream of the in line mixer to monitor the concentration of the binder in the water flowing to the pelletizer. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000005.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="6" xmlns="">
		<title>Powder to Pellets</title>
		<content>    Powder to Pellets </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;In the wet pelletizer, the carbon black powder is converted into carbon black granules or pellets.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000006.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="7" xmlns="">
		<title>Wet Pelleting Theory</title>
		<content>Wetting and Nucleation Important Processes Formation of nuclei pellets Effective mixing of powder and liquid Nuclei formation depends on effective wetting time and aggregate properties Effective mixing depends on the technique used for delivering water to the powder and mixing speed Wet Pelleting Theory </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;The theory of pelleting in a wet pelletizer can be explained in three stages.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The zone where water is injected onto the dry carbon black powder is called the mixing zone.  In this zone, there are two important processes: the formation of nuclei pellets and the effective mixing of powder and liquid.  Nuclei pellet formation depends on the effective wetting time and the properties of the aggregate that promote liquid bridging of the aggregates.  The effective mixing of powder and water depends on the technique used for delivering the water to the powder and the mixing speed of the pelletizer.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000007.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="8" xmlns="">
		<title>Wet Pelleting Theory</title>
		<content>Densification is also impacted by liquid surface tension and viscosity Pellet growth depends on internal surface area and mean pellet path Depends on the diameter and length of pelletizer Clearance  of the pins from the pin to the wall Residence time is affected by caking of carbon black on the walls and wear of the pins Both factors should be controlled by good maintenance Gases are expelled from the aggregate and growth into larger agglomerates begins Collision of the nuclei with pins, other nuclei, and walls compresses aggregates into agglomerates Tumble agglomeration causes growth of spherical agglomerates Dependant upon the number of collisions Dependant on pin velocity, residence time, and number of pins Densification and Growth Wet Pelleting Theory </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Once liquids are effectively mixed in the aggregate, gases are expelled from the aggregate and growth of the nuclei pellets into larger agglomerates begins.  The action of the collision of the nuclei with the pelletizer pins, with other nuclei and with the walls of the pelletizer compresses the carbon black particles into larger agglomerates.  Water is squeezed to the surface and liquid bridges are formed between colliding particles.  This is the period of rapid growth.  The agglomerates are hurled to the wall of the pelletizer cylinder by the action of the pins.  The process of tumble agglomeration on the inside cylindrical surface of the pelletizer causes the growth of spherical agglomerates.  The densification is dependent primarily on the number of collisions of the nuclei with the pins and the walls of the pelletizer.  These collisions are dependent upon the pin velocity, the residence time in the pelletizer, and the number of pins.  The densification is secondarily impacted by the liquid surface tension and the liquid viscosity.  Growth of the round pellet is dependent upon the internal surface area in the pelletizer available for growth and the mean pellet path through the pelletizer.  This is dependent upon the diameter of the pelletizer, the length of the pelletizer and the clearance of the pins from the pin to the wall.  These features define the effective residence time in the machine and are typically fixed by the design of the pelletizer.  The residence time in the machine can also be affected by the caking of carbon black on the walls of the pelletizer and the wear of the pins.  To maintain stable pelletization, these factors should be controlled by good maintenance of the pelletizer and good operational practices.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000008.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="9" xmlns="">
		<title>Wet Pelleting Theory</title>
		<content>During collisions pellets can be broken and reformed At increasing speeds, attrition and breakage can occur which produce smaller agglomerates Speed of mixing and number of collisions after optimum formation is important in controlling deterioration Attrition and Breakage Wet Pelleting Theory </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;With collisions occurring in the pelletizer, the pellets can be broken and reformed.  At increasing pelletizer speed, it has been shown that once pellets are formed, attrition and breakage can occur which can produce smaller agglomerates.   The speed of mixing and number of collisions after optimum formation is important in controlling pellet size deterioration.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000009.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="10" xmlns="">
		<title>Wet Pelletizer (Pin Mixer)</title>
		<content>Key Concepts of the Wet Pelletizer&amp;#x0A; Stability of carbon black powder flow to the pelletizer Water is uniformly mixed with carbon black powder Water reaches capillary state in the aggregates Viscosity of the carbon black-water mixture peaks Peak viscosity of mixture is detected by the motor power Water addition rate is controlled to a constant motor power set point Wet Pelletizer (Pin Mixer) Water &amp;amp; Binder </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;The pelletizer mixes water into the  carbon black powder and controls the water content of the wet pellets.   The uniformity of this mixing is highly affected by the stability of the carbon black powder flow to the pelletizer. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;In the zone where the water is mixed with the dry particles, the coverage of the water and the effective wetting of the carbon black is important.  The water should be mixed into the carbon black aggregates uniformly for uniform growth of agglomerates.  Once the water is added to the carbon black aggregate and the capillary state is achieved, the viscosity of the carbon black-water mixture peaks and the torque of the pelletizer peaks.  This point can be sensed by the power of the drive motor.  The total torque on the pelletizer shaft is dependent upon the structure of the carbon black, the water content of the wet pellet, the throughput of carbon black, and the geometric design of the pelletizer itself.   We can control the water content of the wet pellets and optimize pelletization by controlling the optimum power of the motor with control of the water addition to the pelletizer.  This optimum point of water content is very similar to the optimum point of torque we observe when we measure the oil absorption number of the carbon black in the laboratory. At this point of optimum water content, the pelletizer maximizes the formation of pellets&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000010.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="11" xmlns="">
		<title>Wet Pelletizer (Pin Mixer – con’t)</title>
		<content>Nuclei agglomerates formed due to liquid bridges between aggregates Collisions densify the pellet nuclei Circulation of agglomerates on the inner cylindrical surface generates growth of round agglomerates Residence time in the pelletizer is important for pellet completion Structure is reduced by the work done on the pellets Binder and other additives can be added for improving pellet strength, other properties Higher speed = smaller, harder, more uniform pellets Wet Pelletizer (Pin Mixer – con’t)  </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Once water is added to an optimum level to the carbon black aggregates, nuclei agglomerates are formed.  Then the remaining process of pelletization occurs in the machine. The nuclei are densified as a result of collisions of the nuclei with other nuclei, with the pins of the pelletizer and with the internal shell of the pelletizer.  The agglomerates circulate in the machine on the inner surface of the pelletizer shell forming round agglomerates.  The amount of time the pellets remain in the machine, the residence time in the pelletizer, is important for completing the finished, round pellet.  The residence time for pelletization is normally less than 30 seconds.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The work done in the process of pelletization also breaks the structure of the carbon black aggregate.  Therefore, in the pelletizer, we will observe a reduction of the structure of the carbon black as measured by the oil absorption number.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Binder and other additives can be added to the carbon black in the pelletizer to improve the pellet quality of the carbon black, to oxidize the carbon black, or improve carbon black dispersion.  These additives are normally added to the pelletizer water and mixed uniformly in the water so they will be mixed uniformly in the carbon black.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Higher speeds of the pelletizer tend to produce smaller, harder, and more uniform pellets.  However, at very high speeds the pelletizer can begin destroying the pellets.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000011.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="12" xmlns="">
		<title>Pelletizer Shaft Designs</title>
		<content>Pelletizer Shaft Designs      </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Shown here are pelletizer pin shafts from pelletizers used in our industry.  As you can see from all the photographs, the pelletizer shafts are slightly different with respect to the length of the pins, the diameter of the shaft, the number of pin helixes, and the lengths of the shafts.  What cannot be easily seen are other design variables such as the diameter of the pins, the pitch of the pins in the helix and the clearance of the pins from the pin wall.  All of these variables impact the pellet quality from the pelletizer and the carbon black throughput capacity of the machine.  Some carbon black manufacturers have their own proprietary pelletizers.  There are also many commercial pelletizers available.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000012.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="13" xmlns="">
		<title>Pelletizer Variables</title>
		<content>Pelletizer Variables Pin diameter		Number of Helixes	 Pin pitch		Helix Pitch 		 Pin coating					Shaft diameter Pin length		Dams  			Shaft length		 Pin number 		Pelletizer Inlet/outlet design 			 Pin density 		 Shape of Pin Tip	Shell medium (water or steam) Pin clearance  Rotational speed				Carbon Black rates	 Motor power					Binder Type Water injection spray type			Carbon Black temperature Water spray location				Additive Types (diesel) Water % on wet pellets				Vacuum/pressure in machine Binder rate 	 				Shell temperature Pelletizing water temperature 								   </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;In experimental work with pelletizers, it has been found that the variables shown here can affect the pelletization process, such as, the quality of pellets being formed in the pelletizer, the throughput of carbon black, or the power efficiency of the pelletization process.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Fortunately, many other variables {shown inside the yellow block} are defined by the design of the pelletizer we are using and are fixed for our operation.    We will not discuss these variables in detail.  There are many scientific and engineering manuals that give a more complete discussion of criteria important for pelletization of fine powders and pelletization design.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000013.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="14" xmlns="">
		<title>Pelletizer - Components</title>
		<content> Pelletizer - Components Water is injected at one location One special spray design is used Shell temp = 90oC One, two, three or more helixes of pins Low pin to wall clearance Maintenance is important Allows for pin replacement </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;This is a cut away view of a pelletizer showing the different components.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The shaft can have one, two, three or more helixes of pins.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;One of the primary features of a pelletizer is the low pin to wall clearance of the pelletizer (about 4 millimeters). It is important that the shaft be properly maintained and pins are replaced when the pin wear is excessive and deterioration of pellet quality is observed.  This particular machine design allows easy replacement of the pelletizer pins so the pin to wall clearance can be maintained. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Water is injected at one location at the inlet of the pelletizer and one special spray design is used for good water distribution.  The shell temperature of the pelletizer is maintained at a temperature of about 90 degrees Celsius to prevent cake formation inside the pelletizer which is detrimental to pelletizer quality. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000014.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="15" xmlns="">
		<title>END</title>
		<content>END  </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;This is the end of module 7.3. Wet Pelletization:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; Part 1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000015.jpg"/>
	</section>
</document-metadata>
