<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<document-metadata version="1.0" xmlns="http://breeze.macromedia.com/">
	<document-info>
		<title>1.1 Introduction to Carbon Black</title>
		<summary></summary>
		<author/>
		<keywords/>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000001.jpg"/>
		<view-link href="/viewer.swf?slide={{position}}" href-html5="/" href-swf="/viewer.swf?slide={{position}}"/>
	</document-info>
	<section type="slide" position="1" xmlns="">
		<title>1.1 Introduction to Carbon Black</title>
		<content>1.1 Introduction to Carbon Black  </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;This is the &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Module 1.1 &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Introduction to Carbon Black.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000001.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="2" xmlns="">
		<title>Carbon</title>
		<content> Carbon  C   18.5% C Atomic Number = 6 Atomic Weight and Isotopes 	=12 is stable 	=13 is stable 	=14 is radioactive </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Carbon is a &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;chemical element&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; with &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;symbol&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; C and &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;atomic number&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; 6. It is &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;nonmetallic&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; and &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;tetra-valent&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;—making four &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;electrons&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; available to form &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;covalent&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;chemical bonds&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;. It belongs to group 4 of the periodic table. The isotopes of a chemical element have the same atomic number and nearly identical chemical behavior but with a different atomic mass.  Three &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;isotopes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; of carbon, occur naturally.  Isotopes of carbon with atomic weight 12 and 13 are stable, while atomic weight 14 is a &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;radionuclide&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;, decaying with a &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;half-life&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; of about 5,730 years. Carbon is one of the &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;few elements known since antiquity&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Carbon is the 15th &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;most abundant element in the Earth's crust&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;, and the &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;fourth most abundant element in the universe by mass&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; after &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;hydrogen&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;helium&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;, and &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;oxygen&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;. Carbon's abundance, its unique diversity of &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;organic compounds&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;, and its unusual ability to form &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;polymers&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; at the temperatures commonly encountered on &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Earth&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; enables this element to serve as a common element of &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;all known life&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;. It is the second most abundant element in the &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;human body&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; by mass (about 18.5%) after oxygen.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000002.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="3" xmlns="">
		<title>Allotropes</title>
		<content> Allotropes Eight allotropes of carbon:      Lonsdaleite C60 (Buckminsterfullerene) C540 C70 Graphite Amorphous Carbon Diamond Carbon nanotubes      </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;The atoms of carbon can bond together in different ways, termed &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;allotropes of carbon&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;. The best known are &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;diamond&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;,  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;amorphous carbon&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; and &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;graphite&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;. The &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;physical properties&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; of carbon vary widely with the allotropic form. For example, graphite is &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;opaque&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; and black while diamond is highly &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;transparent&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;. Graphite is soft enough to form a streak on paper while diamond is the hardest naturally occurring material known.  Graphite is a good &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;electrical conductor&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; while diamond has a low &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;electrical conductivity&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;. Under normal conditions, diamond, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;carbon nanotubes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;, and &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;graphene&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; have the highest &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;thermal conductivities&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; of &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;all known materials&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;. All carbon allotropes are solids under normal conditions, with graphite being the most &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;thermodynamically stable&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; form at standard temperature and pressure. They are chemically resistant and require high temperature to react even with oxygen.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000003.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="4" xmlns="">
		<title>What is Carbon Black</title>
		<content> A paracrystalline carbon consisting of at least 95 % carbon by weight. Produce by partial combustion of hydrocarbon (natural gas, acetylene, coal tars, petroleum residual oils). Carbon black is not soot (soot is amorphous and is typically high in PAH content). Carbon black is produced under controlled conditions. Used in rubber, plastics, inks paints. Provides color and enhanced performance properties. Marketed as a granule and a powder.   What is Carbon Black    </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Carbon black is a form of&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold" textDecoration="underline"&gt;paracrystalline&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold" textDecoration="underline"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold" textDecoration="underline"&gt;carbon&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; that has a high &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;surface-area-to-volume ratio&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;, albeit lower than that of &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;activated carbon&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;.   Today it is an industrial material produced mainly by the &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;incomplete combustion of heavy hydrocarbon liquids &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;such as &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;F-C-C&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; tar, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;coal tar&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;, or ethylene cracker tar and hydrocarbon gases such as natural gas and acetylene. It is &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;dissimilar to &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;soot&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; in its much higher surface-area-to-volume ratio and significantly lower &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbon&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; content.   Unlike soot, in today’s modern factories carbon black is produced under &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;precisely controlled conditions&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Carbon black is mainly used as a reinforcing &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;filler&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; in &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;tires&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; and other &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;rubber products&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;. In &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;plastics, paints, and inks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;, carbon black is used as a color &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  textDecoration="underline"&gt;pigment&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  textDecoration="underline"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;and has properties that can inhibit deterioration of polymers from ultraviolet light and provide conductivity.  Generally, carbon black is marketed in &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;granular form &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;with “pellets” that are a few millimeters in diameter or in an agglomerated &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;powder form&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;.  The granular form is usually preferred by customers since it transports easier and causes less environmental issues.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000004.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="5" xmlns="">
		<title>What is Carbon Black</title>
		<content>Elemental analysis of Carbon Black What is Carbon Black Elemental analysis of Carbon Black Carbon (C)		95.0 – 99.5% Hydrogen (H)		0.2 – 1.3% Oxygen (O)		0.2 -	0.5% Nitrogen (N)		0.0 -	1.0% Sulphur (S)		0.1 -	3.0% Other impurities	ppm   Metal, Refractory and Salt   Depends on S in raw material  </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Carbon black purity is reflected in the quality of the raw materials used in production and contaminates that are caused by contact with gases and surfaces in the carbon black process.  In general, carbon black is over 95% pure carbon.  Sulfur in the carbon black generally comes the feedstock and is a residual in the carbon black as well as a component in the gases exhausted from the process.  Fractions of metal, refractory and salts result in impurities in the carbon black that could be detrimental to sensitive applications.  Many carbon black processes have special non-corrosive metals and use high purity water and other ingredients in the recipe to create a very pure product for special applications.  Since carbon black is adsorptive in nature the surface chemistry can be very complex as a result of the contact the carbon black has in the process.  Sometimes special additives are used to give special properties to the carbon black.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000005.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="6" xmlns="">
		<title>What is Carbon Black</title>
		<content>Some general characteristics of Carbon Black: What is Carbon Black Particle aggregates Black pigment Highly adsorptive Morphologically paracrystalline carbon Very small particle size (10-500 nm)         High surface area (6 – 1200 m2/g) Chemically almost pure carbon Nanoparticle </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;In applications, carbon black is generally used as a black pigmenting agent.  It is highly adsorptive and hygroscopic so it must be stored in dry conditions to avoid water being adsorbed into the aggregate.  The shape of a carbon black aggregate is shown in the electron micrograph above.  The particles are the round nodules within the aggregate.  So when measuring particle size we are measuring the “average” diameter of the nodules shown by the distance between the blue arrows in the photograph.  The distance between the red arrows is an approximation of the aggregate size which is an aggregate of many particles or nodules.   The particle size may be measured in nanometers so carbon black can be considered as on of the first nanoparticles investigated in the scientific world.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000006.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="7" xmlns="">
		<title>Particle Size</title>
		<content>Particle Size      </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;This chart shows the relative size of different qualities of carbon black ranging from high color products that are approximately 10 nanometers in diameter to medium thermal blacks, M-T, that are approximately 470 nanometers in diameter.  In the same chart are the relative particle sizes of fumed silica and titanium oxide which are white fillers.  The electron micrograph image of a carbon black aggregate has been magnified by 50 thousand times.  This electron micrograph gives a very clear picture of the structure of a carbon black and within the aggregate, you can see the relative size of the particles.  The 3-D model represents the electron micrograph with the added feature of depth of view.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000007.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="8" xmlns="">
		<title>Manufacturing of Carbon Black</title>
		<content>30,000 BCA – Rudimentary form in cave dwellings. Manufacturing of Carbon Black 1200 BCA – Manufactured by Chinese and Egyptians. 15th Century – Movable type for printing. 1900 – Reinforcement of rubber for auto industry. 1941 – Oil furnace black patented by Phillips Petroleum Corporation Limited. Today – New generation oil furnace Black reactor.     </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Carbon black was used in a rudimentary form in cave dwellings over 30 thousand years ago.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;About 3 thousand years ago, a primitive form of manufacturing carbon black was shown in Egyptian heiroglypics and about the same time Chinese documents show writings using inks made with carbon blacks.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Once printing became common in the 15&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;th&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; century production of carbon black for printing inks increase and with the advent of automobiles using rubber tires became a major mode of transportation, carbon black for reinforcing rubber brought about further growth of the industry.  In the early 20&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;th&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; century most of the carbon black was manufactured by natural gas.  A new method was developed prior to World War II, the oil furnace process,  that led the industry to produce products using liquid hydrocarbons such as petroleum tars and coal tars.  The oil furnace process has continued to be refined and improved until today, the industry is highly efficient with many high quality and unique products.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000008.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="9" xmlns="">
		<title>Carbon Black Process Model of  21st Century</title>
		<content>Carbon Black Process Model of  21st Century  Reactor Heat Recovery Beading Waste Gases  </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;In the oil furnace carbon black process, the reactor is the core of the operation that forms the carbon black particle.  This reactor is precisely controlled so the carbon black is uniform and high quality.  It leaves the reactor in powder form and is pelletized to granules in a pelletizer or beader.  The process of making carbon black is high in energy consumption.  Therefore, heat generated in the process is captured and used to heat raw materials to make the energy consumption of the reactor more efficient.  Also, the by-product gases formed during the carbon black production are used to heat water and make steam and also to dry the wet beaded carbon blacks.   The schematic above depicts an efficient modern day carbon black process that generates electrical power and provides heating for community use.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000009.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="10" xmlns="">
		<title>Modern Carbon Black Plant 21st Century</title>
		<content>Modern Carbon Black Plant&amp;#x0A;21st Century  </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;This modern chemical plant is the Singur plant of Himadri Speciality Chemicals.  Himadri has carbon black production lines that are some of the most modern in the carbon black industry.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000010.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="11" xmlns="">
		<title>Carbon Black at Himadri in Everyday life</title>
		<content>         Carbon Black at Himadri in Everyday life  </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Carbon black produced at Himadri is found in all types of products that you see in everyday life.  Almost everything around you that is black contains carbon black, from the tires on your automobile, the ink on your newspaper, garbage bags, to plastics found in wires and cables.  Even the fabrics in black clothing that are made of polymers have carbon black.    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000011.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="12" xmlns="">
		<title>Global Market of Carbon Black</title>
		<content>SectorComponentShare ValueTireTread70CarcassSidewallBeadTubesNon TireHoses20BeltWeather - StrippingGaskets/ SealsNon RubberPlastic10InksPaints/ CoatingsOthersTotal100 Global Market of Carbon Black     </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;As you can see from this table, most of the carbon black in the world is used in the components of rubber tires.  A tire may have many types of carbon black in it depending on the service required; for instance, life of the tire tread or reduced heat build-up in the sidewalls.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The second most carbon black consumption is in non-tire rubber.  Many rubber products on an automobile including the weather stripping around windows, belts, hoses and even mounts for cushioning vibration have carbon black in them.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;This shows that 90% of the applications for carbon blacks are in rubber products.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The non-rubber applications include pigmenting plastics, inks and paints.  Also, in this segment are many specialty applications that provide ultraviolet light protection in products such as plastic pipes and electrical conductivity in products such as power cables.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000012.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="13" xmlns="">
		<title>Himadri Product Portfolio</title>
		<content>Himadri Product Portfolio ASTM Tire GradesN 115N 234N 375N 121N 326N 550N 134N 330N 660N 220N 339N 772N 231N 347N 774Tire Gold MRG   (Mechanical Rubber Goods)        ProductKlarex RG 223 (N 550 low grit)Klarex RG 225 (Weather strips, profiles)Klarex RG 227 (Smooth extrusions)N 550 (Extrudates)N 660 (Tubes)N 772 (General Purpose) Specialty BlackKP 103 – Commodity plastic, news inkKP 107 – Fine denier fibresKP 111 – Plastic pipesKP 202 – Colour masterbatchKP 203 – UV absorbent plasticsKP 205 – Fibre masterbatchKC 144 – Masterbatch, moulded products.KC 170 – CoatingsElectra 273 – Semi-conductive applicationsElectra 275 – Medium and high voltage applications </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Himadri has a complete range of products for fulfilling the requirements of its carbon black customers.  The ASTM tire products go to many diversified manufacturers in the tire industry.  Non-tire rubber products are classified in a market called M-R-G, or mechanical rubber goods.  And specialty blacks are produced for a wide range of plastic, ink and coatings applications.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000013.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="14" xmlns="">
		<title>Global Production Capacity of Carbon Black</title>
		<content>Global Production Capacity of Carbon Black  17 Billion 7 Billion  </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;In 2018, global capacity of carbon black reached approximately 17 billion metric tons.  In the late 20th century, the North American and European economic regions were producing a very large share of the carbon black in the world.  However, capacity did not grow in these areas due to a variety of factors including raw material costs and environmental pressures.  By 2018, as seen in this table, Chinese carbon black production capacity at approximately 7.0 billion tons annually was the largest in the world and represented about 40% of the global capacity.   In the 20&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;th&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; century, Chinese carbon black was, in general, a low quality commodity product but with the influx of modern global manufacturing technology into the Chinese industry, currently many Chinese products can now compete in the international market on both a cost and quality basis.   &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000014.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="15" xmlns="">
		<title>Global Producers</title>
		<content>Global Producers GLOBAL RANKINGCOMPANYCAPACITY  (MT)1CABOT21302BIRLA-COLUMBIAN20103ORION12954BLACK CAT11455TOKAI - SRC9376CSR - CONTINENTAL8107OMSK5008LONGXING CHEMICAL5009PCBL500  </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;There are many players in the global carbon black market.  Leading the field in productive capacity are Cabot Corporation and Aditya Birla with over 2 billion tons of annual capacity each.  Both of these manufacturers have production facilities and technical support groups in the major tire production zones in the world – North America, Europe and Asia.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000015.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="16" xmlns="">
		<title>Carbon Black Companies in India</title>
		<content>Carbon Black Companies in India   ~ 500, 000 Tons capacity  ~ 180, 000 Tons capacity     </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;India has five major manufacturing companies producing carbon black as shown here.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; Recently a new producer, BKT started production.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; Philips Carbon Black is the largest of those companies in India with four plants and a reported capacity of about 500 thousand metric tons per annum.  Himadri Speciality Chemicals has an annual capacity of 120 thousand metric tons per annum growing to 180 thousand metric tons by 2020.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000016.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="17" xmlns="">
		<title>END</title>
		<content>END  </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;This is the end&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; of Module 1.1. Introduction to Carbon Black.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000017.jpg"/>
	</section>
</document-metadata>
