<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<document-metadata version="1.0" xmlns="http://breeze.macromedia.com/">
	<document-info>
		<title>8.2 Theory of Wetting Powders</title>
		<summary></summary>
		<author/>
		<keywords/>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000001.jpg"/>
		<view-link href="/viewer.swf?slide={{position}}" href-html5="/" href-swf="/viewer.swf?slide={{position}}"/>
	</document-info>
	<section type="slide" position="1" xmlns="">
		<title> 7.2. Theory of Wetting Powders</title>
		<content> 7.2. Theory of Wetting Powders  These materials contain information which may be confidential and protected by law.  All materials are copyright to Orion Engineered Carbons and cannot be copied without the express written consent. </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;This is the module 7.2. Theory&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; of Wetting Powders.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Because of the importance of the wet &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;pelletization&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; process in the carbon black industry, we will briefly explore some aspects of the theory of wetting powders.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000001.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="2" xmlns="">
		<title>What is Pelletization?</title>
		<content>Pelletization or agglomeration Carbon black  Produced at the reactor - loose or smoke Finely divided - fluffy or dusty Low density  Difficult to handle What is Pelletization? Size-enlargement process whereby small particles are gathered together into larger, relatively permanent masses (pellets or agglomerates) in which the original particles can still be distinguished.  </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Pelletization or agglomeration is a size-enlargement process whereby small particles are gathered together into larger, relatively permanent masses (pellets or agglomerates) in which the original particles can still be distinguished.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Carbon black produced at the reactor (“loose” or “smoke”) is finely divided (“fluffy” or “dusty”), has low density, and it is difficult to handle. During pelletization, the small particles of carbon black from the reactors are brought close enough so they will stick together under the action of short range physical forces.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Pelletization produces several benefits to our customers as explained in the next slides.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000002.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="3" xmlns="">
		<title>Benefits of Pelletization</title>
		<content>Increase material density Lower packaging and transportation costs Smaller handling and storage equipment Decrease dust concentration Improve housekeeping in handling and mixing Pellets improve flowability: Provide a more uniform flow rate in conveying  systems Eliminate or reduce  Flow stoppages Flooding  Limited discharge rates from bins and silos      Benefits of Pelletization </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;The &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;pelletization&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; process increases several times the density of the product shipped to our customers. This translates to lower packaging and transportation costs, and smaller equipment for handling and storage of the carbon black.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Fine powders exhibit flow problems in conveying systems such as flow stoppages, erratic flow, flooding and limited discharge rates from bin and silos.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Pellets are much easier and cleaner to handle than the very fine powder produced at the reactors. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Therefore we have improved housekeeping in handling and mixing.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Pellets will Improve &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;flowability which means they p&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;rovide a more uniform flow rate in conveying systems, which helps to Eliminate or reduce: flow stoppages, flooding, and Limited discharge rates from bins and silos&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;     &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000003.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="4" xmlns="">
		<title>Benefits of Pelletization (cont.)</title>
		<content>Reduce segregation of material More consistent feeding Improves final product uniformity Ease the incorporation and dispersion of carbon black into the mix Powders are more difficult to incorporate  Low density : high air content Tend to “float” on the rubber Pelletization densifies the carbon black  Substantially reduces incorporation time Benefits of Pelletization (cont.) </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;The smooth flow of carbon black results in a more consistent feeding to the mixing process improving the final product uniformity.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Powders are more difficult to &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;incorporate&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; due to their low density (high air content). Powders tend to “float” on the rubber or polymer demanding more time and energy to achieve an effective mixing.  Pelletization densifies the carbon black substantially reducing the incorporation time.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000004.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="5" xmlns="">
		<title>Carbon Black Pelletization Processes</title>
		<content>Carbon Black Pelletization Processes Because the importance of the wet process in the industry, a short explanation of wetting powders is explained in the following slides. PelletizationDrySize EnlargementAction of attractive short range physical forces WetAgglomerate into pelletsAction of physical and liquid forces Both forces acting together makes a stronger pellet   </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Fine powder particles, such as the  carbon black particles produced at the reactors, will stick together forming an agglomerate if they are brought close enough for short range forces be effective.  There are a wide variety of size-enlargement processes available. “Dry” and “wet” pelletization processes are the ones used by the carbon black industry to produce pellets.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;In dry pelletization, s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;ize enlargement occurs due to the action of attractive short range &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;physical&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; forces acting between fine powder particles.  Usually the mechanism of tumble agglomeration is used to promote particle to particle contact.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;In wet pelletization, carbon black particles agglomerate into pellets by the  action of &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;physical and liquid&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; forces. The result of both forces acting together is a stronger pellet.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Because the importance of the wet process in the industry, a short explanation of wetting powders is explained in the following slides.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000005.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="6" xmlns="">
		<title>Powder Agglomeration vs Wetting</title>
		<content> Powder Agglomeration vs Wetting               </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;As we form agglomerates from the carbon black aggregates, they do not form a very dense phase as illustrated in the drawing on the left.  There is no mechanism to make the carbon black move around until it fits together more compactly.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;However, when water is added and the mixture is stirred, the aggregates move around and are drawn tightly together.  Let’s explore why this happens.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000006.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="7" xmlns="">
		<title>Capillary Action</title>
		<content>Capillary Action    Height of Water due to  Capillary Action  Water draws aggregates very close together </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;The energy needed to move the aggregates around is believed to originate from what is called “capillary action”.  Capillary action is caused by water being attracted to surfaces already close together.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;This is shown in the picture on the left where a very small glass tube is used to pull colored water from the glass slide.  You can see how high the water has moved up the tube and this is without using a vacuum.  On the right, the drawing shows more clearly what is happening.  The water is attracted to the inside surface of the glass tube.  This attraction actually pulls the water column up the tube until the weight of the water just equals the attractive force of the water for the tube.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;This attractive force is called capillary action.  When aggregates come close to each other and there is the right amount of water present this capillary action draws the aggregates very close together.  This increases the packing density of the aggregates as illustrated on the previous slide.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; A proposed mechanism for what is happening is shown on the next slide. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000007.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="8" xmlns="">
		<title>Capillary State Target</title>
		<content>Capillary State Target  1. Funicular State2. Capillary State3.  Just the right amount of water… or it becomes a slurry. Maximum cohesive force pulls powder together. Through OAN test, we can calculate ratio of water to carbon black. Air pockets   Pendular State </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Our goal here is to get to the capillary state through two other proposed states.  First is the pendular state where there is very little water present in the powder and the water linkages between the aggregates are tenuous.  Next, we go through the funicular state where the water becomes interconnected; yet, there are still air pockets.  Lastly, one reaches the capillary state with just the right amount of water.  All the pores and capillaries between aggregates are just filled with water and a maximum cohesive force pulls the powder together.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Beyond the capillary state with too much water the cohesive forces fall and one obtains a slurry.  We just created mud.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;This explanation gives the reason why wet-pelleting works.  Depending on the structure of the carbon black using the O-A-N test, we can calculate the amount of water required to wet pellitize the amount of carbon black.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000008.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="9" xmlns="">
		<title>End</title>
		<content>End  </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;This is the &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;end of module &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;7.2. Theory&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; of Wetting Powders.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000009.jpg"/>
	</section>
</document-metadata>
