<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<document-metadata version="1.0" xmlns="http://breeze.macromedia.com/">
	<document-info>
		<title>1.2. Introduction to Carbon Black Chemistry</title>
		<summary></summary>
		<author/>
		<keywords/>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000001.jpg"/>
		<view-link href="/viewer.swf?slide={{position}}" href-html5="/" href-swf="/viewer.swf?slide={{position}}"/>
	</document-info>
	<section type="slide" position="1" xmlns="">
		<title>1.2 Introduction to Carbon Black Chemistry</title>
		<content>1.2 Introduction to Carbon Black Chemistry </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;This is module 1.2. Introduction to Carbon Black Chemistry.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Even though our process chemistry in a carbon black process is relatively simple, it is important to understand a bit of the chemistry in order to understand, how to optimize and improve the process.  In this section of the course, we will review the chemistry applicable to the carbon black production process.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000001.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="2" xmlns="">
		<title>Common Chemical Symbols for Elements</title>
		<content>Carbon				C Hydrogen			H Sulfur				S Oxygen				O Nitrogen				N Potassium			K Calcium				Ca Common Chemical Symbols for Elements  </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;In Chemistry, it is useful to use shortcuts that are common abbreviations of the chemical names to represent the elements or atomic substances found in nature.  There is an agreed symbol used internationally for each of these substances.  A standard table called the Periodic Table shows these abbreviations.  It is useful to understand a Periodic table because it contains a lot of other information about these chemicals that can be helpful in understanding their chemistry and the physical nature of the elements.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;In our carbon black process, we are concerned with seven major elements.  These elements and their chemical symbols or abbreviations are as follows:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;	&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Carbon	C&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;	Hydrogen	H&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;	&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Sulfur	S&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;	Oxygen	O&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;	Nitrogen	N&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;	Potassium	K&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;And	Calcium	&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Ca&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Some of the symbols make sense in English since they are the first letter of the chemical’s name in English.  Many others in the Periodic Table are derived from other language roots and may be difficult to understand easily in English. This is true for the chemical symbol of potassium which is K.  The Periodic Table is a good reference for the symbols for chemicals that you do not know. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000002.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="3" xmlns="">
		<title>Molecules and Molecular Weights</title>
		<content>Elements combine to form molecules Molecule notation shows the number of atoms as a subscript  - example    H20 2 atoms of hydrogen  		H 1 atom of oxygen			O Molecular weight  using  Periodic Table Molecules and Molecular Weights  Water : H2OAtomNumber of AtomsAtomic WeightMolecular WeightMass Weight RatioWeight of AtomsH21.02.02/18111 gO116.016.016/18889 gTotal Molecular Weight18.01000 g              </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;In the world around us, the atomic elements in the previous table combine into molecules to form a variety of substances.  The molecules are abbreviated in chemical notation to show the number of each atomic element in each molecule.  The subscript behind the element notation is the number of atoms in each molecule.   &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Early in the history of chemistry, it was found that the elements combined in certain mass ratios to form these molecules or substances.  These mass ratios were formalized into what are called atomic weights for each element that are equivalent to the ratio of the weight in which they are combined.  From these atomic weights, we can determine the molecular weight of a substance which will be helpful later in determining the weight of each element in each molecule.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;An example is given for water.  Water has two atoms of Hydrogen and one atom of Oxygen.  From the Periodic table we find that the atomic weight of one atom of hydrogen is approximately one (1) and for one atom of oxygen is sixteen (16).  Since there are two atoms of hydrogen in a molecule of water and one atom of oxygen, the molecular weight of water is 18.  This allows us to determine that the weight of hydrogen in one kilogram of pure water, 1000 grams, is two divided by 18 or one-ninth of the total weight of the water.  This means that the hydrogen in the water weighs 111 grams.  Oxygen makes up the remainder of the weight or 889 grams.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000003.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="4" xmlns="">
		<title>Common Raw Materials</title>
		<content>Air Feedstock Oil Liquid hydrocarbon Fuel Liquid hydrocarbon Used as source of heat Potassium Compound Additives  Water Sugar Additive (Binders) Common Raw Materials </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;In the carbon black process, we use some common raw materials to produce most of our products.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;We have compressors or blowers to provide air for combustion.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Feedstock oil is delivered in ships and bulk trucks for our primary raw material.  This oil is a liquid hydrocarbon.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Our fuel is a liquid hydrocarbon, primarily light oils, that is used as a  source of heat.   &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Chemicals containing potassium are used for control of carbon black structure in the reactor.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Water is used to cool the reactants in our process and used as an additive for wet pelletization.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Substances containing sugars are used as binders in our pelletization to keep pellets from deteriorating during transport.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;We will discuss the chemistry of each of these raw materials more thoroughly as we proceed through this presentation.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000004.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="5" xmlns="">
		<title>Air</title>
		<content>Nitrogen			N2 Oxygen			O2 Water			H2O Carbon Dioxide	CO2 Argon			Ar Air Air 79%	Nitrogen 21% 	Oxygen Humidity Deprives the combustion reaction of oxygen Must compensate O2 loss  </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Air is primarily composed of nitrogen and oxygen.  On a dry basis air is approximately 79% nitrogen and 21% oxygen.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Air also contains some water in vapor form which we call humidity.  As you know the humidity in air varies with the weather.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The water in air deprives the combustion reaction in our reactor of oxygen.  If we have humidity measurement on the air, we can compensate for this loss of oxygen and keep the combustion reaction and the quality of our product more stable.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Water in air is a very small component.  Do not confuse % relative humidity with the concentration of water in air.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Air contains other trace gases such as carbon dioxide and argon.  The gases are fairly constant in their concentration in air. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Unless, we need very sophisticated analysis of our process, we usually ignore these other trace substances that are in the air when analyzing and controlling our process.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;As you know, at times of the year pollen and dust particles may be in the air.  For very sophisticated carbon black products, these particles may contaminate our process and our products.  For very pure products, it may be necessary to filter these contaminants from the air prior to using this air in our process.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000005.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="6" xmlns="">
		<title>Feedstock Oil</title>
		<content>Hydrocarbon liquid	CnHm Hydrogen	      m = an undefined variable number Carbon		      n = an undefined variable number Feedstock Oil Hm Cn    Carbon content  above  90% for good feedstocks  </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Our feedstock oil is a hydrocarbon liquid.  This means it is composed primarily of Hydrogen and Carbon. Above, we show the symbols n and m as the atomic subscripts since this feedstock is a mixture of substances and  the exact ratios in the hydrocarbon mixture is variable.  It is usually estimated or determined by chemical analysis for each delivery of feedstock and can be reasonably estimated using a specific gravity measurement from mass flow meters.. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;In order to produce the most carbon black, we would like to have very high carbon content feedstock.  The carbon content is above 90% for our good &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;feedstocks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;.   &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000006.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="7" xmlns="">
		<title>Feedstock Oil (cont’d)</title>
		<content>Feedstock Oil (cont’d) Impurities Nitrogen	N From coal source feedstock Source of  environmental concern Forms nitrogen oxide Sulphur		S Can be as high as 4% and as low as 0.1% May vary considerably because of: Refinery’s crude oil feed Process of refining Combustion results in sulfur gases Quantities regulated by environmental authorities Content measured regularly  </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;The carbon content of the oil feedstock is impacted by other impurities in the feedstock such as sulfur.  Sulfur in the feedstock approaches 4% in some plants and may be as low as 0.1% for some high purity &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;feedstocks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;.  The sulfur in a feedstock may vary considerably as a result of a refinery’s crude oil feed or their process for refining the feedstock.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Normally, we pay close attention to the amount of sulfur in our feedstock since our combustion process results in the formation of sulfur containing gases.  The quantity of these gases are regulated by environmental authorities so in &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;our plant, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;we measure the sulfur content of the feedstock regularly.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Feedstocks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; derived from coal sources usually contain considerable nitrogen.  The nitrogen can be a source of environmental concern since it forms gases called nitrogen oxides.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000007.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="8" xmlns="">
		<title>Feedstock Oil (cont’d)</title>
		<content>Impurities (cont’d) Other Fines  from catalysts Monitor for effect on carbon black Measured as ash Sometimes detected by sieve residue test Monitoring : Determine impact on yields and quality Test suppliers of feedstock Test deliveries of oil Online analyzers Feedstock Oil (cont’d) </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;The feedstock may contain many other contaminants in small quantities such as the fines from catalysts used in the refinery.  We usually monitor these contaminants for their effect on our carbon black product and for deterioration of our process.  They can be measured as ash and sometimes are large enough to be detected by a sieve residue test.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;It is important that we monitor the quality of our oil feedstocks to determine the impact on the yields and quality of our carbon black products.  We test our suppliers of feedstock on a regular basis to confirm the composition of various elemental chemicals.  We also test the deliveries of oil on a regular basis from these suppliers.  Some carbon black plants that have very variable feedstocks have on-line analyzers for monitoring changes in their feedstock quality in order to maintain consistency in their quality and high yields.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000008.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="9" xmlns="">
		<title>Fuel</title>
		<content>Fuel Flame Temperature Heating value  Hydrocarbon liquid	CnHm Hydrogen	      m = an undefined variable number Carbon		       n = an undefined variable number Hm Cn    </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Our fuel oil is also hydrocarbon liquid, usually a light or low specific gravity liquid.  Like the feedstock, it is composed primarily of Hydrogen and Carbon. Above, we show the symbols n and m as the atomic subscripts since this fuel is also a mixture of substances and  the exact ratios in the hydrocarbon mixture is variable.  It is usually estimated or determined by chemical analysis for each delivery of fuel and can be reasonably estimated using a specific gravity measurement from mass flow meters.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;It is important for fuels to have a high heating value for providing sufficient heat for efficiently cracking the feedstock into carbon, hydrogen and other components. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;We use the heating value of the fuel and the quantitative mixture of fuel and air to determine the flame temperature that will be used in the reaction process in our reactor.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000009.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="10" xmlns="">
		<title>Fuel</title>
		<content>Methane Molecular Weight AtomNumber of AtomsWeightTotalC11212H414Total Molecular Weight16 Natural Gas 					 Methane	CH4	 Ethane		C2H6 Propane		C3H8 Nitrogen	N2 Fuel     </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Natural gas is a common heating fuel in the United States and other countries and is used in carbon black production.  It is used in the reactors for heating the gas stream prior to oil feedstock injection so an adequate and precise temperature for cracking the feedstock is available.  It may also be used as a supplemental fuel in other areas such as the dryer and boilers.  This fuel will be available to the Himadri plant in the future as a pipeline is installed for delivery.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Natural gas is a gaseous hydrocarbon consisting primarily of methane.  Methane is a simple hydrocarbon that contains one carbon atom and four hydrogen atoms.  It’s molecular weight is calculated by adding the atomic weight of one carbon atom, 12, with four hydrogen atoms, 4.  The molecular weight is 16.  Natural gas may contain other hydrocarbons such as ethane and propane which can contribute to the heating value of the natural gas.  If these gases are in measurable quantities, they should be taken into account for heating value calculations and for consideration in reactions.   Natural gas may often contain nitrogen.  The nitrogen is largely inert in a combustion reaction but it reduces the heating value and the concentration of combustion reactants.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000010.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="11" xmlns="">
		<title>Fuel</title>
		<content>Propane Molecular Weight AtomNumber of AtomsWeightTotalC31236H81  8Total Molecular Weight44 LPG 	 Propane		C3H8 Butane		C4H10 Fuel     Butane Molecular Weight AtomNumber of AtomsWeightTotalC41248H10110Total Molecular Weight58        </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Liquefied petroleum gas or liquid petroleum gas (LPG or LP gas), also referred to as simply &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;propane&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; or &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;butane&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;, are &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;flammable&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; mixtures of &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;hydrocarbon&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; gases used as &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;fuel&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; in &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;heating appliances&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;, cooking equipment, and vehicles.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;It is also a gas that we will be using in our reactor combustors as we explore the production of pure specialty carbon black products such as we are currently making and those that will be made in the future.  It is delivered in pressurized tanker vehicles containing the liquified gases and stored in high pressure tanks on our site.  Evaporators will evaporate the liquid to provide a gaseous fuel to our reactors.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Generally LPG can be a mixture of propane and butane usually with &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;p&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;ropylene&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;butylenes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;and various other hydrocarbons present in small concentrations.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;LPG for Himadri will be propane which has the formula C-3-H-8.  As you can see from the calculation table above it is a much higher molecular weight fuel than the natural gas we discussed earlier which is &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;primarily &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;methane.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;It’s molecular weight is calculated by adding the atomic weight of three carbon atoms, 36, with eight hydrogen atoms, 8.  The molecular weight is 44 compared with 16 for natural gas.  We will see from our calculations for combustion ratios that the propane will require much more oxygen and therefore more air to burn for complete combustion.  We will need to know the molecular weight of the propane when it is used in our operation to estimate the flame temperature in the combustor.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000011.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="12" xmlns="">
		<title>Water</title>
		<content>Reactor Bag Filter Prequench Wet Pelletization Contaminants - Salts Calcium 			Ca Magnesium		Mg Sodium			Na Water purification Reverse osmosis Demineralization Condensed steam Water Water Molecular Weight AtomNumber of AtomsWeightTotalH212O11616Total Molecular Weight18      Can cause residues Know what is in your water to determine impact on carbon black quality and process equipment  </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Water is added to the reactor combustion gases to stop the carbon black formation reaction.  It is also frequently added in the process bag filter prequench to cool the gases prior to the process bag filter and protect the bags of the filter.  Water also is added to the carbon black powder to promote the formation of wet pellets in the pelletization process.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;We will also see later that water is a product formed during the combustion reaction in the reactor.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The water molecule is formed from two hydrogen atoms and one oxygen atom and has a molecular weight of 18.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The water in our process may contain other dissolved chemicals depending on the source and the purity of the water.  Sometimes, calcium, magnesium and sodium salts are found in the water in small quantities.  Because we use so much water in our process, these salts can cause residues that remain in our process equipment or in the carbon black.  To produce very pure carbon blacks,  the water must also be very pure.  In these processes, we may remove the dissolved chemicals in the water using water purification processes called “reverse osmosis”,  “demineralization” or distillation prior to using the water for producing carbon black.  Sometimes water from condensed steam is used in these applications because this water is pure in comparison to normal process water.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;It is always important to know the type and quantity of chemicals that may be present in the water in order to determine the impact they may have on the carbon black quality and the process equipment.  This can be determined by testing the water on a regular basis.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000012.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="13" xmlns="">
		<title>Pelletizing Binders</title>
		<content>Major substances used: Molasses Lignosulfonates Complex carbohydrates Plant derived Used in small quantities for pellet binding Sensitive to heat – can breakdown in dryer Found to actively prevent fouling of air preheaters Pelletizing Binders  </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Pelletizing binders are added to the pelletizing water at small quantities to improve the pellet hardness of the pellets.  Too much of this binder can cause the carbon black pellets to be too hard and to be difficult to disperse in the customer’s matrix.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Two primary substances are used in the industry: molasses and lignin derivatives, usually lignosulfonates.  These binders are complex carbohydrates derived from plants.   The choice of the type binder may be the cost of the binder, the availability of the binder, and the cleanliness of the binder.  For example, pure refined sugar or corn syrup, also carbohydrates, can be used if costs are not prohibitive.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;These binders are usually added to the carbon black at very low concentrations, less than 0.5% solids by weight on the carbon black.  These carbohydrates can break down in the wet pelletizing dryer to carbon dioxide and water when heated at high temperatures usually temperatures in excess of 200 ᴼC.   &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;One additional benefit discovered in the use of pellet binders has been the addition of binder to the quench water in the reactor can prevent tube side fouling of high temperature process air preheaters.  The mechanism for this phenomenon is not fully understood.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000013.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="14" xmlns="">
		<title>Binder - Molasses</title>
		<content>Used in Himadri on rubber products as a pellet binder. In India – comes from cane sugar manufacturing. Sucrose is a disaccharide composed of monosaccharide: Glucose and fructose Carbohydrates in the molasses are the active binding agents. Molasses is impure Binder - Molasses   Sucrose Molecule Sucrose is a disaccharide composed of monosaccharide:   Glucose and fructose  Description% by WeightSolids80Ash3-10K1.787Cl0.570Ca0513S0.365Fe0.014Other0.013 RANDOM SAMPLE Description% by WeightSolids80Ash3-10 </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Molasses is the primary pelletizing binder used in Himadri.  In India, molasses is a by-product of refining sugar cane into sugar.  The molasses contains high levels of sucrose, which is a disaccharide composed of two monosaccharides, glucose and fructose.  The solids content in the molasses is approximately 80% by weight dissolved in water. The sugars in the molasses are the active pellet binding ingredients. The ash content of the molasses ranges from 3 to 10% by weight. Due to the high ash content, it is considered an impure substance.  A random sample was taken of the molasses delivered to Himadri.  It was found to contain almost 2% Potassium, 0.6% Chlorine, 0.5% Calcium, 0.4% &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Sulfur&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;, 0.1 % Iron and low concentrations of other minerals.  This elemental analysis will vary somewhat in molasses due to the agricultural conditions used for sugar cane growth and the sugar refining process. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000014.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="15" xmlns="">
		<title>Binders - Lignosulfonates</title>
		<content>Widely used in the carbon black industry Produce during tree pulping/ paper production Contains high levels of complex carbohydrates – molecular weights from 1000 to 140,000.  Lignins are diverse depending on the source of the trees used for pulping and the pulping process. Usually has been acid neutralized with calcium, sodium and ammonium additives.  The complex carbohydrate is the active binding agent. Some precipitated (clear) some Impure – high ash content Binders - Lignosulfonates PropertyTypical ValuesSolids (as total lignin)&amp;gt;65.5%58.0%Reducing sugar8%11.0%Calcium (as soluble)1%3.6%Sodium (as soluble)2%2.9%Sulfur as Sulfite4.9%Total Sulfur5.5%pH5.5-7.56.6Insolubles&amp;lt;0.08%Viscosity300 cps300 cpsColorBrown   </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Lignosulfonates are widely used in the global carbon black industry as pelletizing additives or binders.  These materials will be used at Himadri for a wide range of specialty and clean carbon black products.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Chemically, lignosulfonates, or sulfonated lignin are water-soluble anionic polyelectrolyte polymers: they are byproducts from the production of wood pulp using a sulfite pulping process. Lignosulfonates have a very broad ranges of&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  textDecoration="underline"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  textDecoration="underline"&gt;molecular ma&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;ss&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; – a &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;range of 1000 to 140,000 has been reported for softwood lignosulfonates with lower values reported for hardwoods.  One example of a lignosulfonate molecule has&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;278 carbon atoms, 407 hydrogen atoms, and 94 oxygen atoms (64% carbon, 8% hydrogen, and 29% oxygen by weight).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Prior to use in the carbon black process, the acidic lignosulfonates coming from the pulping process are neutralized using calcium, sodium, magnesium or ammonium additives, normally hydroxides.  Also, a biocide can be added to the lignin to keep the material from fermenting during storage.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The complex carbohydrate is the active binding agent in the lignin.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Lignosulfonates are available in the market in many different levels of purity.  Some products have been precipitated and contain less than 3% ash content.  These may be labelled &amp;quot;clear&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;pure&amp;quot; by the vendor.  Any vendor should certify the level of contaminants in their products.  The &amp;quot;normal&amp;quot; impure products may range from 3% to 30% ash content.  To produce clean carbon black products, we must to use a &amp;quot;pure&amp;quot; lignin product which will be more expensive than the standard raw product.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;A typical analysis of a lignosulfonate is shown in this table. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The solids content in this table generally represents the binding capability of the lignin binder.  The binding capability is primarily defined by the complex carbohydrate content which is much more difficult to &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;analyze&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;.  This binding capability can be affected by the &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;insolubles&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; and the ash content of the lignin, which should be confirmed for each supplier of lignin binder and each delivery of the binder for use.  Specifications for the lignin should be developed and maintained based on the carbon black quality requirements.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000015.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="16" xmlns="">
		<title>END</title>
		<content>END  </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;This&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; is the end of Module &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;1.2 &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Introduction to Carbon Black Chemistry.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000016.jpg"/>
	</section>
</document-metadata>
