<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<document-metadata version="1.0" xmlns="http://breeze.macromedia.com/">
	<document-info>
		<title>7.1 Pelletization Theory</title>
		<summary></summary>
		<author/>
		<keywords/>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000001.jpg"/>
		<view-link href="/viewer.swf?slide={{position}}" href-html5="/" href-swf="/viewer.swf?slide={{position}}"/>
	</document-info>
	<section type="slide" position="1" xmlns="">
		<title>7.1 Pelletization Theory</title>
		<content>7.1 Pelletization Theory  </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;This is the module 7.1 Pelletization Theory.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Pelletization or agglomeration is one of our most important process steps in the carbon black process after the carbon black powder has been formed in the reactor.  The carbon black customer wants to be able to transport the carbon black as delivered to his process without destroying the original performance properties of the carbon.  The customer also wants the carbon to transport trouble free in his plant without environmental or safety concerns.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Carbon black manufacturers have agglomerated the powder into small pellets or beads to provide a product that is free flowing for many years.  These processes for pelletization have been improved in recent years with our improved understanding of the mechanism of agglomeration and are very reliable and reproducible.  This section will discuss the theory of agglomeration and pelletization.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000001.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="2" xmlns="">
		<title>Fundamentals of Agglomeration</title>
		<content>Agglomeration Definition:  The sticking or balling of (often very fine) powder particles due to short range physical forces becoming active only if the individual particles (forming the agglomerates) are brought closely together by external effects (1) Carbon Black is a fine powder particle Get the particles close enough together, they will stick together External effect = squeezing the carbon with our hands 	Agglomeration = Pelletization = Beading [1] W. PIETSCH,: Size Enlargement by Agglomeration, Salle + Sauerländer Verlag GmbH &amp;amp; Co., Frankfurt, 1991 Fundamentals of Agglomeration </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;In reference book, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;Size Enlargement and Agglomeration&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;, the definition of &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;agglomeration&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; is defined as follows:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The sticking or balling of, often, very-fine powder particles due to short range physical forces becoming active only if the individual particles, forming the agglomerates, are brought together by external effects.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;This sounds like a very complex statement, so let’s break it down into components that we can understand as it relates to carbon black.  Carbon black is a &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;fine powder particle.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;  If we can get these &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;fine powder particles&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; close enough together, and if they have short range physical forces, they will stick together.  If we take a handful of the carbon black powder and squeeze it in our hands, we can get it to stick together like a cake.  It does this because the carbon black particles have short range physical forces between them that attract each other.  These forces are much like the magnetic forces that allow two magnets to attract each other but on a much smaller scale.  The &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;external effect&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; - squeezing the carbon with our hands - brings the particles in close enough contact to allow this “agglomeration” to occur.  Squeezing the carbon black in our hands is not a very sophisticated agglomeration process and our customer probably would not like to have it in his plant in this form, but &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;it is &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;agglomeration.  In our process, we call controlled agglomeration, pelletization or, in some cases, beading.  We will use the word pelletization for this type agglomeration in this module.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000002.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="3" xmlns="">
		<title>Physical Forces</title>
		<content>Cohesive  Attraction between “like” molecules Example – Water molecules  Adhesive  Van der Waal forces – weak attraction between “unlike” molecules Example – fly attaching itself to a vertical glass pane Major forces in dry pelletization Liquid bridges Water is added to carbon black – wet pelletization The cohesive forces of water bring carbon black particles closer together When close enough, van der Waal forces between the carbon black particles form stronger agglomerates Physical Forces </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;There are many types of physical forces between solid particles that exist in nature.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;We are going to concentrate on the physical forces that are the major actors in pelletization.  In simple terms the forces that we are considering are those that are active at the molecular and aggregate level called &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;COHESIVE AND ADHESIVE&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; forces.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;COHESIVE&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; forces are caused by the intermolecular attraction between&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt; like&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; molecules within a body or substance.  Water, for example, is strongly cohesive due to  “polarity” induced by the geometry of the water molecule.   Each molecule acts like a small magnet.   This results in a strong force between the molecules.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;ADHESIVE&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; forces include van der Waal forces. Van der Waals forces are typically weak forces between particles that are &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;not alike&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; at the molecular or particle level.  For instance, the ability of a fly to attach itself to a vertical glass pane is provided by the adhesive nature of van der Waal forces.  Carbon black particles are not &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;polar &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;like water molecules and therefore are &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;not alike&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; at the molecular or particle level.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Solid particle adhesive forces are major forces in the process of &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;dry pelletization&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; where the van der Waal’s forces provide the &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;ADHESIVE&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; forces necessary to attract the particles and bond the particles into a pellet. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;When water is added to carbon black such as in the process of &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;wet pelletization&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; , the attractive nature of the cohesive forces of the water in the carbon black particle interspaces, rapidly pulls the carbon black particles together.  When the particles are close enough, the van der Waal forces between the carbon black particles also come into play and the carbon black particles adhere to each other.  The result of both forces acting together to form the agglomerate is a stronger agglomerate.  The final force is called a liquid bridge.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Cohesion along with adhesion helps explain phenomena such as surface tension and capillary action in liquids.  Capillary action is further described in this course in the short module entitled “Theory of Wetting Powders” which gives more insight into how the process of wet pelletization proceeds . &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000003.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="4" xmlns="">
		<title>Cohesion and Adhesion</title>
		<content> Cohesion and Adhesion Cohesion – Water forming droplets   Adhesion – Water sticking to plants </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Let’s look at this plant with dew drops forming to show an example of the forces that we previously discussed.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;Cohesive forces&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; cause the water molecules to form into droplets.  Water molecules attract each other due to the chemical geometry of the water molecule causing an electrical polarity.  Therefore, they have an affinity for each other which makes them coalesce.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;This &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;cohesive attraction&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; causes each molecule to attract each other uniformly on the surface of the droplet.  This surface effect is called surface tension and this causes the water to try to form into spherical droplets.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;Adhesive forces&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; cause the water droplets to stick to the plant – the water &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;adheres&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; to the plant surface due to van der Waal forces.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000004.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="5" xmlns="">
		<title>Size Enlargement</title>
		<content>Size enlargement processes: Pressure Agglomeration Powder is pressed into molds to form dry tablets Melting/Sintering Powder is melted and formed in molds or forced through extruders Tumble Agglomeration Powder is “tumbled” in a rotating cylinder and adheres to itself to form round pellets Size Enlargement </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Several processes are used in industry to increase the size of the agglomerates to form pellets.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Pressure agglomeration requires the addition of pressure to the powder to cause size enlargement or pelletization of the agglomerate.  We gave the example earlier of using our hands to squeeze carbon black into a lump or cake.  The production of many medicines into tablets use the process of pressure agglomeration.   The powder is pressed into molds to form dry tablets. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Melting or sintering is another process for size enlargement.  Many hard candies and plastics are melted and formed in molds or forced through extruders to form pellets or other forms of larger sizes of the original substance.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;In carbon black, our process has evolved from a process called tumble agglomeration.  In this process, the powder is “tumbled” in a rotating cylinder.  The powder adheres to itself and to other agglomerates to form increased sized agglomerates and eventually round pellets.  In wet pelletization, water is added to the powder and “tumbled” at high energy in a pelletizer or mixer to form round wet pellets.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000005.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="6" xmlns="">
		<title>Tumble Agglomeration</title>
		<content>Tumble Agglomeration During tumble agglomeration, particles stick together due to one or several of the previously described forces. Round agglomerates form as a result of rolling off a declining plane or rolling during the mixing processes.  </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;In tumble pelletization, particles adhere to each other due to one or more of the previously described forces.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Round agglomerates form as a result of rolling down an inclined plane.  This may be the inside surface of a cylindrical dry drum pelletizer or the inside surface of a cylindrical wet pelletizer.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The effect is much like a snowball rolling down a hill of snow, gathering additional snow particles and growing as it goes down the hill.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000006.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="7" xmlns="">
		<title>Dry Pelletization Nucleation</title>
		<content> Dry Pelletization Nucleation    </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;In the primary stage of the tumble agglomeration in a dry pelletization process, small particle agglomerates coalesce into larger loose agglomerates.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The energy in the tumbling action of the pellet mass causes the loose agglomerates to densify into larger nuclei.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The loose agglomerates may also disintegrate into smaller agglomerates by the force of this tumbling action. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Fractured loose agglomerates can be re-pelletized or re-agglomerated into larger nuclei by the attachment of loose powder agglomerates or by combining with each other.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000007.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="8" xmlns="">
		<title>Dry Pelletization Pellet growth</title>
		<content> Dry Pelletization Pellet growth   Densification continues due to the energy mass from other pellets Round pellets form the base for the deposition of fines and loose powder to form a denser and larger pellet </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Once nuclei are formed, they can coalesce with each other to form larger agglomerates or continue to deposit fines and roll up into larger round agglomerates. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The larger agglomerates continue to densify due to the energy mass from the other pellets in the bed and roll up into round pellets. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Once round pellets are formed, they provide a dense base for the deposition of fines and loose powder to form a denser and larger diameter pellet.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000008.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="9" xmlns="">
		<title>Dry Pelletization Disintegration</title>
		<content> Dry Pelletization Disintegration An equilibrium exists between formation and destruction by the forces in the pelletization process This equilibrium should be maintained at a point where number and quality are optimized   </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;During the pelletization process, the larger granules or pellets can facture or be abraded into smaller particles.  These smaller factures and fines can be reformed into pellets.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;An equilibrium exists in the pelletizer between pellet formation and pellet destruction by the forces that exist in the pelletization process.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;It is important to maintain this equilibrium at a point where the number and quality of the pellets formed are optimized.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Therefore, very stable state operations are required for good pelletization.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000009.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="10" xmlns="">
		<title>Wet Pelletization Nucleation</title>
		<content> Wet Pelletization Nucleation Water is mixed uniformly and quickly Water promotes adhesion of carbon black </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;In tumble agglomeration in a wet pelletizer, the water is mixed uniformly and quickly with the carbon black powder in the cylindrical pelletizer.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;When water is added to the carbon black powder, the cohesive forces of the water promote the adhesion of the carbon black particles to one another.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;These liquid bridges promote the growth of agglomerate nuclei that provide the basis for further particle growth.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000010.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="11" xmlns="">
		<title>Wet Pelletization Particle Growth</title>
		<content> Wet Pelletization Particle Growth The energy inside the pelletizer packs the agglomerates closer together This makes the particles more dense and breaks down the primary structure of the carbon black Agglomerates are thrown outward by centrifugal forces The inner shell acts as an inclined surface for the agglomerates to adhere to each other </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;The wet particles coalesce into larger agglomerates as they are tossed around in the pelletizer. The cohesive force of the water promotes the rapid adhesion of these agglomerates to form even larger, denser agglomerates. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The energy of the pins moving through the mass of wet carbon black and throwing the wet carbon black agglomerates to the inside wall of the pelletizer, packs the particles of the agglomerates closer together. This also densifies the agglomerates and even breaks down the primary structure of the carbon black. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The agglomerates are thrown outward by centrifugal forces and roll at high speed on the inner shell of the cylindrical pelletizer. The inner shell of the cylinder acts as an inclined surface for the agglomerates to adhere to each other and the “snowball” of carbon black to form. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The end result is the formation of relatively small, spherical agglomerates called pellets. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000011.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="12" xmlns="">
		<title>Wet Pelletization Disintegration</title>
		<content> Wet Pelletization Disintegration  Best case is that broken agglomerates reform into pellets There is an equilibrium between pellet formation and destruction Wet pellets break upon impact when critical yield stress is exceeded It is important to maintain a balance at a point where pellet formation is optimized </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Again, in the wet pelletizer, the agglomerated particles can disintegrate into smaller agglomerates.  In the best case, these broken agglomerates and fines reform into round pellets.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;An equilibrium exists in the pelletizer between pellet formation and pellet destruction in the process by the available forces.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;It has been shown that the wet pellets can break upon impact when high shear mixers exceed the critical yield stress of the pellets.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;It is important to maintain the pellet formation equilibrium at a point where the number and quality of the pellets formed are optimized.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Therefore, stable state operations are required for good wet pelletization.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000012.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="13" xmlns="">
		<title>Factors Affecting Agglomeration</title>
		<content>Important  Factors Particle size of the aggregate Residence time for agglomeration Energy of mixing  Quality of collisions of agglomerates Length of rolling path of the agglomerates Liquid effects Factors Affecting Agglomeration </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;There are many factors that affect the agglomeration of fine particles including those of carbon black.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The most important of these are&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The particle size of the aggregate.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The residence time available in the pelletizer for agglomeration to complete and stabilize.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The energy that is provided to the mixing process in the pelletizer.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The quality of the collisions between agglomerates and powder.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The length of the rolling path of the agglomerates.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;And the amount and type of liquid used.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000013.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="14" xmlns="">
		<title>Particle Size of the Aggregate</title>
		<content>Particle Size of the Aggregate Complex aggregates – fewer contact sites Simple aggregates – more contact sites   Difficult to Pelletize High OAN High surface area  Easy to Pelletize Low OAN Low surface area  Large particle size – larger adhesive forces Small particle size – smaller adhesive forces How particle size and aggregate complexity affect adhesion. Conclusion Cohesive forces of water enhances the agglomeration </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;The assessment of agglomerating ability requires a brief study of the carbon black at the primary particle and aggregate level.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Van der Waal forces are the primary adhesive force for promoting agglomeration and finally, pelletization of the aggregates. A large primary particle results in a higher adhesive force at the contact point than a small primary particle.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;As the aggregate becomes more complex with a higher degree of branching, the number of contact sites decrease and therefore the complexity of the structure results in poorer pelletization. A less complex aggregate has more contact sites and the resulting forces will be stronger.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The conclusion for practical purposes is that carbon blacks with low oil absorption numbers and low iodine surface areas are easier to pelletize. Carbon blacks with high oil absorption numbers and high iodine surface areas are more difficult to pelletize.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;When water is added to the powder aggregates, cohesive forces in the water influences the aggregate to pull together which results in more contact points between the particles. The total adhesive forces between the particles are then stronger. Again, the short module entitled “Theory of Wetting Powders” gives more insight into how the process of the water in the aggregate promotes pelletization.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The assessment of agglomerating ability requires a brief study of the carbon black at the primary particle and aggregate level.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Van der Waal forces are the primary adhesive force for promoting agglomeration and finally, pelletization of the aggregates. A large primary particle results in a higher adhesive force at the contact point than a small primary particle.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;As the aggregate becomes more complex with a higher degree of branching the number of contact sites decrease and therefore the complexity of the structure results in poorer pelletization.  A less complex aggregate has more contact sites and the resulting forces will be stronger.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The conclusion for practical purposes thus is that carbon blacks with low oil absorption numbers and low iodine surface areas are easier to pelletize.  Carbon blacks with high oil absorption numbers and high iodine surface areas are more difficult to pelletize.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;When water is added to the powder aggregates, cohesive forces in the water influences the aggregate to pull together which results in more contact points between the particles.  The total adhesive forces between the particles are then stronger. Again, the short module entitled “Theory of Wetting Powders” gives more insight into how the process of the water in the aggregate promotes pelletization. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000014.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="15" xmlns="">
		<title>Residence Time for Agglomeration</title>
		<content>Higher flow rate = lower residence time Lower density = lower residence time Density is governed by OAN Higher OAN with lower density = lower residence time Higher bed depth = more residence time To increase production rate, increase pelletizer residence time Large pelletizers with large residence times are necessary for products with high OAN and low density  Residence Time for Agglomeration Factors affecting granulation time Flow rate Density of powder Density of agglomerates Size of pelletizer Bed depth or void depth    </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;This chart shows that for a given time for granulation or pelletization, the pellet becomes harder and increase in strength.  It becomes less plastic and more brittle.  This means that as the residence time is increased particles move to an optimum density and strength and then become brittle which increases the possibility of fracture of the agglomerates.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The granulation time or residence time for pelletization in our carbon black process is dependent upon several factors:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The flow rate of carbon black through the pelletizer.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The density of the powder being introduced to the pelletizer.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The density of the agglomerates being formed.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The size of the pelletizer – the diameter and length.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The bed depth of pellets in a dry pelletizer or the equivalent void depth of a wet pelletizer.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;For a carbon black with consistent properties, the rate of pellet formation is very constant.  Therefore, there is a direct relationship between the residence time and production throughput. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;In a given fixed pelletizer &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;	1.  The higher the carbon black flow rate the lower the residence time.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;	2.  The lower the density of carbon black the lower the residence time.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;	3.  The resulting density of carbon black is generally governed by the oil absorption 	number.  Higher OAN carbon blacks with lower densities result in lower residence times.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;	4.  A higher bed depth results in more residence time.  This is not a linear relationship since it impacts other characteristics of bed mixing that may be more influential in pellet formation.  We will discuss these issues in the module on dry pelletization.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;To increase the production rate for a product with fixed density, we need to increase the pelletizer residence time.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Larger pelletizers with larger residence times are required to pelletize products with high oil absorption numbers and low densities.	&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Having too much residence time in the pelletizer after pellets are formed can be detrimental to the product.  As you can see from the above diagram, there is a point where the forces in the pelletization process can cause pellet destruction or fracture.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000015.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="16" xmlns="">
		<title>Energy of Mixing</title>
		<content>Forces that promote pelletization Impact forces from the pellet mass on the individual pellets, Centrifugal forces of the pelletizer,  Gravity forces in the bed caused by the bed being lifted up the cylindrical wall of the pelletizer and the pellets falling down the surface of the bed. Energy of Mixing Primary Energy In a Pin Pelletizer Primary Energy In a Rotating Drum     </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;In a dry bead pelletizer, the energy of pelletization is provided primarily by the rolling energy in the bed of pellets.  There is a balance between the degree of densification and the time the pellets remain in the bed of the dry pelletizer. This rolling energy is provided by the rotational speed and the mass of pellets in the pelletizer.  The forces that promote pelletization are &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;	1. the impact forces from the pellet mass on the individual pellets,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;	2. the centrifugal forces of the pelletizer, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;	3.  the gravity forces in the bed caused by the bed being lifted up the cylindrical wall of the pelletizer and the pellets falling down the surface of the bed.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;An electrical motor turning the drum at rotational speeds normally less than 20 rpm provides the power to the pelletizer.  From a force analysis it can be clearly shown that the impact forces of the mass of pellets acting on the individual pellets are the driving force for pelletization.  These forces are 50 times higher than the gravity and centrifugal forces in a dry pelletizer. If the bed is mixed at too rapid a rate or too violently the pellets will be broken. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;In a wet bead pelletizer, the energy of pelletization is provided by the pin shaft turning in the mass of water and carbon black.  The energy is supplied by an electrical motor turning the pin shaft at rotational speeds from approximately 350 to 700 rpm.  There is an optimum balance between the degree of mixing by the pelletizer pin shaft, the water content of the wet pellets, and the time the pellets remain the pelletizer.  If the pellets are mixed too severely, the pellets can be broken.  The energy to the mass of pellets is generally fixed at a constant weight ratio of carbon black to water and can be measured by measuring the percent water in the wet pellets.  In the wet pelletizer the forces are similar to the forces in the dry pelletizer.  However, the driving force is provided by the centrifugal forces of the pelletizer shaft mixing the water in the agglomerates and driving the agglomerates to the wall of the pelletizer for rapid pellet formation.  There is again a balance between the degree of pelletization and the energy provided.  Too rapid mixing and too violent mixing result in the pellets being broken.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000016.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="17" xmlns="">
		<title>Quality of Collisions of Agglomerates</title>
		<content>Quality of Collisions of Agglomerates Rolling of the agglomerates on an incline Intimate mixing of agglomerates with water Rolling of the round agglomerates with other round agglomerates  Disintegration by gravity Disintegration by pins impacting pellets and pellets impacting the wall of the pelletizer Intimate mixing of powder with the round agglomerates Disintegration by fracture or abrasion Collisions should promote the growth, roundness, and densification of the agglomerates Good pelletizations is promoted by increasing the speed of intimate mixing of the powder and promoting rolling Minimize the destructive effects of abrasion and forceful effects that break the pellets </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Inside the pelletizing cylinders, it is important that the quality of collisions promotes the growth, roundness, and densification of the agglomerates in order to promote the quality of pellets that are desired.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;In a dry pelletizer, pelletization is promoted by:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; the intimate mixing of powder with round agglomerates&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; the rolling of the resulting agglomerates on the inclined surface or inside surface of the cylindrical drum and&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; the rolling of the resulting agglomerates with other round and smooth agglomerates&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Destruction of pellets is increased by:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; abrasion of agglomerates with rough agglomerates and&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; the fall of the pellets on the bed of pellets or surface of the drum by gravity impacts&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;In addition to the above effects, in the wet pelletizer, pelletization is also promoted by the intimate mixing of water with the powder.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The destruction of pellets is also increased by:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; the impact of the pellets by the pelletizer pins and&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; the impact of the pellets thrown to the surface of the cylindrical drum by the force of the pelletizer pins&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Ideally, we promote good pelletization by increasing the speed of intimate mixing of the powder and promoting rolling of the agglomerates.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;We need to minimize the destructive effects of abrasion and forceful effects that promote impacts that break the pellets.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Inside the pelletizing cylinders, it is important that the quality of collisions promotes the growth, roundness, and densification of the agglomerates in order to promote the quality of pellets that are desired.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;In a dry pelletizer, pelletization is promoted by &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;	the intimate mixing of powder with round agglomerates&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;	the rolling of the resulting agglomerates on the inclined 				surface or inside surface of the cylindrical drum and&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;	the rolling of the resulting agglomerates with other round and 			smooth agglomerates&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The destruction of pellets is increased by&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;	abrasion of agglomerates with rough agglomerates and&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;	fall of the pellets on the bed of pellets or surface of the drum 			by gravity impacts&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;In addition to the above effects In the wet pelletizer, pelletization is also promoted by&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;	The intimate mixing of water with the powder&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The destruction of pellets is also increased by the &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;	Impact of the pellets by the pelletizer pins&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;	Impact of the pellets thrown by the force of the pelletizer pins 			to the surface of the cylindrical drum&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Ideally, we promote good pelletization by increasing the speed of intimate mixing of the powder and promoting rolling of the agglomerates.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;We need to minimize the destructive effects of abrasion and forceful effects that promote impacts that break the pellets.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;	&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000017.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="18" xmlns="">
		<title>The Rolling Path of Agglomerates</title>
		<content> The Rolling Path of Agglomerates S ~ D × n × t = a constant    </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;The total length of the pellet's rolling path is a crucial parameter in a a cylindrical pelletizer. Rolling path controls all the pellet properties in a decisive way since this factor defines how the pellet effectively “rolls up” into pellets. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The mean total length of the pellet's rolling path, S,  is directly proportional to the pelletizer diameter, D, the number of revolutions, n,  and the mean residence time, t.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Although we see the impact of residence time again on the pellet properties, the rolling path shows the importance of the diameter of the pelletizer in creating a round, dense-packed, uniform, smooth and glossy pellet.  When we define the final pellet quality parameters required, we will again highlight the importance of this parameter.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;It is clear that the diameter of the pelletizer provides the inclined surface for travel of the pellet along the length of the pelletizer and this parameter is very critical in defining the total rolling path.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;If the pellet properties are expected to scale up due to volumetric rate from one operation to another, this factor must be kept constant during volumetric scaleups of equipment.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000018.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="19" xmlns="">
		<title>Liquid Effects</title>
		<content> Liquid Effects Liquid bridges form only where liquid and powder initially touch Wetting becomes faster with increasing rotational speed and smaller water droplets  </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;This graph shows the relationship between the particle diameter and the agglomerate strength for difference types of adhesive forces.  As you can see, as the forces move from simple van der Waal’s forces to those that are provided by liquid bridging or liquid necks, the particle strength of the agglomerate increases dramatically.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;If the wettability of a powder is good the liquid will spread evenly and form a film over the powder’s surface.  Liquid bridges will form between most contacting particles creating a strong and dense wet pellet.  Liquid bridges form only where liquid and powder initially touch.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The wetting in our process becomes faster and more homogeneous with increasing rotational speed of the wet pelletizer and smaller droplet size of the water. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;This table predicts that simple processes using only van der Waal’s forces for adhesion of particles such as dry pelletization will form much weaker pellets than those using liquid bridges such as those formed in wet pelletization.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000019.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="20" xmlns="">
		<title>END</title>
		<content>END  </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;This is the end of Module 7.1 Pelletization Theory&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000020.jpg"/>
	</section>
</document-metadata>
