<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<document-metadata version="1.0" xmlns="http://breeze.macromedia.com/">
	<document-info>
		<title>8.2 Indirect Rotary Dryer (Part 1)</title>
		<summary></summary>
		<author/>
		<keywords/>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000001.jpg"/>
		<view-link href="/viewer.swf?slide={{position}}" href-html5="/" href-swf="/viewer.swf?slide={{position}}"/>
	</document-info>
	<section type="slide" position="1" xmlns="">
		<title>8.2 Indirect Rotary Dryers</title>
		<content>8.2 Indirect Rotary Dryers Part 1 </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;This is Module 8.2, Indirect Rotary Dryers (Part I)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000001.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="2" xmlns="">
		<title>Drying</title>
		<content> Rotary Dryer  Wet Pellets ~ 40% - 60% water Dry Pellets  &amp;lt; 1% water Dryers Types Indirect Fired Rotary Dryers Indirect-Direct Fired Rotary Dryers Direct Fired Tray Dryers Fluidized Bed Dryers      Drying  ROTARY DRYER DRYER COMBUSTOR </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;After wet pellets are formed they range from about 40% to nearly 60% water or moisture.  The level of water in the wet pellets  depends directly on the structure of the carbon black.  These wet pellets must be dried to a level less than 1% since the customer does not want to purchase water and in some cases the water may cause defects in the polymer.  This removal of water is done using a dryer.  Several types of dryers are used in the industry including indirect fired rotary dryers, indirect-direct fired rotary dryers, direct fired tray dryers, and fluidized bed dryers which can be direct or indirect fired.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000002.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="3" xmlns="">
		<title>Drying</title>
		<content>Rotary Dryer – Indirect Fired Drying  Carbon Black wet pellets introduced at Inlet. Drum rotating at 3 to 6 rpm and virtually level. Hot gases surround the drying drum. Temperature of Carbon Black increased to 180 C. Carbon Black discharged through screeners and rotary valve to transport system to storage. Dryer Inlet Dryer Discharge   Rotary Dryer </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;In a rotary dryer, the carbon black is discharged from the pelletizer into the inlet, internal side of a drying drum which is rotating at a speed of from 3 to 6 rpm.  The drum is virtually horizontal with slopes to the discharge of less than 1%.  Hot gases surround the drum shell and the heat is transmitted internally into the carbon black bed which is tumbling inside the drying drum at levels of a few centimeters to levels of about 300 centimeters depending on the design and operating criteria of the dryer.  If this is a indirect-direct rotary dryer, hot gases from the combustor are also introduced into the drying drum to increase the heat transfer on the inside of the drum.  In some cases, the direct contact of combustion gas is detrimental to the quality of the carbon black.  Typically, indirect-direct heated dryers have more capacity for the same dimensions than indirect heated dryers.  The temperature of the bed of carbon black is measured and the carbon black temperature is controlled at temperatures that can confirm there is no water remaining in the carbon black pellets, usually about 180 degrees C.  In some cases the carbon black flows through discharge screens in the dryer to remove any large lumps or equipment such as broken vanes.  The carbon black is then discharged through a rotary valve which prevents leaks of air into the dryer drum and prevents leaks of steam into the bucket elevator and storage vessels.  Condensation of steam downstream of the dryer causes cakes and lumps of carbon black which are detrimental to the quality of the final product.  Screw or belt conveyors usually transport the dried carbon black from the bucket elevator to storage and packaging.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000003.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="4" xmlns="">
		<title>General Arrangement of Indirect Rotary Dryer</title>
		<content>General Arrangement of Indirect Rotary Dryer    DEVFHEATING LINE STACK Carbon  Black+H20 from Wet Pelletizer FIREBOXDRUM INLET SEALSOUTLET SEALS COMBUSTOR TAIL GAS FUELAIR Dry Carbon Black To Rotary Valve and Bucket Elevator </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Indirect rotary dryers are used widely in the carbon black industry.  These dryers are used to dry the wet pellets from the pelletizer without the carbon black coming into contact with combusted tail gases as in a direct-indirect dryer.   &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The features of this dryer are shown in the sketch.  Carbon black is discharged from the wet pelletizer into the hot zone of a rotating drum.  The drum is rotating at a speed range of 3 to 6 rpm.  The carbon black enters the drum at a temperature of approximately 40 degrees C (entry is shown on the left side of the sketch) and leaves the dryer through a chute (shown on the right side of the drawing).  The discharge has a rotary valve and discharges the carbon black to the bucket elevator.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The heat for drying the carbon black comes from a combustor that mixes tail gas with preheated combustion air and generates a flame with a temperature of approximately 1200 degrees C.  This flame is introduced into a dryer casing or firebox that surrounds the rotating drum.  The hot gases flow down the firebox until they exit a stack installed at the discharge end of the casing.  The casing itself is not as long as the rotating drum since supports for the trunnions and rotating drives of the drum cylinder must have room to support the drum while it is rotating uniformly in the stationary casing.  Hot steam which contains carbon black and some oxygen are discharged from the dryer drum using a dryer exhaust fan that goes to the dryer exhaust bag filter.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000004.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="5" xmlns="">
		<title>Typical Heat Balance for Indirect Rotary Dryer</title>
		<content>HEAT INPUT SOURCE: Tail gas combustion:                                  	87 to 90% Tail gas sensible heat at 232 °C: 	  		10 to 13% Air pre-heater  (Combustion air)  	 Supplemental Fuel (LPG, Natural gas, Oil)               0                                               HEAT USAGE AND LOSSES Heat transferred to water, CB, and purge gas:   	40 to 50% Stack loss:                                                            25 to 30% Walls and other losses:                                      	25 to 35% Air pre-heater  (Combustion air)  	 Typical Heat Balance for Indirect Rotary Dryer </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;The input of the heat from the combustor – the heat input source – comes from the fuels used in the combustor.  This is primarily tail gas in our operation.  Some combustors are also equipped to use other fuels such as natural gas or liquid fuels.  Since those fuels have to be purchased, we would prefer to use the tail gas only as a fuel.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Heat is used in the dryer to heat and evaporate the pelletizing water, heat the carbon black, heat the purge gas and heat the combustion air that is recycled back to the combustor.  About 40 – 50 percent of the heat added is used for these purposes.  There are are heat losses from equipment in the dryer amounting to  50 – 60 percent of the total heat input.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000005.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="6" xmlns="">
		<title>Dryer Design Recommendation</title>
		<content>Dryer Design Recommendation Heat   More Heat Water Evaporates  Agglomerate or Pellet Path Through Dryer 40º 60 calories 100ºC 540 calories Evaporate 1 kilogram of water +   100ºC 600 calories  </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;A dryer is rated on it’s capability to heat and evaporate the water added at the wet pelletizer.  Since the water content of each carbon black is different due to the structure or DBP of the wet pellet as discussed in the pelletizer module.  A carbon black with a high structure will have a lower capacity in a carbon black dryer than a carbon black with a low structure.  We will cover this in more detail later.  Therefore for consistency, it is better to define the capacity of a dryer based on the pelletizer water evaporation which is common in the industry.  From a physical heat requirement standpoint, it takes 1 calorie of heat to heat water 1 degree C and 540 calories to evaporate the water at 100 degrees C.  Therefore to heat one kilogram of water from 40 degrees C to 100 degrees C takes about 60 kilocalories and then to evaporate the water at 100 degrees C it takes 540 kilocalories per kilogram.   &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Therefore, to heat one kilogram of water from 40 degrees C which is approximately the inlet temperature of the wet carbon black and evaporate the water takes about 600 kilocalories.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000006.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="7" xmlns="">
		<title>Total Heating Requirements</title>
		<content>TO HEAT THE WATER: 		to evaporation temperature		 8% 		to evaporate					80% 		to heat purge gas				 5% 	  TOTAL							93% TO HEAT THE CARBON BLACK		 	  7% Total Heating Requirements Heating the water and carbon black </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;In the dryer drum, we are heating the water and the carbon black.  We will ignore any small amounts of air that might leak into the dryer.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The carbon black in the wet pellets has to be heated from the temperature of the wet pellets, 40 to 60 degrees C to the discharge temperature of the dryer –  160 to 200 degrees C.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The water in the wet pellets has to be heated from the temperature of the wet pellets, 40 to 60 degrees C to the evaporation temperature of water, 100 degrees C and then evaporated.  As we showed in the previous slide this takes about 600 kilocalories of heat per ton of water.  The evaporated water that is now in the form of steam in the dryer exhaust gases.  This steam also absorbs some additional heat (increases temperature) before exiting the dryer and going to the dryer exhaust gas filter..&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;We have identified the major heat requirements to dry the wet carbon black and increase its temperature to the final requirement to assure dry carbon black.  We will not go into further details but above we can show that the water requires 93% of the total heat requirements and the carbon black only 7%.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Therefore, in general, in the carbon black industry, dryers are capacity rated based on how much water they can dry regardless of the type carbon black.  If the carbon black type is used to gauge the rate, then that carbon black must be identified because any carbon black with a different structure will have a different water content, different water throughput and a different carbon black capacity.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The above is an example that we will use to determine the amount of tail gas required to dry the carbon black in our dryers.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;More exact heat data can be generated with a more thorough analysis of temperatures and gas compositions.  This information will be provided in a “tool box” calculation that can be used to estimate all these values.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000007.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="8" xmlns="">
		<title>Dryer Thermal Efficiency</title>
		<content>Dryer Thermal Efficiency For an Indirect Dryer we assume: Energy to heat and evaporate the water = 40%     Total heat input from tail gas/fuels Required energy input =  600 0.40 = 1500 kcal/kg H2O Required energy input = 600 0.60 = 1000 kcal/kg H2O  Factor affecting energy requirement Metallic Surface area of the dryer drum. The conductivity of material of construction. Effectiveness of the pins and lifter. Temperature and flow of hot gases to the dryer firebox. Heat losses from the dryer. For an Direct - Indirect Dryer we assume: Energy to heat and evaporate the water = 60%    Total heat input from tail gas/fuels If we use 60% efficiency, what will be the required energy input ? </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;The thermal efficiency of dryers are dependent upon the water evaporation rate as we discussed in the previous slide.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The energy required from the combustor from the tail gas to heat and evaporate that water is dependent upon many factors including the metallic surface area of the dryer drum, the conductivity of the materials of construction of the dryer drum, the effectiveness of the pins and lifters installed on the surface of the drum, the temperature and flow of the hot gases to the dryer firebox, and heat losses from the dryer.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;By experiment the dryers are rated by what is usually called drier thermal efficiencies which are calculated by the percentage of the total heat input from the tail gas and fuel that is required as energy to evaporate the water.  For the indirect fired dryers we have on Lines 3 and 4,  this efficiency ranges from about 35% to 55%.  For the direct-indirect dryers we have on Lines 1 and 2, the efficiency ranges from 55 – 70%.  In the following example, we will use an efficiency of 40% to estimate the heat input required from the tail gas to heat the carbon black in an indirect dryer.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;We will use the 600 kilocalories of heat from the previous calculation to heat water from 40 degrees C to steam at 100 degrees C  Since the efficiency of the dryer is 40%, we will determine the required energy input by dividing the 600 kilocalories by .40 (40% in decimal form).  We get an energy requirement from the tail gas of 1500 kilocalories per kilogram of water.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;If we use 60% for the efficiency of a Direct-Indirect Dryer what will be the required energy input? &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The answer is 1000 &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;kcalories&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; =/kilogram of water.  Notice that the tail gas energy required is less than that of an indirect fired dryer.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000008.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="9" xmlns="">
		<title>Tail Gas Heating Value</title>
		<content> Tail Gas Heating Value   </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;These are estimates of the heating value for tail gas in kilocalories per cubic meter for different products we produce and for a range of reactor yields.  The heating value for N660 is about 900 kilocalories per cubic meter and the value for N220 is about 700 kilocalories per cubic meter of tail gas.  Normally, the tail gas from two operating lines are mixed for use in the dryer combustors.  With these values, we can now easily estimate the amount of tail gas in cubic meters that we will require to dry the wet pellets of one of our products in our dryers.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000009.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="10" xmlns="">
		<title>Tail Gas Requirement to Dry Carbon Black</title>
		<content>Tail Gas Requirement to Dry Carbon Black For an Indirect Dryer we assume: Energy to heat and evaporate the water = 40%    Total heat input from tail gas/fuels REQUIRED ENERGY INPUT = 600/.4 = 1500 kcalories/kilogram H2O   For the above example, let’s assume we are using a mixed tail gas with a calorific value of 750 kcalories/ Nm³  in the dryer combustor above. Then 1500 kilocalories/kg = 2.0 Nm³ of tail gas/kilogram H2O          750 kilocalories/Nm³ If we are producing a carbon black with 55% water content in the wet pellets at a production rate of 2500 kg/hr,  the TAIL GAS REQUIREMENT for the dryer combustor can be estimated as:  2500 kg/h CB x (0.55 kg H₂0 /0.45 kg CB) = 3056 kg/h H₂0 x 2.0 Nm³ tail gas/kg H₂0 = 6111 Nm³ of tail gas/h  </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Let’s again assume that the drying efficiency is 40%.  In practice, we will determine the exact efficiency using actual data from our production runs.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The required energy input for 40% efficiency will be 1500 kilocalories per kilogram of water.  We can use the previous graph to determine the calorific value of the tail gas.  Based on the probability of having a mixture of gases from two production lines, let’s assume that the tail gas has a caloric value of 750 kilocalories per Normal cubic meter.  By dividing the requirement of 1500 kilocalories per kilogram of water by the tail gas heating value of 750 kilocalories per Normal cubic meter of tail gas, we get a requirement of 2.0 Normal cubic meters of tail gas required to dry each kilogram of water contained in the carbon black.  By our measurement of the pellet moisture, we will assume that the pellet moisture of the carbon black is 55%.  If the carbon black throughput to the dryer is 2500 kilograms per hour, the water content will be at a ratio of 0.55 kg of water to 0.45 kilogram of carbon black or 3056 kilograms of water.  Multiplying that rate by the tail gas consumption of 2.0 Normal cubic meters of tail gas , we arrive at an estimate of 6111  Normal cubic meters per hour of tail gas to dry 2500 kilograms of carbon black. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000010.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="11" xmlns="">
		<title>Combustor Arrangement</title>
		<content>TAIL GAS COMBUSTOR Combustor Arrangement     FIREBOX                        R         TIC        CONTROL LOOP TAIL GAS AIR FUEL 1000 TO 1100 °C  O₂I  </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;The tail gas combustor on the dryer provides the heat to the firebox or casing by generating a flame using a fuel such as tail gas with preheated combustion air.  This flame will generally be controlled and enter the firebox at levels between 1000 degrees C to 1100 degrees C.  Usually a fixed ratio of tail gas to combustion air is used to generate the maximum flame required and the ratio controller (R) is set to maintain this flame at a set temperature regardless of tail gas throughput.  Normally, only if the tail gas calorific value changes due to changes in mixes of the tail gas is this ratio changed.  In more advanced control systems, the tail gas and fuel rates are determined by the water input into the dryer.  We will discuss this aspect of control later.  An oxygen meter is also provided to determine the excess oxygen in the combusted tail gas which allows the flame to be optimized.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000011.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="12" xmlns="">
		<title>Combusted Gas Exhaust System </title>
		<content>Combusted Gas Exhaust System&amp;#x0A;                   PIC  &amp;lt; 0 mBar Draft Stack Outlet of Firebox Combustor Inlet  of Firebox Pressure Indicator - Controller ROTATING DRUM    Typical Arrangement </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;The exhaust system of the dryer combustor gas is typically a draft stack.  This is a stack that is tall enough to exhaust the hot gases from the dryer without creating any positive pressures in the dryer casing or firebox.  The pressure at the inlet of the casing should be controlled at slightly negative pressures.  The stack inlet should be designed to provide low pressure losses at maximum flows of combusted gases.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000012.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="13" xmlns="">
		<title>Purge Gas Exhaust System</title>
		<content>Purge Gas Exhaust System   TIC232 °CPIC Dryer Exhaust Gas Fan  Rotating Drum To Dryer Exhaust Bag Filter  &amp;lt; 0 mBar Combustor Inlet  of Firebox Firebox Draft Stack Dryer Exhaust Fan   &amp;lt;0 </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Inside the dryer rotating drum, the gas is primarily water in the form of steam.  There is also some carbon black dust that is entrained in the steam and air from leakages into the drum from the atmosphere through the seals.  These gases must be exhausted from the drum and cleaned before exhausting to the atmosphere.  A dryer exhaust fan is used to convey these gases from the rotating drum to the dryer exhaust bag filter.    The gases inside the dryer are heated by the carbon black stream and the dryer wall.  If these gases are too low temperature, they will condense as water vapor.  Then plugging occurs in the bag filter.  Therefore, we must maintain the temperature of these gases higher than the condensation point of the mixed gas stream.  A temperature is selected in the temperature indicator – controller and if the gas temperature exiting the dryer is too low, combustion gases from the firebox or the combustor directly are added to the gas stream to heat the low temperature gases to a minimum to eliminate the possibility of condensation.  In this example a set point of 232 degrees C is set as the minimum temperature.  Also, the pressure of the gases in the rotating drum must be controlled as low as possible to prevent air leaking into the drum from the seals.  Also the pressure (vacuum) must be controlled to prevent carbon black laden gases from the dryer drum leaking to the atmosphere.  Generally, this can be performed by operating at a low vacuum in the dryer inlet.  If the vacuum at this point is too extreme – that is a high vacuum -, the vacuum will induce the flow of powder and pellets through the pelletizer so fast that there will be insufficient residence time to pelletize and round the pellets properly.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000013.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="14" xmlns="">
		<title>Internal Fittings</title>
		<content>INTERNAL FITTINGS DISTRIBUTION (TYPICAL FOR A 60 FT DRUM) Internal Fittings 03’60’48’ to 50’PlowsStraight vanesZigzag vanes 100 mm (4”)150 mm (6”)t = 6.25mm (¼”)25mm (1”)½”#/row = 3 x drum dia.STRAIGHT VANES 150 to 200 mm (6 to 8”)t =6.25 mm (¼”) h =100 mm (1 ½”) ½”)ZIGZAG OR RIPPLE VANES     </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;At the beginning of the dryer on the left hand side of the sketch, the wet carbon black pellets from the pelletizer have to be moved away from the dryer inlet to the main heating zone.  Metal fittings called plows or inlet spirals are generally used to convey the carbon black.  After this, internal vanes or fittings have been added to the inside of the rotating drum to enhance the stirring of the carbon black so the pellets are moved away from the wall and mixed as the drum rotates.  The straight vanes at the beginning two thirds of the drum heating area,  that is within the firebox, also add a small additional surface area that transfers heat by conduction to the carbon black pellets.  The final part of the drum can be fitted with the straight vanes or zigzag (ripple) vanes that are used to convey the black to the discharge of the dryer drum.  At the latter part of the dryer, all of the pelletizing water has been removed and the carbon black is being heated primarily from direct contact with the dryer shell.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;There are specific instructions about how to weld these vanes to the dryer drum internal wall to prevent stress to the drum wall.  The welding stress along with mechanical stress and heat cause most dryer drum wall failures.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000014.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="15" xmlns="">
		<title>Dryer Drum Pins</title>
		<content> Dryer Drum Pins  External Pins on the Dryer Drum  Length of Firebox  Inlet Outlet     </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Another feature that adds to the heat transfer from the combustor gasses to the dryer drum wall is the addition of cylindrical pins to the first part of the drum where there are wet pellets.  These 10 x 80 mm pins are stud welded to the drum wall on 50 mm centers with each row offset from the neighboring row.  The offset is made to minimize stress on the dryer drum wall which can lead to cracks.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The color photo to the right bottom shows how the pins cool the drum wall where the heat is transferred to the wet pellets..&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000015.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="16" xmlns="">
		<title>Dryer Control – Typical Scheme</title>
		<content>Dryer Control – Typical Scheme                     m   .                   Combustion Chamber        carbon black inlet  stack FICpelletizing water     carbon black outlet TIC      QIC TIC  O2    US                     FIC FFIC FFIC FIC combustion air 1 tailgas combustion  air 2 fuel Stack gas temperature Carbon Black Temperatures      TIC TIC1 TIC2  Pyrometers TICn   TICn TICnPurge Gas  </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;The simplest indirect fired dryer control scheme monitors the combusted gas exit temperature from the dryer casing, sometimes called the “stack” temperature and the operator manually adjusts the combustor flow rates of combustor air and tail gas to increase or decrease the exit temperature to maintain a constant temperature of the carbon black exiting the dryer.  The operator must then be careful not to increase or decrease the flow rate of the combustor too fast or the carbon black can overheat and catch on fire or can remain high in water content.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Initially, Lines 3 and 4 will have a scheme such as the one shown in this sketch to control the carbon black temperature.  Because the resulting carbon black discharge temperature (T-I-C-1) will lag the heat input at the inlet of the dryer, an algorithm will have to be custom developed to take this lag time into effect along with the other synergies of the dryer system.  This can be installed and tested during the initial commissioning of the dryer on startup.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Most carbon black control schemes for the combustor provide ratio control to control the flow of combustion air to the tail gas and fuel flow so when either is changed the proper amount of air for control of the temperature is at a constant combustion ratio. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;More elaborate control schemes integrate different parameters into an equation that provides an external setpoint for controlling the heat input to the dryer from the combustor with the water flow rate and carbon black flow rate into the dryer.  We will explore the design and operation of these elaborate control schemes outside this course.  The algorithms used may include the following parameters:  shell temperatures from pyrometers installed along the dryer firebox, firebox gas temperatures, purge gas exhaust temperatures, and dryer temperatures at more points inside the dryer – such as TIC2.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000016.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="17" xmlns="">
		<title>Dryer Control – Temperature Control</title>
		<content>Dryer Control – Temperature Control FICpelletizing water Two thermocouples in carbon black Temperature &amp;gt; 150 C Maintain thermocouples accuracy                     m   .                   combustion chamber         carbon black inlet  stack      carbon black outlet TIC TIC      QIC TIC  O2    US                     FIC FFIC FFIC FIC combustion air 1 tailgas combustion  air 2 fuel offgas temperature carbon black temperature      TIC TIC2  TIC1 </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;The carbon black temperature should be measured inside the dryer drum by a thermocouple installed about one meter inside the drum – this is just inside the heated area of the firebox.  This is typically the thermocouple temperature used to determine if the carbon black has high moisture.  Typically, carbon black temperatures below 150 degrees C indicate the carbon black may still have water in the pellet.  A second thermocouple is normally installed further from the discharge.  This thermocouple can alert the operator if a dramatic change in temperature occurs and allows some time to respond to these changes in temperature by changing the combustion conditions to add more heat before the carbon black reaches the discharge thermocouple.  If the temperature of the carbon black is measured too close to the discharge or after discharge, the carbon black temperature is a less accurate measurement of the moisture content due to the cooling effects in this zone. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The thermocouples must always be embedded in the bed of carbon black pellets and not be in the gas stream above the bed of carbon black.  We want to measure the temperature of the carbon black, not the not gases.  Usually a rigid supporting structure is installed in the dryer drum to make sure the thermocouple locations remain fixed properly.  If temperature errors are noted, the thermocouples need to be inspected and repaired.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000017.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="18" xmlns="">
		<title>Dryer Control – Temperature Control</title>
		<content>Dryer Control – Temperature Control                     m   .                   combustion chamber        carbon black inlet  stack      carbon black outlet TIC TIC      QIC TIC  O2    US                     FIC FFIC FFIC FIC combustion air 1 tailgas combustion  air 2 fuel offgas temperature Carbon Black Temperatures      TIC TIC2 TIC1   AIR  180 ᴼ C FICpelletizing water Low Temperatures Wet Black High Temperatures Hot Black to Customer Breakdown of Binders and Additives Oxidation and Surface Effects </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;The carbon black temperature – T-I-C-1 should always be in control in the range of 160 degrees C to 200 degrees C.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Temperatures below 150 degrees C can lead to a product with high moisture content.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;High temperatures in the dryer may result in hot black being shipped to customers, damage to the packaging materials and fires, including fires in the customer’s warehouse.  High carbon black temperatures can cause the binder in the carbon black to decompose and cause deterioration of the pellet properties, such as pellet hardness, and lead to fines in the final product.  If certain chemicals are added to specialty products, these may compose when they experience high temperatures.  The impact should be known prior to adding these chemicals and proper safeguards should be used.  High temperatures can also lead to oxidation of the carbon black which may cause the surface effects we discussed in the module on surface chemistry.  There may be times when we want to raise the temperature to cause oxidation of the carbon black, but these conditions must be carefully and uniformly controlled.  Many plants install an air inlet at the discharge of the dryer to control the air to oxidize the carbon black.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000018.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="19" xmlns="">
		<title>Dryer Control Basics</title>
		<content>FORMULA FOR CONSTANT DRYER TEMPERATURE = CONSISTANT WATER FLOW TO DRYER  = CONSISTANT CARBON BLACK FLOW TO PELLETIZER/DRYER = CONSISTENT FLOW OF CARBON BLACK FROM THE SURGE BIN  = MINIMUM UPSTREAM DISRUPTION OF BAG FILTER FLOW + = NO CARBON BLACK IN UNMEASURED STREAMS + = STABLE REACTOR CONTROL  Dryer Control Basics WHEN THIS IS ACHIEVED THE SIMPLEST CONTROL LOOP WILL PRODUCE GOOD CONTROL. </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;The most important element for control of the dryer is the consistent flow of carbon black and water to the dryer.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;We discussed this aspects of good pelletization.  Controlling the dryer temperature is consistent with that type philosophy.  No control system will work if the variation in the upstream flows is too great or fast for the control scheme to compensate.  Therefore, to achieve good temperature control in the dryer, we need to have consistent flow of carbon black and water through the wet pelletizer.  This means good control from the surge bin which means carbon black flows from the main bag filter.  There must be no carbon black from unmeasured streams.  Also, the fresh black from the reactor needs to be controlled in a narrow range.  No uncontrolled shutdowns of the reactors can be tolerated.  When stability is achieved in these areas, the carbon black dryer temperature can be easily controlled.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000019.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="20" xmlns="">
		<title>END</title>
		<content>END  </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;This is the end of Module 8.2 Indirect Rotary Dryers (Part I)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000020.jpg"/>
	</section>
</document-metadata>
