<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<document-metadata version="1.0" xmlns="http://breeze.macromedia.com/">
	<document-info>
		<title>2.2 Form and Morphology</title>
		<summary></summary>
		<author/>
		<keywords/>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000001.jpg"/>
		<view-link href="/viewer.swf?slide={{position}}" href-html5="/" href-swf="/viewer.swf?slide={{position}}"/>
	</document-info>
	<section type="slide" position="1" xmlns="">
		<title>2.2 Form and Morphology</title>
		<content>2.2 Form and Morphology </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;This is the module&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; 2.2 Form and Morphology.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Chemical morphology is the &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;shape&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; and size of a specific body, the texture or topography of a surface and the &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;distribution&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; of phases in a material.  In this section we will review the terms and methods used to classify carbon black in its forms as a particle, an aggregate and/or an agglomerate.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000001.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="2" xmlns="">
		<title>Morphology: Form</title>
		<content>Particles  Aggregates Agglomerates Pellets Morphology: Form </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Morphology describes the many forms of carbon black from the smallest entity called a particle to the largest we experience as a pellet or bead.  Once you have an understanding of the morphology of carbon black then other properties, such as those for aggregates, agglomerates, and pellets will flow from these fundamentals.  In producing carbon black we will learn how we can control both particle and aggregate size.  However, first let's explore what we mean by the morphological terms we have mentioned.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000002.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="3" xmlns="">
		<title>Carbon Black Formation</title>
		<content>Carbon Black Formation        </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;A simple way to mimic the lampblack process is to take a porcelain crucible and place it in the flame of a burning candle.  The soot or lampblack will form on the surface of the crucible as shown in this drawing.  What we have is a hydrocarbon source (the candle wax), a high temperature (the burning of part of the wax as it vaporizes from the wick) and the collection of the lampblack on the surface of the crucible.  The crucible simply cools part of the flame before the wax has time to completely burn up into carbon dioxide and water.  Now, let us look at the layer very close to the crucible.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000003.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="4" xmlns="">
		<title>Carbon Black Formation: Details</title>
		<content>Carbon Black Formation:&amp;#x0A;Details    Expanded  View Expand This Area    Particles Aggregates Agglomerates </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;We will schematically expand the layer so that we can visualize what is happening to the unburned carbon just before it sticks to the surface of the crucible.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The forms of carbon which still contain a little hydrogen have very low vapor pressure.  This condenses in to spheres called particles.  These particles bump into each other and fuse together to form what is called an aggregate.  The chemical bonding within an aggregate between particles is called covalent bonding and is very strong.  It is very difficult to break apart an aggregate We will discuss aggregate formation in more detail in the next few slides.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;As the aggregates cool off, there is a lack of reacting carbon in this region to form more particles or to cause fusion of two aggregates  into a larger one.  Also, at this point aggregates come together but do not strongly bond to form agglomerates.  The attraction among aggregates in an agglomerate is due to what is called Van der Waal's forces.  However, these weak attractions can be overcome with simple mixing of the carbon black in a customer's matrix whether it is water, oil, plastic or rubber. Hence agglomerates break down into aggregates in the customer's matrix.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000004.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="5" xmlns="">
		<title>Lampblack Aggregate: A Micrograph</title>
		<content>Lampblack Aggregate:&amp;#x0A;A Micrograph   Not round as in drawings  Average made from a range of sizes Aggregate Average = 0.1 mm 0.2mm </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Pictured here is an actual photo of an aggregate of lampblack taken with an electron microscope.  We cannot observe the individual particles and the aggregate with our naked eye.  All we will see in a carbon black is a small black speck.  In this electron micrograph, you will immediately notice that the nodules which make up the aggregate are not exactly round as we will picture them in drawings.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The particles that make up lampblack average around 0.1 micrometer. The particles of the large aggregate in the foreground are in the range of 0.2 micrometer.   &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Note the much smaller aggregate with much smaller particles in the upper right hand corner of the micrograph that are also part of the distribution of particles that define this carbon black.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;When we say that the average is 0.1 micrometer, there is quite a range in the size that makes up this average particle size.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000005.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="6" xmlns="">
		<title>Carbon Black Particle</title>
		<content>Carbon Black Particle      Particle Impacts Surface Area and Chemistry Can be controlled by modern furnace process </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Here is another view of an aggregate of carbon black which has been pictured with different contrast.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;It is very important that you are quite clear as to what makes up a particle of carbon black.  Again, we picture it here and indicate the diameter by the distance of the arrow on the particle label. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The particle size of the carbon black will directly impact surface area and chemistry, which we will explore later.  However, it is important to note that particle size is one of the two (2) most important properties that can be controlled in modern furnace processes.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000006.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="7" xmlns="">
		<title>Particle Size:  Function of Reaction Temperature</title>
		<content> Particle Size:  Function of Reaction Temperature   How do you control  the number of  particles that stick together to form  an aggregate? How is particle size controlled in a reactor? </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;How is particle size controlled in a reactor?  Simply stated, it is the reaction temperature that dictates the particle size (and surface area) as we see in the graph here.  As the temperature of reaction increases, the particle size decreases.  As the particle size decreases, the surface area increases.  Well, we are getting ahead of ourselves so we will stick to the form (morphology) for the present.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;If this is how you can control particle size then how do you control the number of particles that stick together to from an aggregate?  The next slide will illustrate the proposed mechanism&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000007.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="8" xmlns="">
		<title>Aggregate Size: Control with Potassium</title>
		<content>Aggregate Size:&amp;#x0A;Control with Potassium  K+ +K     Repulsion </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;As the aggregate forms, particles collide with and stick to it at the high reaction temperature.  However, to keep particles from bonding together, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;kalium&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; (or better know to us as potassium with a symbol of K) is added to the oil before the reaction takes place.  This will be illustrated on the next slide.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The potassium ionizes to form a positive ion on the surfaces of the particles and forming aggregates.  If a positively charged particle and  aggregate approach each other, they are repelled. This repulsion of like charges is similar to how the same poles of two magnets repel each other.  As more potassium is added, the more likely the surfaces of both the particle and the forming aggregate will have a positive charge and not bond to each other.  This reduces the structure of the carbon black. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000008.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="9" xmlns="">
		<title>Formation Zone</title>
		<content>Formation Zone  Potassium (K) injected with the oil Formation Zone </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;First, we add potassium to the oil before it reaches the carbon black formation zone.    Typically, the potassium must be in a solution, such as potassium acetate, dissolved in water which is then added to the oil.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The formation zone is where the oil (a hydrocarbon) is cracked by the high temperature and reforms into particles which collide together to make aggregates.  Again, the repulsion of positively charge surfaces keep particles from attaching to each other.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Once the aggregates cool slightly they will not continue to bond with each other. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000009.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="10" xmlns="">
		<title>Structure</title>
		<content>LowModerate Branching Extensive BranchingHigh Permanent Structure Structure </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;We have seen in previous slides how to control the number of particles that bond together to form an aggregate.  Now, let's see the impact of that control on tests to measure structure.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;If you have fewer particles per aggregate then you have less branching and this is called low structure.  And with higher number of particles per aggregate, you have high structure or more branching. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;When we are talking about the structure resulting from the aggregates, this is called permanent structure.  The reason for this is that it is very difficult to break an aggregate due to it's covalent bonds between the particles fused together.  With this difficulty comes permanence.  This is the structure that most customers will see impacting their application.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000010.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="11" xmlns="">
		<title>Structure from Agglomeration </title>
		<content>Structure from Agglomeration&amp;#x0A;        More pelletizing energy =     tighter packing Secondary or Temporary </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Now, let us discuss the temporary structure resulting from agglomerates.  As you can see in this illustration, we have identical size and shape aggregates forming an agglomerate.  Obviously, we would never have identical aggregates but it helps with the illustration.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;As the aggregates come together, they have spaces between them that are larger than the spaces within the aggregates branches.  This is the secondary or temporary structure.  It is temporary in the sense that it is a function of how much energy is used to form the agglomerate.  The more energy added, such as in pelletization, the tighter the packing and hence the less temporary structure.  This effect can actually be measured and that is exactly what we will discuss next in the tests used for structure.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000011.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="12" xmlns="">
		<title>Tests for Structure: Aggregate Branching</title>
		<content>Disadvantages Tests for Structure:&amp;#x0A;Aggregate Branching Advantages Quick Precise Automated Machine Requires standard reference black to calibrate Affected by densification history Affected by individual pellet hardness and distribution 1) OAN 2) COAN Measures the amount of oil needed to fill the  spaces within agglomerates and aggregates </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Let's look at three tests used to determine the structure of carbon black.  Two tests which you will become familiar with are the oil absorption number, O-A-N and the compressed oil absorption number,  C-O-A-N.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The O-A-N test measures the amount of oil needed to fill the spaces within aggregates and agglomerates.  It is a quick and precise method that uses an automated machine to make this determination.  The disadvantages are that the test needs a standard reference black to calibrate.   In other words it is not a direct measurement.  It is affected by densification as we mentioned earlier when discussing agglomerates and the test can also be impacted to a slight degree by individual pellet hardness and distribution.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000012.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="13" xmlns="">
		<title>Tests for Structure: Aggregate Branching</title>
		<content>Tests for Structure:&amp;#x0A;Aggregate Branching Eliminates Densification History Quick Precise Automated Machine More Steps than OAN More Equipment Advantages Disadvantages 2) COAN Carbon black is subjected to a crush pressure of 24,000psi four times before the test is run. </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;COAN is the same as OAN except the carbon black is subjected to a crush pressure of 24,000 psi four times before the test is run.  This helps eliminate the densification history of the carbon black especially in the pelletizer.  The main drawbacks are the extra steps in crushing the carbon black and the equipment used to do this.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000013.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="14" xmlns="">
		<title>Oil Absorption Number Instrument</title>
		<content>  Mixing Blades Oil Absorption Number Instrument </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Many of you have seen this instrument in the plant labs.  The OAN instrument is used throughout the world on virtually every carbon black line to determine the structure of carbon black.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The system consists of three key components.  There is a precise oil delivery system, a mixing bowl and a torque sensor.  The oil is slowly added to the mixing bowl containing a weighed amount of carbon black - usually 20 grams.  As the oil fills up the spaces in the aggregates and agglomerates, the torque increases.  This is the same as when adding milk to a recipe of pancakes.  The dry ingredients absorb the milk as you stir.  The mixture becomes stiffer until the excess milk thins out the recipe. In our OAN instrument, a sensor picks up the increase in torque on the mixing blades and cuts the oil addition off when a preset torque is reached.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000014.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="15" xmlns="">
		<title>Carbon Black Bulk Forms</title>
		<content> Carbon Black Bulk Forms  Powder  Dry Pellets Wet Pellets Specialty Grades Form as it comes out  of the reactors with  with some compression  for shipping </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;The morphology of carbon black which consumers actually see can be either in the form of powder, dry pellets or wet pellets that have been dried.  Most rubber grades are wet beads which are pelletized with water and dried in a dryer.  This is the form marketed by Himadri.     Many specialty grades are powders and dry pellets. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Powder form is how the carbon black comes out of the reactor even though there has usually been some type of compression or densification so that it is easier to package and ship.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000015.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="16" xmlns="">
		<title>Dry Pellet Form</title>
		<content> Dry Pellet Form   Dry Pellets Dry Pellets friable, small  pellets easier to handle than powders; less dust Rolled Less dense Easily broken </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Dry pellets are carbon black powder that has been rolled in a cylinder so that round pellets have formed by weak forces between the carbon black agglomerates.  These pellets tend to be less dense and easily broken.  These pellets tend to mix easier in the application of a customer and are preferred by customers who have simple incorporation methods for mixing the carbon black in the liquid or polymer.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000016.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="17" xmlns="">
		<title>Wet Pellet Form</title>
		<content>Highly densified pellets Best for use in severe bulk handling systems to prevent attrition Moderate to high viscosity systems required for dispersion Wet Pellet Form  Wet Beads Wet with water and possibly binder  Dried Very hard and can survive severe handling Wet Pellets </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Lastly, but most importantly are the wet pellets. “ Wet pellet” is a term which refers to the process of pelletization.  We pellets have been formed by densifying the carbon black in a pelletizer where water is added but then dried to a low water content in a dryer.  These pellets can be quite hard and survive the most severe handling systems.  Also, customers who use these type pellets must have aggressive mixing processes to mix the carbon black into their liquid or polymer.  Himadri produces this form of carbon black pellets, so these processes will be discussed in more detail later in the training program.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000017.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="18" xmlns="">
		<title>Pellet Property Tests</title>
		<content>Pellet Property Tests Pour Density Fines Content Attrition Pellet Size Distribution Individual Pellet Crush Strength Pellet Hardness Suitability of Bulk Handling,  Shipping Final Product&amp;#x0A; Measures Carbon Black for: </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;There are numerous tests to characterize carbon black pellets. Listed on this slide are typical tests performed for quality control and pre-shipment quality assurance.  Each test tells something different about the pellets.  These properties can have an impact on handling, shipping and performance in the final product.  We will go into a little more detail for pour density and pellet size distribution to complete this module; however, let's briefly describe each of the other tests.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;Fines&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; is simply the fraction of the carbon black that will pass through a 125 micron screen after a 5 minute shaking process.  Fines can make both handling and incorporating into the final product more difficult.  The results are reported in % of the original sample.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;Attrition&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; is just how much more fines can be generated over time after the initial fines are removed.  In this test the fines are removed and additional shaking is carried on for 15 minutes.  The additional fines generated are called the  “attrition”.  This has implications for shipping and handling.  As more fines are generated, the carbon black becomes more difficult to handle and incorporate into the customer's product.  The results are report in % of the original sample.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;Individual pellet crush &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;strength or &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;pellet hardness &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;gives a good indication as to how easily the product will disperse in our customer's matrix. This test can be performed manually or automatically on a standard size of pellets and the results are reported in grams-force or milli-newtons.  The softer the pellet, the easier to incorporate in the customer’s matrix unless too much fines are generated.  If too many fines are present, they can float out of the mixed medium such as the rubber, plastic, oil, or water.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000018.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="19" xmlns="">
		<title>Pour Density</title>
		<content> Low Structure Carbon Black High Structure  Carbon Black N358 N326 Pour Density Low Structure : Higher Density </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Let's now apply some of the principles that we have learned earlier in this module to predict the pour density of carbon black.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;On the left side is an illustration of a low structure carbon black such as N326.  With the lower number of particles per aggregate, the pellets compact more and are more dense.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The right side of the drawing shows how a high structure carbon black will pack.  With more particles per aggregate the ability to pack more densely has been reduced.  A higher structure carbon black such as an N358 will have a lower pour density than the N326 even though the particle size, and hence, surface areas are similar.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000019.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="20" xmlns="">
		<title>Pellet Size Distribution</title>
		<content>Pellet Size Distribution  Screen Sizes        Sieve opening (micron)   10 mesh				2000   18 mesh				1000   35 mesh				  500   60 mesh				  250 120 mesh				  125 Pan (-120 mesh)              	-125 Mixture of pellet sizes  How Big? How Uniform? Visual: 	How round in each fraction. 	How much fracture in each fraction. </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;The pellet size distribution test tells us &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;how big &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;the pellets are and &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;how uniform &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;are the size of the pellets.  In the photo of carbon black pellets above you can see that there is a mixture of pellets of different sizes.  The pellet size distribution tests separates these pellets into different size fractions by passing the mixture through &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;different screen sizes &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;as shown above.   The test is performed by putting a fixed weight of well-mixed carbon black pellets on a set of decreasing mesh-size screens, shaking the carbon black for a fixed time and finally measuring the amount of carbon black found on each screen.  The measurement is reported as the percent fraction of each screen and the remaining fraction in the final collection pan.  If we &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;look at each fraction&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;, we can determine the relative amount of &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;round pellets &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;and the relative degree of &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;fractured pellets &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;in the mixture.  Large pellets will not incorporate in the customer’s mixture as well as small pellets.  Small pellets can become dust in the customer’s factory.  Therefore the best pellets are round, average about 500 micron in diameter, and have a narrow size distribution.  The pellet size distribution test can give us an impression of how the pelletization process is working and also how the upstream equipment and processes are breaking the pellets upstream of the sampling location.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;As we have noted, the properties of pellets are very important to our customers.  They may not understand what is happening in our processes to produce pellets with specific characteristics; however, depending on the customer's handling and mixing systems and the matrix in which it is being placed, they are impacted by pellet properties.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000020.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="21" xmlns="">
		<title>END</title>
		<content>END </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;This is the end&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; of module 2.2 Form and Morphology.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000021.jpg"/>
	</section>
</document-metadata>
