<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<document-metadata version="1.0" xmlns="http://breeze.macromedia.com/">
	<document-info>
		<title>2.5 Applications</title>
		<summary></summary>
		<author/>
		<keywords/>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000001.jpg"/>
		<view-link href="/viewer.swf?slide={{position}}" href-html5="/" href-swf="/viewer.swf?slide={{position}}"/>
	</document-info>
	<section type="slide" position="1" xmlns="">
		<title>2.5 Applications </title>
		<content>2.5 Applications   </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;This is the &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;module 2.5 &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Carbon Black Applications.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;This module will explore the variety of end use applications of carbon blacks.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000001.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="2" xmlns="">
		<title>Approximate Market Share by Volume</title>
		<content>Approximate Market Share by Volume 70% - Tire  Tread  Sidewall  Bead  Etc. 20% - Non-Tire Rubber  Hoses  Belts  Weather-stripping  Gaskets/Seals  Etc. 10% - Specialty  Plastics  Inks  Others </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Most carbon black is used in the rubber in tires.  The next largest use is for non-tire rubber products.  Adding both rubber product areas together  we see that about 90% of all carbon black goes into rubber products.  Approximately 10% goes into plastics, inks, and other applications.  We will now explore each of these major application areas in more detail.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000002.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="3" xmlns="">
		<title>Largest Volume Application:  </title>
		<content>Largest Volume Application:&amp;#x0A;&amp;#x0A;      TIRE </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;The largest volume of carbon black goes into rubber which is used in tires.  All types of tires are manufactured using carbon black - from automobiles, to bicycles, to motor bikes and even the largest off the road tires used in mining and construction.  Even the space shuttle had carbon black in it’s landing tires.  Although the profit margins are relatively low on most tire carbon blacks, this is a very important application for the total profitability of the industry.  Also, because of the competitive nature of these products, it results in our making sure that our plants are running cost-effectively.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000003.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="4" xmlns="">
		<title>Ultra High Performance Passenger Tire</title>
		<content>Ultra High Performance Passenger Tire   Steel Belts Liner Sidewall Complex engineered product Minimum of three different grades  Tread: N110, N200, N300  Sidewalls: N500, N600, N700  Steel belts: N300 (N326)  Liner: N700 Tread </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;An automobile tire is a complex engineered product.  It must do many things at once: long wear, low heat buildup,  stable at high speeds, cushion the ride, brake, accelerate, corner and all this while providing a safe and cost-effective ride.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;There are a minimum of three different grades of carbon black in an automobile tire and some may have three or four more.  An N100, N200 or N300 grade is used to reinforce the tread.  The sidewalls must not create too much heat; therefore, they will contain an N500, N600 or N700 grade.  The steel belts shown here must first be coated with a rubber so that the metal bonds to the rubber and the other layers when the tire is cured.  This is called the “skim stock” and is made of a rubber that usually contains an N300 type carbon black.  Often this carbon black is N326.  The interior liner must not let the air out and will have a large particle carbon black such as an N700 grade.  Also, this larger particle black reduces heat buildup in the liner versus a higher surface area carbon black.  There can be other rubber compounds with specific purposes requiring similar carbon blacks already mentioned.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Every type tire has a unique design with customized rubber compounds using the carbon blacks that will deliver the required performance.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000004.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="5" xmlns="">
		<title>Mechanical Rubber Goods (MRG) Applications  </title>
		<content>Mechanical Rubber Goods&amp;#x0A;(MRG) Applications&amp;#x0A;&amp;#x0A; Also known as &amp;#x0A;Non-Tire Rubber (NTR)  </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;The other rubber applications area is known as MRG or mechanical rubber goods.  Sometimes you may hear this applications area referred to as non-tire rubber or NTR.  Most MRG customers prefer the “MRG” label since they do not want to be thought of as “other than tire.”&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000005.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="6" xmlns="">
		<title>Typical MRG Products</title>
		<content>Sheeting (roofing, pond and reservoir liners, gaskets) Tapes Extruded profiles Hose jackets and liners Seals O-Rings Boots, Mounts, Vibration dampers, Grommets, Tubing Typical MRG Products </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;In the MRG area we begin to see a very diverse list of applications made from rubber compounds containing carbon black.  Normally, if you see anything that is made of rubber and is black, it will have carbon black in it.  The next time you have your bonnet raised on your vehicle look at all the applications that are black such as hoses, belts, mounts, grommets, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;tubings&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; and wire covers made with carbon black.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000006.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="7" xmlns="">
		<title>Hoses and Belts</title>
		<content>  N500, N600, and N700 Answer Most hoses and belts are made with which grade(s) of carbon black? Hoses and Belts </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Hoses and belts come in all sizes and shapes.  Even fire hoses have part of their construction made with rubber containing carbon black.  Most hoses and belts are made with soft carbon black grades which are – do you remember? – N500, N600 and N700 grades.  This allows the rubber compounds to flow into the fabric which is contained in all belts and most hose.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000007.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="8" xmlns="">
		<title>Extruded &amp; Molded Parts</title>
		<content>  Extruded parts are the most demanding Virtually no residue can remain so extrusions are flawless Molded goods are less demanding Exceptions include items such as diaphragms Extruded &amp;amp; Molded Parts </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Typically, the most demanding applications in the rubber area are extruded parts especially those that will be seen by customers such as window profiles and wiper blades on the outside of a vehicle.  Imperfections can cause the customer to walk away without buying from us.  That is why the soft grade carbon blacks must have virtually no large residue or grit particles in them so the extrusions are virtually flawless on the surface.  Molded goods are typically less demanding in cleanliness and they also use the soft grades.  They are usually formed as a thick rubber part where imperfections will not be easily seen.  However, there are always exceptions to this such as a molded part is used as a diaphragm.  In this case a small imperfection from the grit could cause catastrophic failure!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000008.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="9" xmlns="">
		<title>Specialty Sector</title>
		<content>Specialty Sector Others2.5%Plastics4.5%Inks3.0%PlasticsInksOthers  ~10% of the total market    </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Much of the carbon black in the specialty segment goes into plastics and inks applications.  The “other” category shown in the graph will not be explored in this module but includes such applications such as insulation in electric arc reactors and blanketing of molten metals during refining.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000009.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="10" xmlns="">
		<title>Plastics Applications</title>
		<content>Plastics Applications Geomembrane/ Geosynthetics Pipe Fiber  Films: Bags &amp;amp; Agricultural Wire &amp;amp; Cable Insulation Cable Conductive Sheathing Utility Office/ Home Furnishings Pots </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Many plastic applications can be seen right from where you are sitting.  The computer, monitor, mouse, printer, wires, phone or other office furnishings may be colored with carbon black.  Besides color, carbon black offers Ultra-Violet light protection to plastics which inhibits the deterioration of the plastic in sunlight.  Carbon black can be used to make plastics electrically conductive.  Let’s now look briefly at some examples of these applications in pictures.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000010.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="11" xmlns="">
		<title>Ultraviolet Light Protection</title>
		<content> Ultraviolet Light Protection     </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Even huge plastic pipe as pictured here along with large pipe connectors may have carbon black in them.  Also, note the film in the top middle photo.  Ultraviolet light causes the rubber polymer to deteriorate rapidly.  Much plastic film is made with carbon black since it offers some of the best Ultra-Violet light protection even at relatively low concentrations in the plastic.  Typical carbon blacks used for these applications include very clean N330 and N660.  KP103 and KC120 are Himadri products that are used in these type applications.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000011.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="12" xmlns="">
		<title>Conductivity Applications  </title>
		<content>Conductivity Applications&amp;#x0A;     • High concentration       </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Commonly, carbon black is found in an electrical cable’s outer jacket to provide U-V protection. KP202 is a Himadri product that &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;can provide &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;excellent U-V protection for the cable jackets.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Carbon black is also used in a semi-conductive plastic.  This is shown as the second black layer on the cable in the lower right hand photograph.  This layer helps prevent the electrical currents from the outside getting to the conductor and destroying the cable. Lastly, the sheath around the conductor is a highly conductive plastic that prevents the current from concentrating on the wire surfaces.  This prevents what is known as “blow through” from the inside which also can damage an expensive cable. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Himadri’s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; Electra 273 and Electra 275 have been designed for these applications. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The tray with the electronic part in it has enough carbon black to be antistatic.  This protects the electronics during storing and transport.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000012.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="13" xmlns="">
		<title>Carbon Blacks for Pigmentation</title>
		<content> Carbon Blacks for Pigmentation  Concentration ~ 1 %  </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Now that I have lost your attention, let me get it back by explaining that carbon black is used to make black fibers.  As we have mentioned earlier, applications also include black plastic and rubber parts as seen in the interior of this European car.  The fabric in the seats will be made from a large diameter fibers.  The ladies’ dresses and the man’s tuxedo are made with very fine fibers.  These fibers contain carbon black as the pigment of choice.  The Himadri carbon blacks for coarse fiber applications are KP103 and KP202 The carbon black for fine fiber applications must be completely free of sieve residue down to less than 25 microns in size.  One of &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Himadri’s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; products for this market application is KP107.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000013.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="14" xmlns="">
		<title>Printing Ink Applications</title>
		<content>Printing Ink Applications   </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Finally, inks are used in a myriad number of processes to produce printed products.  The different types of processes demand different types of carbon black.  Himadri has a full range of designer products for these ink applications.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000014.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="15" xmlns="">
		<title>Myriad Uses for Inks </title>
		<content> Myriad Uses for Inks       So many different printing applications! What an interesting product! </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Just think of all the surfaces on which different types of inks must be used to create letters and pictures. From simple newspapers to slick plastic bags for bread, the processes to print these items are quite varied and complex.  The carbon black in the inks is what makes everything from magazines to brochures readable.  What an interesting product to be studying!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Now, that you know where all the carbon black goes, I hope that you have a better appreciation for why carbon black is a necessity in any modern society.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000015.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="16" xmlns="">
		<title>END</title>
		<content>END  </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;This is the end of &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;module 2.5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; Applications.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000016.jpg"/>
	</section>
</document-metadata>
