<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<document-metadata version="1.0" xmlns="http://breeze.macromedia.com/">
	<document-info>
		<title>8.4 Dryer Safety</title>
		<summary></summary>
		<author/>
		<keywords/>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000001.jpg"/>
		<view-link href="/viewer.swf?slide={{position}}" href-html5="/" href-swf="/viewer.swf?slide={{position}}"/>
	</document-info>
	<section type="slide" position="1" xmlns="">
		<title>8.4 Dryer Safety</title>
		<content>8.4 Dryer Safety  </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;This is module 8.4 Dryer Safety.  This module will cover the principles of good safety practices in the design and operation of a carbon black dryer.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000001.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="2" xmlns="">
		<title>Dryer Safety</title>
		<content>Routine Safety Checks Prior to Startup Dryer Combustor Safety Systems Dryer Exhaust Bag Filter (DEBF) Safety Maintenance for Safety Hazardous Chemicals Review Dryer Safety </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;In this session we will review:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;  Routine safety precautions that should be made prior to startup of a dryer system.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;  Dryer combustor safety systems that are recommended for a standard indirect fired dryer.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;  Safety practices for the dryer exhaust bag filter.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;  Maintenance procedures to assure safe dryer operations.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;And…&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;  A review of the hazardous chemicals that may be found in the dryer system area.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000002.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="3" xmlns="">
		<title>Safety Checks Prior to Startup</title>
		<content>Routine Safety Checks Prior to Startup Dryer Combustor Safety Systems Dryer Exhaust Bag Filter (DEBF) Safety Maintenance for Safety Hazardous Chemicals Review Safety Checks Prior to Startup </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Before starting the drying process, the dryer system should be prepared for safe operations. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000003.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="4" xmlns="">
		<title>Safety Checks Prior to Startup</title>
		<content> Safety Checks Prior to Startup Lock-out and tags removed  Vessel entry permits complete   No tools, parts, equipment or personnel remain inside vessels Equipment guards and personnel guards installed Vacuum on and vessel purged Personal protective equipment </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;The following safety checks should be made:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Assure that all lock-out and tags have been removed by designated personnel.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Assure that all vessel entry permits have been completed and vessel entry tags have been removed by proper personnel.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;All vessels should be thoroughly checked to assure that no tools, parts, equipment or personnel remain inside the vessels.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Check that all equipment guards and personnel guards have been installed.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Assure that vacuum is available to all vessels and that the vacuum has been operated for an adequate period of time to purge the vessels of residual gases and dust.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Personnel that will work in the area should wear the proper personal protective equipment. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000004.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="5" xmlns="">
		<title>2. Dryer Safety Systems</title>
		<content>Safety Checks Prior to Startup Dryer Control Safety Systems Dryer Exhaust Bag Filter (DEBF) Safety Maintenance for Safety Hazardous Chemicals Review 2. Dryer Safety Systems </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;The dryer and dryer combustor must have a safety control system that will maintain the safety of the equipment and personnel that are operating the dryer.   The system that follows is recommended for standard indirect fired dryers.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000005.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="6" xmlns="">
		<title>Indirect Dryer Safety Systems</title>
		<content> Indirect Dryer Safety Systems                vent vent  Tail Gas FUEL  </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;This schematic shows the instrumentation and controls for a standard indirect dryer installation.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Controls for the combustor include flow measurement and controls for the fuel &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;(FUEL),&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; the tail gas &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;(TG),&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; and the combustion air &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;(AIR).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;  Temperature measurements, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;T&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;, are provided for the combustor, the combustion gases in the dryer, the carbon black in the dryer, and the exhaust gases, including the steam and air, going to the dryer exhaust bag filter.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Pressure measurements,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt; P&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;, are shown for the fuels, the combustion air, the combustion gases and the dryer exhaust gases.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;A flame detector, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;FD&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;, and oxygen meter, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;OX&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;, are shown to monitor the safe combustion of the gases in the combustor.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The motor load or amperage, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;AMP&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;, is monitored on all critical motors.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;In this diagram, you can see &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;double block and bleed systems&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; for the fuel and tail gas.  In these systems, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;two valves&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; are provided to assure positive shutoff of explosive gas or fuels to the dryer combustor and a &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;vent&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; is included between the valves to relieve pressure on the valves and to assure that valve leaks can be detected.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000006.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="7" xmlns="">
		<title>2. Dryer Control Safety Systems</title>
		<content>“Crash” the dryer to a fail safe condition means:   Combustibles are isolated from the dryer The fuel gas and tail gas flows are shut down to the dryer Combustion air valve fails to a position to allow purge Cooling down of dryer is started Dryer is turned The distributed control system (DCS) is available to monitor conditions for a defined time period Valves go to fail (safe) positions Carbon black flow to pelletizer is stopped 2. Dryer Control Safety Systems </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;When the dryer is drying carbon black under normal operations and a major process upset occurs that could jeopardize the safety of personnel or the dryer equipment the dryer is shutdown in a controlled manner to a safe condition by automatic controls. This condition is referred to as a “crash” condition.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;In this condition, all combustibles are isolated from the dryer.  Fuel and tail gas flows are shutdown.  The combustion air valve fails to a position that will allow the dryer combustion chamber and the dryer casing to be purged of all combustibles and cooled.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The dryer drum continues to turn so the dryer drum is cooled by the air without warping or damaging the dryer.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The distributed control system continues to monitor and record conditions for a defined time period so any event that can jeopardize dryer safety can be observed and the operator can respond appropriately.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;All valves in the system fail to a safe condition and the carbon black powder  flow to the pelletizer is stopped.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000007.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="8" xmlns="">
		<title>Critical Resources Required in Crash Condition:</title>
		<content>An uninterrupted power supply keeps the DCS system operational for a minimum of 20 minutes All fail-safe valves are spring buffered to their fail-safe condition Energy for turning dryer or other defined emergency equipment Purge medium available for dryer exhaust bag filter Critical Resources Required in Crash Condition: 2. Dryer Control Safety Systems </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;The following safety resources are recommended for the safe operation of the dryer: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;An uninterrupted power supply should be available to keep the DCS system or instrument system for the dryer operational for a minimum of twenty minutes.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;All fail safe valves must be spring buffered to their fail safe condition.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Energy must be available for turning the dryer and for providing energy for other defined emergency equipment.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;A purge medium must be available for purging the dryer exhaust bag filter.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000008.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="9" xmlns="">
		<title>Dryer Combustor Management Logic</title>
		<content>AMPPELLETIZER LOADAMP2DRYER DRIVE AMPS LOWAMP3COMBUSTOR AIR FANAMP4COMBUSTOR TAIL GAS FANFD1PILOT FLAME DETECTOR - FAILL1DENSIFIER TANK LEVEL 1L2DENSIFIER TANK LEVEL 2L3DENSIFIER TANK LEVEL 3L4DENSIFIER TANK LEVEL 4OX1COMBUSTOR O2 ANALYZERP1DENSIFIER TANK PRESSUREP2DRYER DRUM INTERNAL PRES.P3PELLETIZER LIQUID PRES.P4PILOT HP AIR SUPPLY PRES.P5NAT GAS SUPPLY PRES.P6DRYER GAS PRES. - LOWP7DRYER GAS PRES. - HIGHP8DRYER MAIN BURNER GAS PRES.P9DRYER PILOT GAS SUPPLY PRES.P10TAIL GAS SUPPLY PRES LOWP11DRYER FIRE BOX EXIT PRES.P12               COMBUSTOR AIR PRESS LOWRPM1PELLETIZER FEEDER RPM CNTL.RPM2PELLETIZER RPM CONTROLT1TAIL GAS SUPPLY TEMP.T2COMBUSTOR TEMP 1 (2 Meter) HIGHT3COMBUSTOR TEMP 2 (5 Meter) HIGHT4DRYER STACK TEMP.T5DRYER BLACK TEMP. - 10 ftT6DRYER BLACK TEM. - 3 ftT7DRYER EXHAUST TEMP.COMBUSTORREADY(FIRE OFF)Tail Gas Fire -ONMain Burner -Nat Gas ONStandby -Pilot OnIgnition - PilotGas ONMain Burner Nat Gas - ONTail Gas Fire -Start UpPurgeTimerIGNITIONDelay TimerAMP1PELLETIZER LOADAMP2DRYER DRIVE AMPS LOWAMP3COMBUSTOR AIR FANAMP4COMBUSTOR TAIL GAS FANFD1PILOT FLAME DETECTOR - FAILL1DENSIFIER TANK LEVEL 1L2DENSIFIER TANK LEVEL 2L3DENSIFIER TANK LEVEL 3L4DENSIFIER TANK LEVEL 4OX1COMBUSTOR O2 ANALYZERP1DENSIFIER TANK PRESSUREP2DRYER DRUM INTERNAL PRES.P3PELLETIZER LIQUID PRES.P4PILOT HP AIR SUPPLY PRES.P5NAT GAS SUPPLY PRES.P6DRYER GAS PRES. - LOWP7DRYER GAS PRES. - HIGHP8DRYER MAIN BURNER GAS PRES.P9DRYER PILOT GAS SUPPLY PRES.P10TAIL GAS SUPPLY PRES LOWP11DRYER FIRE BOX EXIT PRES.P12               COMBUSTOR AIR PRESS LOWRPM1PELLETIZER FEEDER RPM CNTL.RPM2PELLETIZER RPM CONTROLT1TAIL GAS SUPPLY TEMP.T2COMBUSTOR TEMP 1 (2 Meter) HIGHT3COMBUSTOR TEMP 2 (5 Meter) HIGHT4DRYER STACK TEMP.T5DRYER BLACK TEMP. - 10 ftT6DRYER BLACK TEM. - 3 ftT7DRYER EXHAUST TEMP.DRYER SAFETY LOGICCrash  Dryer Combustor Management Logic                 </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;This diagram shows a recommended logic for managing the combustor of a dryer to prevent explosions or other damaging operations to the dryer.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The logic block instruments are those identified by symbols in the dryer diagram shown.  For instance, AMP2 is the dryer drive amperage shown on the motor in the diagram.  All the instruments in the dryer diagram have a corresponding symbol in the logic block.  Those in dark blue are the ones that become active for the logic shown.  For instance, if AMP2, the dryer amperage,  is low, the “tail gas fire start up”  is not allowed and the dryer combustor fails to the “main burner natural gas on” stage.  This means the combustor cannot be fired using tail gas as a fuel until all the criteria in this block, the dark blue items, are satisfied. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The logic cycle begins with a purge timer completing its cycle for purging the dryer of any combustibles with combustion air.  This time cycle is to assure that no concentration of combustible gases is available to cause an explosion.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Once the purge timer completes its cycle, the combustor is ready for lighting the pilot.  The ignition pilot gas or fuel can then be turned on and the standby pilot can be lighted.  Once the standby pilot is on, the main burner is ready for fuel combustion.  Once the main fuel burner is started, the logic block shows the minimum settings that must be satisfied to fire the dryer on tail gas as we discussed earlier.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;If the following equipment meets the preset logic limits the tail gas can be ignited:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;  The dryer motor drive must be on - AMP2 is not low.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;  The pilot flame detector must be satisfied - FD1 has not failed to detect the pilot flame.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;  The dryer fuel pressure must be within an established range - P6 is not low, P7 is not high.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;  There must be adequate tail gas as indicated by the tail gas supply pressure - P10 is not low.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;  There must be combustion air indicated by adequate supply pressure - P12 is not low.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;  The temperature inside the combustor must satisfy minimum temperature limits to assure adequate combustion of the tail gas when it is introduced to the combustor - T2 and T3 are not high.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;If any of these limits are not satisfied, tail gas combustion cannot occur and the logic will revert or continue  to firing the main burner with fuel.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;If all of these limits are satisfied, the tail gas combustion is allowed. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000009.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="10" xmlns="">
		<title>Dryer Combustor Crash Logic</title>
		<content>AMP1PELLETIZER LOADAMP2DRYER DRIVEAMP3COMBUSTOR AIR FANAMP4COMBUSTOR TAIL GAS FANFD1PILOT FLME DETECTORL1DENSIFIER TANK LEVEL 1L2DENSIFIER TANK LEVEL 2L3DENSIFIER TANK LEVEL 3L4DENSIFIER TANK LEVEL 4OX1COMBUSTOR O2 ANALYZERP1DENSIFIER TANK PRESSUREP2DRYER DRUM INTERNAL PRES.P3PELLETIZER LIQUID PRES.P4PILOT HP AIR SUPPLY PRES.P5NAT GAS SUPPLY PRES.P6DRYER GAS PRES. - LOWP7DRYER GAS PRES. - HIGHP8DRYER Main Burner GAS PRES.P9DRYER PILOT GAS SUPPLY PRES.P10TAIL GAS SUPPLY HEADER PRES.P11DRYER FIRE BOX EXIT PRES.RPM1PELLETIZER FEEDER RPM CNTL.RPM2PELLETIZER RPM CONTROLT1TAIL GAS SUPPLY TEMP.T2COMBUSTOR TEMP 1 (2 Meter)T3COMBUSTOR TEMP. 2 (5 Meter)T4DRYER STACK TEMP.T5DRYER BLACK TEMP. - 10 ftT6DRYER BLACK TEM. - 3 ftT7DRYER EXHAUST TEMP.AMP1PELLETIZER LOADAMP2DRYER DRIVEAMP3COMBUSTOR AIR FANAMP4COMBUSTOR TAIL GAS FANFD1PILOT FLME DETECTORL1DENSIFIER TANK LEVEL 1L2DENSIFIER TANK LEVEL 2L3DENSIFIER TANK LEVEL 3L4DENSIFIER TANK LEVEL 4OX1COMBUSTOR O2 ANALYZERP1DENSIFIER TANK PRESSUREP2DRYER DRUM INTERNAL PRES.P3PELLETIZER LIQUID PRES.P4PILOT HP AIR SUPPLY PRES.P5NAT GAS SUPPLY PRES.P6DRYER GAS PRES. - LOWP7DRYER GAS PRES. - HIGHP8DRYER MAIN BURNER GAS PRES.P9DRYER PILOT GAS SUPPLY PRES.P10TAIL GAS SUPPLY HEADER PRESP11DRYER FIRE BOX EXIT PRES.RPM1PELLETIZER FEEDER RPM CNTL.RPM2PELLETIZER RPM CONTROLT1TAIL GAS SUPPLY TEMP.T2COMBUSTOR TEMP 1 (2 Meter)T3COMBUSTOR TEMP. 2 (5 Meter)T4DRYER STACK TEMP.T5DRYER BLACK TEMP. - 10 ftT6DRYER BLACK TEM. - 3 ftT7DRYER EXHAUST TEMP.COMBUSTORFIRE OFFTail Gas Fire -ONMain Burner -Nat Gas ONStandby -Pilot OnIgnition - PilotGas ONCrashTail Gas Fire -Start UpAMP1PELLETIZER LOADAMP2DRYER DRIVE Rotation LowAMP3COMBUSTOR AIR FAN - FailAMP4COMBUSTOR TAIL GAS FANFD1PILOT FLAME DETECTOR - FailL1DENSIFIER TANK LEVEL 1L2DENSIFIER TANK LEVEL 2L3DENSIFIER TANK LEVEL 3L4DENSIFIER TANK LEVEL 4OX1COMBUSTOR O2 ANALYZERP1DENSIFIER TANK PRESSUREP2DRYER DRUM INTERNAL PRES.P3PELLETIZER LIQUID PRES.P4PILOT HP AIR SUPPLY PRES.P5NAT GAS SUPPLY PRES.P6DRYER GAS PRES. - LOWP7DRYER GAS PRES. - HIGHP8DRYER MAIN BURNER GAS PRES.P9DRYER PILOT GAS SUPPLY PRES.P10TAIL GAS SUPPLY HEADER PRES.P11DRYER FIRE BOX EXIT PRES.P12               COMBUSTOR AIR PRES LOW LOWRPM1PELLETIZER FEEDER RPM CNTL.RPM2PELLETIZER RPM CONTROLT1TAIL GAS SUPPLY TEMP.T2COMBUSTOR TEMP 1 (2 Meter)T3COMBUSTOR TEMP. 2 (5 Meter)T4DRYER STACK TEMP.T5DRYER BLACK TEMP. - 10 ftT6DRYER BLACK TEM. - 3 ftT7DRYER EXHAUST TEMP.PurgeTimerDelayTimerAMP1PELLETIZER LOADAMP2DRYER DRIVEAMP3COMBUSTOR AIR FANAMP4COMBUSTOR TAIL GAS FANFD1PILOT FLME DETECTORL1DENSIFIER TANK LEVEL 1L2DENSIFIER TANK LEVEL 2L3DENSIFIER TANK LEVEL 3L4DENSIFIER TANK LEVEL 4OX1COMBUSTOR O2 ANALYZERP1DENSIFIER TANK PRESSUREP2DRYER DRUM INTERNAL PRES.P3PELLETIZER LIQUID PRES.P4PILOT HP AIR SUPPLY PRES.P5NAT GAS SUPPLY PRES.P6DRYER GAS PRES. - LOWP7DRYER GAS PRES. - HIGHP8DRYER MAIN BURNER GAS PRES.P9DRYER PILOT GAS SUPPLY PRES.P10TAIL GAS SUPPLY HEADER PRESP11DRYER FIRE BOX EXIT PRES.RPM1PELLETIZER FEEDER RPM CNTL.RPM2PELLETIZER RPM CONTROLT1TAIL GAS SUPPLY TEMP.T2COMBUSTOR TEMP 1 (2 Meter)T3COMBUSTOR TEMP. 2 (5 Meter)T4DRYER STACK TEMP.T5DRYER BLACK TEMP. - 10 ftT6DRYER BLACK TEM. - 3 ftT7DRYER EXHAUST TEMP.DRYER SAFETY LOGIC Dryer Combustor Crash Logic It is important that these safeties are not disabled&amp;#x0A;or bypassed under any circumstance. </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;This diagram shows logic that leads to a “crash” condition for a dryer.   If you compare this diagram to the previous diagram, you will see that the low amperage on the dryer motor will cause the dryer combustor to crash and the purge cycle to start again.  This type of logic can be followed for all of the critical settings of parameters important to the dryer operation.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;This logic is required to protect the dryer during combustion with explosive mixtures such as those containing the fuel and tail gas.  The sequence provides for a safety purge of the dryer prior to proceeding with any flame or combustible gas being introduced to the dryer combustor and the shutdown of the dryer combustor when any unsafe condition exists.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;It is important that these safeties are not disabled or bypassed under any circumstance.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000010.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="11" xmlns="">
		<title>3. Dryer Exhaust Bag Filter (DEBF) Safety</title>
		<content>Routine Safety Checks Prior to Startup Dryer Combustor Safety Systems Dryer Exhaust Bag Filter (DEBF) Safety Maintenance for Safety Hazardous Chemicals Review 3. Dryer Exhaust Bag Filter (DEBF) Safety </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;The dryer exhaust bag filter is susceptible to fire during normal operation of the dryer and also during dryer upset conditions..  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000011.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="12" xmlns="">
		<title>3. Dryer Exhaust Bag Filter (DEBF) Safety</title>
		<content>Fire causes: Sparks from dryer entering filter and igniting bags or igniting carbon black in filter High temperature excursion igniting one of combustibles in filter  Filter safety system provides design scheme to prevent extent of damage due to unsafe conditions 3. Dryer Exhaust Bag Filter (DEBF) Safety </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Fire can be caused by sparks from the dryer entering the filter and igniting the bags or igniting carbon black in the filter.  Fire can also be caused by a high temperature excursion igniting one of the combustibles in the filter.  The filter safety system must provide a design scheme to prevent the extent of damage due to an unsafe condition.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000012.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="13" xmlns="">
		<title>3. Dryer Exhaust Bag Filter (DEBF) Safety</title>
		<content>Minimum Safety Features: Inlet and outlet temperature monitoring and alarm Compressed air flow shutdown due to low pressure (for pulse jet filters)  Inert purge medium available   Steam is recommended Water spray is usually available For High Temperature Excursion: Inert purge medium to filter is on Air pulse system is stopped (for pulse filters) after cleaning bags through one cycle  Purge gas supply fan is stopped 3. Dryer Exhaust Bag Filter (DEBF) Safety  </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;The safety system of the dryer exhaust bag filter is designed to prevent fires or other damage to the filter.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The inlet and outlet temperatures of the filter are monitored.  Alarms are provided if the temperatures are too high or too low.  If the filter is a pulse jet filter, low pressure on the system results in the shutdown of compressed air.   This is to prevent air loss and high air flows to the filter in the event of damaged solenoids on the filter.  A purge medium is required for the filter.  A steam purge is recommended in plants where steam is available.  When steam is not available, a water spray is usually available to provide water to cool any high temperature gas streams to the filter.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;If a high temperature is detected in the filter, the inert purge medium is turned on to purge the filter of any combustibles and to provide cooling.  The air pulse system is stopped for pulse filters after cleaning the carbon black from the bags through one filter cycle.  The air pulse system is stopped to eliminate air in the filter to prevent fires.  The bags are cleaned through one cycle to reduce the amount of carbon black as a combustible that is residual on the filter bags and in the filter hopper.  The purge gas supply fan is stopped so any potential heat coming from the dryer is eliminated and a source of air that could propagate combustion is eliminated.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000013.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="14" xmlns="">
		<title>Dryer Safety - Overview</title>
		<content>Routine Safety Checks Prior to Startup Dryer Combustor Safety Systems Dryer Exhaust Bag Filter (DEBF) Safety Maintenance for Safety Hazardous Chemicals Review Dryer Safety - Overview </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;In order to have safe operations of a dryer system, the system must be well maintained.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000014.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="15" xmlns="">
		<title>4. Maintenance for Safety</title>
		<content>Following preventative checks on a defined, systematic schedule: Standby equipment checked on a routine basis   Air, natural gas and tail gas flow measurements calibrated  Safety equipment tested  Double block and bleed valve systems on fuels Critical interlocks tested  Validate O2 analyzer accuracy 4. Maintenance for Safety </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Regular preventative maintenance checks need to be conducted on a routine schedule in order to keep the dryer safe and personnel working around the dryer safe under all conditions. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The standby equipment such as the uninterrupted power supply should be operational and verified to be ready to provide power in the event of a loss of power.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The flow instruments for combustion air, natural gas and tail gas should be calibrated routinely and also confirmed to be accurate by taking oxygen readings on the combustor during operation.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;All safety equipment should be tested to make sure that it will work when needed.  Double block and bleed valve systems on fuels require that two valves block the flow to the combustor and that the pipe between the two valves vents to the atmosphere so that no fuel or pressure stays on the pipeline during failure.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Interlocks are sequences of switches that shut down equipment in a predetermined order in order to prevent unsafe conditions.  For instance, when the dryer shuts down, the carbon black flow to the pelletizer is shutdown immediately and automatically.  These interlocks should be documented and confirmed to be working on a regular basis.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;An oxygen analyzer is installed on the dryer combustor.  This analyzer assures the proper mixture of air with tail gas and or other fuels when the combustor is fired.  This analyzer accuracy should be confirmed using a portable oxygen meter on a regular basis.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000015.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="16" xmlns="">
		<title>5. Hazardous Chemicals Review</title>
		<content>Safety Checks Prior to Startup Dryer Combustor Safety Systems Dryer Exhaust Bag Filter (DEBF) Safety Maintenance for Safety Hazardous Chemicals Review 5. Hazardous Chemicals Review </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;It is important that we are aware of the presence of hazardous gases in the dryer system area, the area where there may be exposure to tail gas or combusted tail gas..  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000016.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="17" xmlns="">
		<title>Dryer Tail Gas Combustion Gases</title>
		<content> Air: N2	Nitrogen O2	Oxygen Tail Gas: N2	Nitrogen H2O	Water H2	Hydrogen CO	Carbon Monoxide CO2	Carbon Dioxide C2H2	Acetylene CH4	Methane H2S	Hydrogen Sulfide Dryer Tail Gas Combustion Gases Combusted Tail Gas N2		Nitrogen H2O		Water CO2		Carbon Dioxide SO2		Sulfur Dioxide O2		Oxygen Reactants Products Regular maintenance of this equipment should be performed to maintain gas tight seals and assure adequate vacuum on vessels to prevent leaks. Combustion    Hazardous To Breath!     </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Tail gas contains combustibles such as hydrogen, carbon monoxide, acetylene, methane and hydrogen sulfide. Since all of these gases are combustible, a tail gas when mixed with air can be explosive.  Care should be taken that no uncontrolled ignition sources be present where tail gas is present in a vessel or where leaks occur from the process equipment. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;After combustion, the combusted tail gas contains sulfur dioxide. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Carbon monoxide and hydrogen sulfide in the raw tail gas are hazardous to breathe, as is the sulfur dioxide in the combusted tail gas.   If you are working in areas where exposure to these gases is possible, you should be familiar with the safety requirements and the proper precautions to take to avoid exposure and treat exposure in the event of contact.  See your supervisor prior for further guidelines or call a safety professional.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;It is important that these gases remain in gas tight pipes and vessels to prevent fires and injury.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;Proper vacuum in vessels must be maintained to prevent leaks of these gases into the atmosphere and employee working areas.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;   Regular maintenance of this equipment should be performed to maintain gas tight seals and assure adequate vacuum on vessels to prevent leaks.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000017.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="18" xmlns="">
		<title> END</title>
		<content>&amp;#x0A;END  </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;This is the end of module 8.4 Dryer Safety.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000018.jpg"/>
	</section>
</document-metadata>
