<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<document-metadata version="1.0" xmlns="http://breeze.macromedia.com/">
	<document-info>
		<title>8.3 Indirect Rotary Dryer (Part 2)</title>
		<summary></summary>
		<author/>
		<keywords/>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000001.jpg"/>
		<view-link href="/viewer.swf?slide={{position}}" href-html5="/" href-swf="/viewer.swf?slide={{position}}"/>
	</document-info>
	<section type="slide" position="1" xmlns="">
		<title>8.3 Indirect Rotary Dryer</title>
		<content>8.3 Indirect Rotary Dryer Part 2 </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;This is module 8.3 Indirect Rotary Dryers (Part 2).  Rotary dryers are the current standard technology in the carbon black industry.  This session is intended to provide an overview of some of the basic elements used to determine the capacity of these dryers with a focus on Indirect Rotary Dryers.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000001.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="2" xmlns="">
		<title>Drying</title>
		<content> Rotary Dryer  Wet Pellets ~ 40% - 60% water Dry Pellets  &amp;lt; 1% water Dryers Types Indirect Fired Rotary Dryers Indirect-Direct Fired Rotary Dryers Direct Fired Tray Dryers Fluidized Bed Dryers      Drying  ROTARY DRYER DRYER COMBUSTOR </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;After wet pellets are formed they range from about 40% to nearly 60% water or moisture.  The level of water in the wet pellets  depends directly on the structure of the carbon black.  These wet pellets must be dried to a level less than 1% since the customer does not want to purchase water.  This is done using a dryer.  Several types of dryers are used in the industry including indirect fired rotary dryers, indirect-direct fired rotary dryers, direct fired tray dryers, and fluidized bed dryers which can be direct or indirect fired.  The dryers on Lines 1 and 2 are indirect-direct fired dryers and on Lines 3 and 4 are indirect fired dryers.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000002.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="3" xmlns="">
		<title>Indirect Dryer Design Layout</title>
		<content>Indirect Dryer Design Layout      Firebox Off gas Purge Gas CB, Wet Drum Oxidation/ Relief Air Tailgas Combustion Air Combustion Chamber Q hi Natural Gas  CB, Dry            </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;There are a number of rotary dryer configurations in service in the carbon black industry..  The above outline establishes the basic elements of an indirect fired dryer.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The combustion chamber is the refractory lined element of the dryer system where an auxiliary  fuel (such as oil, L-P-G or natural gas), and tail gas are burned with heated combustion air to provide the hot combustion products needed to heat the dryer drum.  The “Fire Box”, sometimes called a casing”, is the refractory-lined, tubular structure that surrounds the dryer drum and retains the heated combustor gasses to heat the drum.  The off gas exits the dryer stack at the discharge end of the firebox after the drying process has extracted the heat needed to dry the carbon black and raise the temperature to a level of approximately 180 degrees C.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;In the above view of the standard design the wet carbon black enters at the left from the wet pelletizer, and the dry black exits on the right and is discharged into a bucket elevator.  The Line 3 and 4 dryers have a rotary valve at this location to prevent the leakage of wet gasses into the elevator which may cause wet pellets in storage and to prevent the leakage of air into the dryer drum which may cause the black to be oxidized during the drying process.  The purge gas (steam and air) exit the dryer at the upstream end of the drum and are directed to a dryer exhaust bag filter that separates any entrained carbon black from the purge gases.. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000003.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="4" xmlns="">
		<title>Fire Box Inlet</title>
		<content>Fire Box Inlet   Front End of Fire-Box  Combustion Gas  Gas entering forward and at bottom: Minimizes drum stress Localized overheating Metal fatigue Maximizes gas velocity  </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;The fire box inlet has an entry of the combustor gas into a single entry point under the wet end of the dryer drum.  In order to maximize the effective heating this entry should be as far forward, toward the wet black entry, in the firebox as possible.  As can be seen in this sketch the combustion gas entry is below the bottom of the dryer drum.  As we will discuss later in our study of rotary dryers this is an important design revision from the past in order to &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;minimize the stresses &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;on the drum from &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;localized overheating&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;.  In many cases this localized overheating results in drum cracks and &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;metal fatigue&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;In addition to minimizing the direct contact of the dryer drum with the combustion gasses this design &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;maximizes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; the velocity of the gas around the drum by encouraging a spinning component into the gas flow.  This  added gas velocity greatly aids the heat transfer to the drum wall, especially at the wet end.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000004.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="5" xmlns="">
		<title>Dryer Drum Pins</title>
		<content> Dryer Drum Pins  Inlet Outlet     Rate of heat transfer from combustor gas to dryer drum = External Heat Transfer Coefficient (EHTC) Rate of heat transfer from drum wall to carbon black on inside = Internal Heat Transfer Coefficient (IHTC) </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Another feature that adds to the heat transfer from the combustor gases to the dryer drum wall is the addition of cylindrical pins to the first part of the drum.  These 10 x 80 mm pins are stud welded to the drum wall on 50 mm centers with each row offset from the neighboring row.  The offset is made to minimize the &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;circumvential&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; stress on the dryer drum wall.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The rate of heat transfer from the combustor gas to the dryer drum wall is defined as the External Heat Transfer Coefficient (EHTC).  The rate of heat transfer from the dryer drum wall to the carbon black pellets on the inside of the drum is defined as the Internal Heat Transfer Coefficient (IHTC).  The addition of pins to the first part of the drum is to improve the heat transfer efficiency and capacity of the dryer because the External Heat Transfer Coefficient is limiting at the wet end of the drum.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000005.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="6" xmlns="">
		<title>Dryer Heat Transfer</title>
		<content> Dryer Heat Transfer Heat Transfer Considerations That Impact Dryer Design HTC Units: W/(m2*K) Internal and External Heat Transfer Coefficients 					 EHTC		IHTC Wet Carbon Black Pellets		&amp;lt;&amp;lt;82		&amp;gt;90 Dry Carbon Black Pellets		&amp;lt;  57		   11        </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;As we showed in drying theory, the heat transfer coefficients are basically composed of the combustor heat that provides heat to penetrate the dryer drum wall and the heat transferred through the drum wall into the carbon black pellets.  This table quantifies the heat transfer considerations that impact a dryer’s design.  The effective use of this information can provide a dryer with the maximum capacity that the metallurgy of the dryer drum will tolerate without over stressing or overheating the drum wall in the heating zone.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;At the wet end of the dryer the Internal Heat Transfer Coefficient,. IHTC,.  may exceed 90 Watts per square meter per degree Kelvin while the External Heat Transfer Coefficient is less than 82 Watts per square meter per degree Kelvin .  This means that the rate that the wet pellets can remove heat from the dryer drum wall is faster than the rate the combustor gases can transfer heat to the drum wall.  At this location in the dryers configuration it is okay to have hot combustion gases in the firebox because the wet, moisture-laden pellets can transfer heat fast enough to keep the drum wall from overheating. An analogy for this is that a pot does not overheat if there is water in the pot to boil.  Once the pot goes dry the heat transfer to the air in the pot is no longer fast enough to keep the pot from melting or overheating.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;To follow through with this concept, the heat transfer to the carbon black after it is dry is limited by the IHTC because the internal heat transfer coefficient of 11 Watts per square meter per degree Kelvin  is less than the external coefficient of about 57 Watts per square meter per degree Kelvin .  If we were to install external pins on the dryer drum at this end of the drum we would raise the external coefficient and still not transfer any more heat to the black.  That is why pins are not recommended for this area of heat transfer.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000006.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="7" xmlns="">
		<title>Overall Heat Transfer Coefficient</title>
		<content> Overall Heat Transfer Coefficient Calculating the Balance of Internal &amp;amp; External Heat Transfer   </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;When we consider the Overall Heat Transfer Coefficient we are calculating the balance of both internal and external heat transfer through the dryer.  As it turns out, this is largely a function of the percent moisture on the pellets at any point in the drying process.  When the pellets have the highest moisture content the external heat transfer coefficient is limiting in the dryer.  As the pellets dry, the internal heat transfer coefficient becomes the limit.  The carbon black bed temperature will only be at the boiling point of water until the moisture content drops below about 2 % .  This is the reason that one of the thermocouples in the bed of carbon black is located in the last 3 meters of the dryer.  This location is about 1.5 meters before the carbon black pellets exit the fire box.  The outlet thermocouple is usually located outside the heat transfer zone where the temperature has begun to drop from its peak.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000007.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="8" xmlns="">
		<title>Indirect Dryer Carbon Black Capacity vs Pellet Moisture</title>
		<content> Indirect Dryer Carbon Black Capacity vs Pellet Moisture N774 N660 N330 N220 N234   </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Most of us want to talk about how much carbon black a dryer will dry. Elevating the carbon black temperature from the entry of the dryer to the discharge of the dryer requires only 6 to 10 % of the heat transferred to the dryer.  The primary heat requirement for a dryer is the heat required to heat and evaporate the water that is used to form the pellets.  Therefore, if the structure of a product changes, the water content of the wet pellet changes at optimum performance and the amount of carbon black that can be dried is changed for a fixed dryer capacity.   As the water content of the wet pellets goes up on the wet pellets, the carbon black that can be dried decreases as shown above.  We can dry significantly more N660 in a dryer than we can dry N234 in the same dryer.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000008.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="9" xmlns="">
		<title>Indirect Dryer Carbon Black Capacity vs OAN</title>
		<content> Indirect Dryer Carbon Black Capacity vs OAN  N774 N660 N330 N220 N234     </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Above is a graph showing how the capacity of a dryer is related to the pellet OAN for a 160 tons of water per day dryer.  The capacity of the dryer in tons of carbon black per day goes from about 250 tons per day for N774 which has a OAN of 72 to about 130 tons per day for N234 which has an OAN of 125.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000009.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="10" xmlns="">
		<title>Indirect Rotary Dryer Capacity</title>
		<content> Indirect Rotary Dryer Capacity The capacity of a dryer is dependent upon the heated surface area of the dryer   </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;This chart illustrates the relationship of an indirect dryer size as expressed in the heated area of the dryer versus the capacity of the dryer in tons of water &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;per&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; day. The heated area of the dryer is the drum area enclosed by, that is inside, the firebox.  Smaller dryers below 18 meters in length typically have about 2.5 meters outside the firebox and longer dryers have about 3.0 meters.  The length outside the firebox is usually dictated by the size of the equipment required to drive and support the dryer shell while it is rotating in the firebox.  As you can see above, for a heated area of 60 square meters, the dryer will dry just over 140 tons of water per day.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000010.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="11" xmlns="">
		<title>Capacity vs. Dryer Rotational Speed, RPM</title>
		<content>Capacity vs. Dryer Rotational Speed, RPM  Capacity vs. Base Capacity  Drum Rotation, RPM Increasing drum speed keeps drum cooler &amp;amp; allows a higher firing rate.  However, it also increases parts wear at faster speeds.   8% </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Increasing the drum rotational speed (R-P-M) is a means of increasing the dryer capacity.  Dryer drums that turn faster have more capacity than dryer drums that turn slowly.  One way to look at the dryer is that when the drum has no black in contact with the surface it is being heated by the combustion gases.  When the drum is in contact with the carbon black it is being cooled by the carbon black. For most of the drying duration the inside coefficient is higher than the outside coefficient, and speeding up the dryer cools the drum and allows operating at a slightly higher firing rate than a dryer turning more slowly.  The overall effect is that the dryer capacity will increase approximately 8% if the drum rotational speed is doubled.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The negative of this practice is that the driving parts for rotation (chains, trunnions, trunnion rollers, drives, etc.) have much higher mechanical wear rates when operated at higher speeds.  Generally the wear of these parts will increase approximately by the square of the speed ratio.  Doubling the speed will result in replacing these parts at least 4 times more often at the higher speed than operating at the lower speed.  It also requires higher electrical power from the motor to operate at the higher speed.  All of these factors must be taken into account when increasing the rotational speed of the dryer.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000011.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="12" xmlns="">
		<title>Capacity vs. Dryer Bed Depth</title>
		<content>Capacity vs. Dryer Bed Depth   % Capacity Change  Bed Depth, mm   7%   5% Deeper bed depth = Increased residence time 150 0 200 250 300 350 50 100  </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Increasing the dryer bed depth from 150 millimeters to 300 millimeters will result in a capacity increase of about 7 % and lowering the bed depth at the outlet to zero will reduce the capacity from the basic design expectation by 5 %.  This effect is the result of the time the black remains in contact with the drum surface during each revolution.  Deeper bed depths have more surface contact between the carbon black and the drum wall.  The down side of deeper bed depths is the disproportionate increase in residence time in the dryer.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;If a deeper bed depth is selected, the residence time in the dryer may increase significantly.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;This means that if a reactor quality change is required the time required for the carbon black to travel through the dryer is increased.  Any upset upstream &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;that causes off &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;specification production will take longer to resolve at the dryer outlet.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000012.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="13" xmlns="">
		<title>Capacity vs. Firing Rate</title>
		<content>Capacity vs. Firing Rate  % Max Capacity  % Max Firing Rate     14% reduction  </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;If the dryer capacity is defined as 100% of the rated capacity when the firing rate of the combustor is 100% of its capacity, we would observe only a 14% reduction in dryer capacity when we reduce the firing rate of the combustor by 20%.  The hot combustor gases remain in the fire box longer at the reduced firing rate, and a higher percentage of the energy in these gases is transferred to the drum when the rates are reduced.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;A better way to explain this is that the firing rate is used to ensure the black gets dry.  We do not adjust the production rate because of the dryer firing rate.  When we reduce the production rate 14% we will require only 80 % of the full load firing rate to dry the black.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000013.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="14" xmlns="">
		<title>END</title>
		<content>END  </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;This is the end of Module 8.3 Indirect Rotary Dryer (Part 2).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000014.jpg"/>
	</section>
</document-metadata>
