<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<document-metadata version="1.0" xmlns="http://breeze.macromedia.com/">
	<document-info>
		<title>2.4  Surface Chemistry</title>
		<summary></summary>
		<author/>
		<keywords/>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000001.jpg"/>
		<view-link href="/viewer.swf?slide={{position}}" href-html5="/" href-swf="/viewer.swf?slide={{position}}"/>
	</document-info>
	<section type="slide" position="1" xmlns="">
		<title>2.4 Surface Chemistry</title>
		<content>2.4 Surface Chemistry </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;This is the module &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;2.4 &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Surface Chemistry.  We have already discussed structure and surface area and how they are the two most important properties measured for carbon black characterization.  Now we will discuss the last area that can impact performance &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;- &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;surface chemistry.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;You will see that an understanding of surface chemistry is an extension of the surface area  discussed in the previous module.   &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000001.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="2" xmlns="">
		<title>Chemical Analysis  </title>
		<content>Carbon Black is ~98% Carbon  ~1-3% Sulfur and Oxygen   Typically with &amp;lt;1% Hydrogen and Nitrogen Most of the Oxygen is Found on the Surface Most Active Surface Groups Contain Both Oxygen and Carbon  Chemical Analysis   </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;First, the bulk chemical composition of carbon black from a furnace reactor consists of approximately 98% carbon.  Sulfur and oxygen are present at or below 1-3% while hydrogen and nitrogen typically are below 1%.  Nitrogen may be higher when using coal-based feedstocks.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Most of the oxygen is found &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;on &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;the surface of the carbon black.  This oxygen is combined with mainly carbon to form most of the functional groups on the surface&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000002.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="3" xmlns="">
		<title>Why Is Surface Chemistry Important? </title>
		<content>In Rubber Can Affect: Cure Characteristics such as Scorch Safety Abrasion Resistance Tensile Strength and Modulus Hysteresis Energy wasted in building heat instead of allowing the tire to roll further In Plastics and Inks Can Affect: Wetting and Incorporation Viscosity Why Is Surface Chemistry Important?  </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;The surface of the carbon black is what interacts with the customer's product matrix and has an impact on the carbon black's benefits.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;In rubber this surface chemistry has been shown to affect cure characteristics such as scorch.  Scorch is the time before a rubber compound starts to rapidly cross-link and &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;becomes &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;a solid.  It is important to have a controlled cure, such as in a tire, to allow the rubber to flow into the tread design before it becomes too stiff.  Other properties can also be affected in rubber such as abrasion resistance, tensile strength, modulus and hysteresis.  Hysteresis is the energy wasted in your automobile tires in building up heat in the polymer instead of allowing the tire to roll further on a tank of gasoline – that is lowering rolling resistance of the tire.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Lastly, surface chemistry can impact plastics and inks in ease of wetting out which can also affect viscosity.  In a polar matrix, if the surface chemistry on the carbon black is also polar then the two mix together better.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000003.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="4" xmlns="">
		<title>Carbon Black Particle</title>
		<content>Higher surface area = smaller particle size The larger the surface area, the more potential for surface groups Typical aggregates are smaller than 100 nanometers Carbon Black Particle     Particle     Aggregate  </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;We will start with our now familiar aggregate to explore surface chemistry.  It is very important to remember that surface chemistry must have a surface on which to form and the higher the surface area (smaller the particle size) the more potential you have for surface groups to form.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;A typical aggregate is less than 100 nanometers in size remembering that a nanometer is one billionth of a meter.  You cannot see an aggregate even with the most powerful optical microscope.  Now we are going to go down to have a very close look at the surface of the carbon black &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000004.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="5" xmlns="">
		<title>Crystalline Nature of  Carbon Black</title>
		<content> Crystalline Nature of &amp;#x0A;Carbon Black Graphitic Plate  Carbon black particle under transmission electron microscope Carbon crystallites with graphitic layers </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;As we take a look at a particle of carbon black using a transmission electron microscope, the image on the right is what we can see.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;There are very small crystallites of carbon with graphitic layers as illustrated on the left.  When the graphite layers are on the surface of the particle they are subjected to reactions especially with oxygen or oxygen containing molecules such as water.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The edges of these surface graphitic planes &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;are &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;especially prone to reaction.  The next slide offers an even closer look at these surface features.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000005.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="6" xmlns="">
		<title>Clean Surface of Carbon – Graphitic Plate</title>
		<content>Clean Surface of Carbon – Graphitic Plate  The Illustration Represents a Graphitic Carbon Plane  Found on the Carbon Black’s Surface This Graphitic Plane and Especially its Edges Can React with Oxygen </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;This graphite-like structure is found on the carbon black’s surface.  This structure is especially reactive on its edges.  To complete our illustration, we need to add the surface groups containing mostly oxygen.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000006.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="7" xmlns="">
		<title>Functional Groups Formed on Surfaces </title>
		<content>Functional Groups Formed on Surfaces                O O O O HO COOH OOHCO Surface reactions occur as soon as particles begin to form and continue well into the dryer system Oxygen-containing groups react with the carbon surface to form the  most important and abundant surface chemistry One of each unique oxygen groups is shown </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;As the carbon black particle is formed, reactions are taking place and continue to do so well into the dryer system if it is a wet pelleting process.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Here we see how oxygen or oxygen-containing groups react with the surface to &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;form &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;oxygen surface groups.  Oxygen groups are the most important and abundant surface chemistry on carbon black.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Next we will see what each of these groups are called and how acidic or basic they are relative to each other.   For simplicity, we show just one of each of the unique oxygen-containing groups.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000007.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="8" xmlns="">
		<title>Common Chemical Functional Groups </title>
		<content>Common Chemical Functional Groups  Quinoid carbonyl groups (weakly acidic) Pyrone structure (basic) Lactole groups (slightly acidic) Phenolic groups (acidic) Carboxylic groups (highly acidic) </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Here are listed some of the more prevalent oxygen-containing groups making up the surface chemistry on carbon black.  From the upper left, we see the highly acidic carboxylic group, then the phenolics.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Lactole&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; and quinoid carbonyl groups form weak acidic chemistry. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Finally, but certainly not least is the pyrone structure which exhibits basic properties.  Note that many furnace grade carbon blacks exhibit a basic pH due to the presence of pyrones.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000008.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="9" xmlns="">
		<title>Furnace Reactor                                               Surface Chemistry Formation Zone                 </title>
		<content> Furnace Reactor                                      &amp;#x0A;        Surface Chemistry Formation Zone                &amp;#x0A;  Formation Zone  for Surface Chemistry Gas black reactor (not illustrated)  Works on the same principle as the channel black process  2 – 4% oxygen content  When these blacks are oxidized, oxygen content reaches up to 16% </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;In this illustration of a furnace reactor, note that the formation zone for surface chemistry extends well past where the aggregates have finished forming.  Addition of chemical groups continues even in the dryer where there may be more available oxygen to react with the surface.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Though not illustrated, a gas black reactor which is based on the same principle as the channel black process has quite high oxygen content in the 2-4% range.  When these blacks are oxidized, the oxygen content and hence the oxygen-containing surface groups can reach up to 16%!  These gas black reactors are available in the industry for making highly specialized carbon blacks.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000009.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="10" xmlns="">
		<title>Polyaromatics and Water</title>
		<content>Polyaromatics and Water                      O O O O O HO COOH   OH C  O OHH OHH   napthalene anthracene </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;In addition to the chemical groups bonded to the surface there are compounds that adhere to the surface.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Compounds call polyaromatic hydrocarbons coat the surface of many carbon blacks. These simple ring groups form in the cooler parts of the reactor and condense onto the surface as the carbon black cools.  The two compounds shown here are naphthalene and anthracene. Note that this oily coating becomes more pronounced with the lower surface area - larger particle - carbon blacks because of the lower temperature in the reactor zone.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Another very prevalent compound on the surface of the carbon black is &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;water H&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;O.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;This water comes from both the combustion process and can be added either in water quench sprays in the process or in wet pelletization.  Even though not considered part of the surface chemistry, water can have both a positive and negative impact when present in the carbon black.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The positive effect is the carbon black wetting out easier in water-based ink compounds making the carbon black easier to mix into the ink.  A negative effect is when the water causes blowing problems and resultant defects in polymers such as rubber or plastics.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000010.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="11" xmlns="">
		<title>Other Chemicals Impacting Surface Chemistry</title>
		<content>Feedstock Impurities Salts in the Process Water Especially for Pelletizing – Calcium, Magnesium, etc. Binders/Pelleting Aids: Lignin or Molasses and the Elements Contained in These Post Production Oxidation: Acid Residues Other Chemicals Impacting Surface Chemistry </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;One must also remember that there are quite a few other compounds and elements present in the carbon black process that can be on the surface and can have an impact on the carbon black properties and the customer’s application.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;These include but are not limited to feedstock impurities, water salts, pellet binders such as lignin and molasses and residual acid from post-oxidation processes.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Of course post-oxidation of the carbon black can add significantly to the surface chemistry.  Post oxidation will not be discussed in this module.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000011.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="12" xmlns="">
		<title>Test Methods for Surface Chemistry</title>
		<content>Heat Loss (105 ºC)  Toluene Discoloration Volatiles (950 ºC) pH Titration of Surface Oxide Groups Spectrometric Methods Test Methods for Surface Chemistry </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;We have seen what all can be on the surface of carbon black.  Now, let us turn our attention to the more standard test methods and show what these methods actually indicate as far as surface chemistry and surface coatings.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Many of these tests may sound familiar.  They &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;include &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;heat loss (commonly called moisture), toluene discoloration, volatiles, pH, titration of surface groups and spectrometric methods.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000012.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="13" xmlns="">
		<title>Heat Loss (105 ºC) or Moisture Level</title>
		<content>Heat Loss (105 ºC) or Moisture Level                      O O O O O HO COOH   OH C  O OHH OHH   A sample is weighed before and after heating Mostly water is evaporated, but some low weight polyaromatics may also evaporate </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;A test most will be familiar with is heat loss at 105 &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;degree &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Centigrade.  In this test, the sample is weighed before and after heating for an hour.  Typically, this only drives off water and, hence, many people call this a moisture test.  There could be some lower molecular weight polyaromatics driven off also.  This is usually not a concern since the weight of the polyaromatics is very low when compared to the typical levels of water at 0.2 to 1 percent found using this test.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000013.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="14" xmlns="">
		<title>Toluene Extraction</title>
		<content> Toluene Extraction OOOOHOCOOHOOHCOOHH OHH   Toluene extracts the polyaromatics from a sample  Polyaromatics extracted discolor the toluene  Amount of discoloration is measured with a specific  wavelength of light source  Polyaromatics have little effect on performance  Must be extremely low in plastics for food contact  Light  </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;The toluene discoloration test is where the carbon black is extracted with toluene.  The amount of discoloration of the toluene - usually yellow to red - is measured at a given wavelength of light and is reported in percent transmittance.  The higher the number the less poly aromatics present in the sample.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Remember that polyaromatics play a minor role in impacting the performance of the carbon black.  However, these polyaromatic compounds must be extremely low when the carbon black is to be used in plastics that will come in contact with food.  The maximum content of these polyaromatics is controlled and defined by regulation in some countries.  We must be aware of these regulations if our products are marketed in these regions.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000014.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="15" xmlns="">
		<title>Volatiles  </title>
		<content>Volatiles                 O O O O HO COOH OOHCO OHH OHH    A sample is heated to 950o C   Oxygen groups and polyaromatics vaporize  A small amount of oxygen may survive the test </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;For volatiles, the sample of carbon black is weighed and heated in a covered crucible to 950 &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;°C &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;.  The sample is then again weighed after heating.  The loss in weight is recorded as the % volatile.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;At &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;this &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;high temperature, both the water and the polyaromatics are vaporized.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;However, most of the weight loss is due to the oxygen groups being removed from the carbon black at this high temperature.  Most oxygen groups will not survive; however, there may be a small amount of oxygen left on the surface at the end of the test.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;This test is a very good indicator of how much the carbon black is oxidized on its surface. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000015.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="16" xmlns="">
		<title>pH</title>
		<content>pH                      O O O O O HO COOH   OH C  O OHH OHH   OHH H+  OH- Basic &amp;gt; 7 pH units Acidic &amp;lt; 7 pH units </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;pH &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;is the amount of ionized hydrogen present in a water solution of carbon black.  A measurement of 7 is the &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;pH &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;of distilled water which is considered neutral.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Depending on the surface groups, carbon black can be either acidic, less than 7 &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;pH &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;units or basic, greater than 7 &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;pH &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;units.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Typical furnace grades are basic as illustrated here because the pyrone groups are plentiful and extract Hydrogen ions from the water causing the &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;pH &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;of the water to be basic that is greater than 7 &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;pH &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;units.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;There are acidic groups as illustrated by the purple oval around the carboxylate group.  These carboxylate groups dominate the surface chemistry where the carbon black has been purposefully oxidized.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Typical &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;pH's &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;for oxidized furnace blacks are from 3  to 5.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000016.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="17" xmlns="">
		<title>Acid and Base Titrations</title>
		<content>Titration – solutions of unknown concentrations of chemicals are reacted with solutions of known concentration to estimate the concentrations in the unknown solution    Weak to strong acids and bases are used to determine the amount of each compound within a sample Not an exact method Allows for grouping of different oxygen groups to get a feel of the ratios in different carbon blacks Acid and Base Titrations </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Lastly, to test for specific oxygen surface groups both titration and spectrometric methods are used.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;In a titration, a &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;solution&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; of unknown &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;concentration&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; is reacted with a solution of a known concentration in order to find out more about the unknown solution, usually its concentration. One of the most common titrations is an acid-base titration.  In our case, the unknown solution will contain the carbon black of interest.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Though very difficult, weak to strong bases and acids are used to determine the amount of acidic and basic groups in a set pH range.  This is not an exact science but allows for grouping of the different known oxygen containing chemistries to get a feel of the ratios in different carbon blacks.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000017.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="18" xmlns="">
		<title>X-ray Photoelectron Spectrometry</title>
		<content>                     O O O O O HO COOH   OH C  O OHH OHH          X-ray Photoelectron Spectrometry  X-Rays               </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;One spectrometry method used to determine surface chemistry is called X-ray photoelectron spectrometry.  In this test, the carbon black sample is exposed to x-rays and these interact with the groups on the surface to cause different wavelengths of light to be emitted depending on the chemistry of the groups.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;From the wavelengths of light and the amount of light coming off the surface, one can calculate the population density of the different groups present.  This technique can be very accurate in determining the type and amount of surface activity on the carbon black surface.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Now that you have been exposed to the surface chemistry of carbon black, you can begin to appreciate what a complex and useful product carbon black can be.  Also, how complex and difficult it can be to produce consistently for the applications of all our customers with different applications.  This area of carbon black chemistry is an opportunity for future development of new and exciting products.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000018.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="19" xmlns="">
		<title>END</title>
		<content>END </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;This is the end&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; of module 2.4 Surface Chemistry.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000019.jpg"/>
	</section>
</document-metadata>
