<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<document-metadata version="1.0" xmlns="http://breeze.macromedia.com/">
	<document-info>
		<title>1.4 Introduction to Carbon Black Manufacturing</title>
		<summary></summary>
		<author/>
		<keywords/>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000001.jpg"/>
		<view-link href="/viewer.swf?slide={{position}}" href-html5="/" href-swf="/viewer.swf?slide={{position}}"/>
	</document-info>
	<section type="slide" position="1" xmlns="">
		<title>1.4 Introduction to Carbon Black Manufacturing</title>
		<content>1.4 Introduction to Carbon Black Manufacturing </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;This is module 1.4 Introduction to Carbon Black Manufacturing.  In this session, we will learn the primary manufacturing process steps and unit operations required to produce a carbon black.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000001.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="2" xmlns="">
		<title>Production Processes</title>
		<content> Production Processes Continuous process in closed vessels Sophisticated process control systems High Efficiency Flexibility in manufacturing various grades Thermal Black Process Furnace Process Reactor   Channel Black Plant Worker  Original Channel Black Plant  </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Carbon black has been produced since antiquity as a pigmenting agent for inks and paints.  With the advent of the automobile in the early twentieth century and the discovery that adding carbon black to rubber increased the lifetime of a tire, demand for carbon black has increased significantly.  Therefore, manufacturing methods have been developed to produce large volumes of carbon black.  The most significant change in manufacturing occurred with the development of the &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;channel black process plants &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;in the early twentieth century.  These plants used natural gas to produce the carbon black in fairly open hot houses under poorly controlled combustion conditions.  These plants had &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;high levels of black smoke emissions&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;.  In the early days of air flights, it was said by many pilots that the channel black plants of West Texas in the United States could be used as a locator for flight paths due to the emissions of black smoke that could be seen for many kilometers.  Thermal black plants also used natural gas in a &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;thermal decomposition process &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;to make very large particle carbon blacks.  Natural gas was a low cost feedstock and practically a waste product of oil exploration.  Prior to World War two, a new type &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;furnace reactor &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;was developed that used heavy aromatic liquid &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;feedstocks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; for producing carbon blacks.  This furnace reactor allowed continuous operations in closed vessels that eliminated smoke emissions.  It also provided opportunity for sophisticated process control systems to reduce variability in the process.  This new process is &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;highly efficient &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;and has flexibility in manufacturing &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;a wide variety of products &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;used in all types of applications.  Most carbon black manufacturers today use this process, although elements of the older processes are still in existence to produce some unique products that are still used by some customers.  This module will focus on this manufacturing process known as the &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;furnace black process&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000002.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="3" xmlns="">
		<title>Carbon Black Manufacturing Plant</title>
		<content>  Carbon Black Manufacturing&amp;#x0A;Plant </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Modern carbon black companies such as Himadri have the latest furnace black technology for producing carbon blacks.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;These&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; plants are efficient, clean and environmentally friendly.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000003.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="4" xmlns="">
		<title>Raw Materials</title>
		<content> High Aromatic Content Hydrocarbons Catalytic Crackers, Ethylene Crackers, Coal Tar Distilleries U.S. Gulf Coast - FCC Oils  Local Sources – EBO oils China – Coal Tar Oils Himadri – Anthracene Oils from pipeline  Raw Materials </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;The major raw material used for the production of carbon black in the furnace black process is &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;high aromatic content hydrocarbons&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;.  Most commonly, the source of this major raw material is refinery catalytic crackers, ethylene crackers, or coal&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  textDecoration="underline"&gt;tar&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;distilleries.  In the industry, these &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;feedstocks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; are referred to as FCC oils, EBO oils, and Anthracene oils respectively.  Large low-cost supplies of FCC oils are found at refineries on the Gulf Coast of the United States and these oils are delivered to carbon black plants around the world in &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;large oil tankers&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;EBO oils &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;are generally available from local ethylene producers and are normally in relatively small quantities.  These supplies are delivered primarily by rail car or truck tankers.  China is a large producer of &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;anthracene&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; oils from steel manufacture but consumes most of their supply internally.  Some carbon black manufacturers have their own feedstock source such as Himadri which has refined &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;anthracene&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; oils on site that can be delivered by pipeline directly to the carbon black plant.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Other raw materials that are used in the carbon black process are water, potassium salts, and pelleting binders.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Electrical power and steam are used as energy sources in the process but also are generated as a by-product using the energy in the waste gas produced by the carbon black furnace process. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000004.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="5" xmlns="">
		<title>Unit Operations</title>
		<content> Reaction Transport Drying Separation Packaging Pelletization         Heat Exchange  Unit Operations </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;In this program, we will explore the major unit operations of a modern carbon black plant.  We will start where the process of carbon black formation takes place in the &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;reactor&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; and follow the process through &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;heat exchange&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;separation&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;pelletization&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;drying&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;transport&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; and &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;packaging&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;.  After packaging a final product is transported by truck to our customer in small bags or bulk bags.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000005.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="6" xmlns="">
		<title>Reaction</title>
		<content>Reaction  Reaction    </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;The reaction process is the initial process in the production of carbon black.  A heavy aromatic oil is cracked at high temperatures into carbon, hydrogen and various combustion gases.  The carbon black is a powder agglomerate suspended in a gas mixture.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000006.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="7" xmlns="">
		<title>Reaction</title>
		<content>   Temperature Controlled by air to fuel ratios   Reaction Time Controlled by Water Quench   Potassium Controls Structure   Reaction </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;The core of the carbon black furnace process is the reactor.  In the typical tread reactor a high temperature flame is generated in the first stage of the reactor, the combustion section, using a mixture of a hot process air and a fuel.  This fuel may be a light fuel oil or a gas such as natural gas.  A highly aromatic feedstock oil is injected into this hot flame at levels to generate a carbon black powder in the gas stream.  The reaction mixture of carbon black and gases generates heat and the reaction is completed by injecting quench water in the reactor.  The mixed reaction temperature is directly related to the particle size of the carbon black formed.  Potassium salts are added to the reactor in a controlled manner to inhibit the growth of carbon black aggregates forming during the reaction process.  As a result a defined particle size and aggregate size for the carbon black can be controlled and produced.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000007.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="8" xmlns="">
		<title>Reaction</title>
		<content> Fuel Reactor Geometry defines the quality and quantity of carbon black. Distinguishes the range of products a carbon black unit can produce. Fixes range of carbon black unit can efficiently produce. Hard black reactor – Tread Soft black reactor – Carcass Specialty reactor - Various Reaction </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;The geometry of the reactor and the mixing techniques used in mixing the various fuels and feedstocks in the reactor as the reaction process takes place, define the quality and quantity of the carbon black produced.  The design of the reactor also typically fixes the range of carbon black products a carbon black unit can efficiently produce.  For rubber grade products there is typically a reactor design for the “hard” black products called a tread reactor and a design for the “soft” black products called the carcass reactor.  These designs are usually proprietary and unique for each manufacturer.  Specialty products may require other reactor geometries and specialty raw materials.  These may include elements of both the furnace designs and other special techniques.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000008.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="9" xmlns="">
		<title>Carbon Black Tread Reactor</title>
		<content> Carbon Black Tread Reactor First stage flame  1500°C to 2000°C Carbon Black Formation 1300°C to 1800°C Refractory Lining </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;This drawing represents the stages of reaction as previously described but for a reactor with a slightly different geometry. The &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;first stage flame &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;may &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  textDecoration="underline"&gt;range&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; from 1500 degrees Celsius to over 2000 degrees &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  textDecoration="underline"&gt;Celsius.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;  The &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;carbon black formation section&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; experiences temperatures ranging from about 1300 degrees Celsius to about 1800 degrees &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  textDecoration="underline"&gt;Celsius&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;.  As stated earlier, the mixed reaction temperature in the &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;carbon black formation stage &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;is directly related to the particle size and the particle size distribution of the carbon black formed.   This drawing shows the high temperature &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;refractory linings &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;of the reactor required to withstand the high temperatures generated in various stages of the reaction process.  Other style reactors will be discussed in more detail later.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000009.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="10" xmlns="">
		<title>Heat Exchange</title>
		<content>Heat Exchange Heat Exchange   Reduces costs  Recovered heat increases efficiency Air preheat important in reaction </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;An important step in the efficiency of the carbon black process is the heat recovery performed during the production process.  Of primary importance is the process air preheater.  This air preheater recovers heat generated in the reactor and transfers the heat to the process air which is recycled to the first stage of the reactor.  Since the reaction itself requires heat to break the &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  textDecoration="underline"&gt;hydrocarbon&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; bonds in the aromatic feedstock, this recovered heat &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;makes the reaction process more efficient&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;.  The heat recovery area may also include heat exchangers to heat feedstock oil, heat fuel, heat water, and generate steam.  The more economic ways that are found to recover this heat adds to the efficiency of the line and generally &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;reduces the cost &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;of manufacturing.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000010.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="11" xmlns="">
		<title>Heat Exchange</title>
		<content>                         Boiler Oil Preheater Water Water Water Heat Exchange &amp;lt; 300 °C </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;There are process temperature limitations due to materials of construction so the hot gas temperature may have to be controlled &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;prior to the air preheater&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;upstream of oil preheaters &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;and &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;before collection in the primary bag filter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;.  The collection bag filters have fabric bags that are limited in temperature normally to less than 300 degrees Centigrade depending on the fabric used.  Therefore water may be added at various stages to achieve this temperature and to protect the materials of construction of other equipment.  Some water may be added upstream of the oil preheater to &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;prevent overheating and coking &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;of the feedstock in the preheater.  Any water added provides temperature reduction and control but also decreases the relative efficiency of the process and dilutes the energy available in the off gas that is used for generating heat in other parts of the process.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000011.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="12" xmlns="">
		<title>Process Air Heat Exchanger</title>
		<content>  Process Air Heat Exchanger </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;These are examples of high temperature process air heat exchangers that are commonly used in the industry.  These preheaters are shell and tube type.  There are several other designs depending on the requirements for heat recovery and the investment costs.  Commercial shell and tube heat exchangers have become a standard in the industry and are used in most plants.  Some manufacturers have their own proprietary designs.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000012.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="13" xmlns="">
		<title>Separation</title>
		<content>Separation Carbon Black from Reactor is Filtered from Reactor Gases and Water Vapor Use Cylindrical  Fabric Bags Separation    Dirty Gas Inlet Clean Gas Outlet </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;The next process step we will review is the process of separation. In the &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;separation&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; operation, the carbon black is separated from the gas stream.  Typically this is done using &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;bag filters &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;which have cylindrical fabric bags suspended in the filter body either on wire cages or using tension of the bags.  The carbon black laden gases are forced through the fabric and the carbon black collects on the surface of the filter.  Some type of cleaning method is used to automatically remove the collected carbon black from the surface of the filter bags.  The methods commonly available are reverse flow of process gases, pulse jets of external gases, and mechanical shaking.  The powder carbon black is collected in the hoppers of the filter body where it can be discharged using screw conveyors or rotary &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  textDecoration="underline"&gt;valves&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;.  A powder conveying system or screw conveyor transports the carbon black to the next step for further processing or packaging as a powder.  In some cases, cyclonic collectors are used upstream of the bag filters to reduce the particle loading going to the cloth bag filters.  If a powder pneumatic conveying system is used for conveying, the carbon black powder is mixed with &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  textDecoration="underline"&gt;air&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; which again must be removed by filtration.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000013.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="14" xmlns="">
		<title>Process Bag Filters</title>
		<content>  Two types of filters Repressuring bag filters Pulse jet filters Process Bag Filters </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;There are two major types of filters used in the carbon black industry.  Repressuring filters use reverse flow of filtered gases to clean the carbon black from the fabric bags.  Pulse jet filters use an external high-pressure gas to generate a shock wave to clean the carbon black from the fabric bags.  The pulse jet filters are usually smaller in size and with lower installed cost than the repressuring filters.  Himadri use pulse jet filters.  These filters are usually 99.9 percent efficient in removing carbon black powder from the gas stream.  It is important to change any bags that have defects and may leak carbon black to the atmosphere.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000014.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="15" xmlns="">
		<title>Energy System</title>
		<content>Energy System           </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;The reactor gases with water vapor are commonly called tail gases or waste gases.  These gases cleaned of carbon black, are a low energy value fuel that can be used in other parts of the process such as for heating the wet pellets in a dryer and for generating steam in a boiler that can be used for generating electrical power.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000015.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="16" xmlns="">
		<title>Process Bag Filters</title>
		<content> Process Bag Filters </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;These are photos of the typical cylindrical compartment pulse-jet bag filters used by Himadri.  In this filter shown, 480 fabric filter bags are in each filter compartment.  These bags lose porosity over time and must be changed.  This is one of the most expensive maintenance requirements for carbon black plants.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000016.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="17" xmlns="">
		<title>Pelletization</title>
		<content> Pelletization   Pelletization   </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Some carbon black is marketed to customers who want the product in powder form.  This powder is typically easier to mix in some liquids and requires less mixing power to incorporate.  Packaging directly from the process as a powder also eliminates further processing and energy consumption.   However, most customers prefer carbon black granules, also called pellets or beads,  which require a separate pelletization process to agglomerate the powder into the round pellets.  The resulting pellet size averages plus or minus 3 millimeters in diameter.  These pellets are higher in density than the powder form therefore can be packaged in more compact containers which can reduce storage and transportation costs.  There are two common methods used to pelletize carbon black – dry pelletizing and wet pelletization.  Himadri uses wet pelletization&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000017.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="18" xmlns="">
		<title>Wet Pelletization</title>
		<content>Water mixed with carbon black powder. At saturation point viscosity peaks Pin circulation generates round agglomerates (pellets) Pelletizer motor senses peak power Additives improve other properties of carbon black  Allows the pellet size and hardness to be controlled over a wider range  Excellent bulk handling properties - Minimum dusting Handles very well in bulk containers and aggressive transport systems Wet Pelletization       </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;The wet pelleting process is used in much of the industry for pelletizing carbon black.  The pin pelletizer used is a cylindrical body containing pins that are installed on a rotating shaft.  The powder carbon black is introduced to the pelletizer where water is mixed with the powder until the saturation of the mixture peaks.  The pin circulation creates granules that are thrown outward to the inner surface of the machine where the agglomerates are rounded by tumble agglomeration.  The pelletizer senses the peak power at the saturation point and this power setting can be controlled by altering the water content on the black mixture.   Pelletizing additives may be introduced in the pelletizer to improve the performance of the carbon black including pellet hardness and dispersion.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The pelletizer allows the pellet size and pellet hardness to be controlled over a wider range.  The pelletization results in excellent bulk handling properties with minimum dusting.  The wet pellets retain their properties in bulk containers and aggressive transport systems.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;A wide variety of proprietary and commercial wet pelletizers are used in the industry.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000018.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="19" xmlns="">
		<title>Drying</title>
		<content>Drying Wet Pellets ~ 40% - 60% water Dry Pellets  &amp;lt; 1% water Dryers Types    Indirect Fired Rotary Dryers    Indirect-Direct Fired Rotary Dryers    Direct Fired Tray Dryers    Fluidized Bed Dryers      Drying  </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;After wet pellets are formed they range from about 40% to nearly 60% water or moisture.  The level of water in the wet pellets  depends directly on the structure of the carbon black.  These wet pellets must be dried to a level less than 1% since the customer does not want to purchase water.  This is done using using a dryer.  Several types of dryers are used in the industry including indirect fired rotary dryers, indirect-direct fired rotary dryers, direct fired tray dryers, and fluidized bed dryers which can be direct or indirect fired.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000019.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="20" xmlns="">
		<title>Drying</title>
		<content> Rotary Dryer  Rotary Dryer – Indirect Fired Carbon Black wet pellets introduced at Inlet Rotating at 3 to 6 rpm Hot gases surround drying drum Temperature of Carbon Black raised to 180 C Carbon Black discharged to transport system Dryer Inlet Dryer Discharge   Drying   </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;In a rotary dryer, the carbon black is discharged from the pelletizer into the inlet, internal side of the drying drum which is rotating at a speed of from 3 to 6 rpm.  Hot gases surround the drum shell and the heat is transmitted internally into the carbon black bed which is tumbling inside the drying drum at levels of a few millimeters to levels of about 300 millimeters depending on the design and operating criteria of the dryer.  If this is a indirect-direct rotary dryer, hot gases from the combustor are also introduced into the drying drum to increase the heat transfer on the inside of the drum.  In some cases, the direct contact of combustion gas is detrimental to the quality of the carbon black.  Typically, indirect-direct heated dryers have more capacity for the same dimensions than indirect heated dryers.  The temperature of the bed of carbon black is measured and the carbon black is discharged at temperatures that can confirm there is no water remaining in the carbon black pellets, usually about 180 degrees Centigrade.  The carbon black is then discharged from the dryer and transported to storage and packaging.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000020.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="21" xmlns="">
		<title>Carbon Black Dryers</title>
		<content>                 1 2  n   A Dryer Drum    Inside A Dryer Drum with a Snorkel Carbon Black Dryers </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;These are photographs of carbon black rotary dryers of different designs showing the external design.  There is also an example of the internal dryer drum cylinder with a pipe called a snorkel which is used to introduce hot gases into a direct-indirect fired dryer.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000021.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="22" xmlns="">
		<title>Transport</title>
		<content>Transport Transport Powder Reactor gases Dryer gases Rotary valves Pellets Rotary valves Bucket elevators Screw conveyors     </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;In the carbon black process there are several modes of transport of the carbon black that we will discuss.  The first is the transport of carbon black powders using gases.  This is common in the movement of carbon black from the reactor through the filters, the movement of carbon black from the internal drum of the dryer through the filters, and from the pneumatic systems conveying carbon black to filters to be further processed.  Carbon black is also moved using rotary valves from one stage of a process to another to limit the process gases from being entrained in an undesired area of the process.  One example of this is the movement of powder carbon black from the process bag filter to the pneumatic conveyor.  This &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  textDecoration="underline"&gt;operation &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;can also be done with a screw conveyor.  Finally, the dried pellets from the dryer are transported through rotary valves to a bucket elevator which lifts the pellets to the height of the bulk storage tanks and then into screw conveyors which distribute the carbon black to the various bulk tanks.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000022.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="23" xmlns="">
		<title>Pneumatic Conveying of Powder</title>
		<content>                                                                                                                                                       FIRC    PIRC                                 TIA    Dust &amp;amp; Rerun Streams  Main Process Filter Conveying Filter Surge Tank Mikro Exhaust                                                             PIC CF1	 	 Pneumatic Conveying System CF2 CF3 CV3 CV2      Atmospheric          Silencer        Rotary Valves  Pipeline   Fans or Blowers    Pneumatic Conveying of Powder </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;In this flow diagram you will see an arrangement of fans and piping that is commonly referred to as a dilute phase pneumatic conveying system.  In this system the carbon black powder is discharged from the filter through rotary valves into a stream of air in a pipeline going from the ground level under the filter to another collection filter on top of the surge tank.  At the surge bin, the powder is normally discharged through a rotary valve or lobe feeder then processed into granules or pellets. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000023.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="24" xmlns="">
		<title>Pellet Transport and Storage</title>
		<content>  Screw Conveyor   Pellet Transport and Storage     </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;The dry pellets from the dryer are discharged by gravity flow into a bucket elevator which uses a series of small buckets on a chain to lift the pellets up to the height of the bulk silos or bulk storage tanks.  The buckets then discharge the dry pellets into a screw conveyor that conveys and distributes the pellets to storage.   Other types of distribution may be designed for the horizontal pellet transport including belt conveyors.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000024.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="25" xmlns="">
		<title>Packaging</title>
		<content>Packaging Packaging Other Markets Bulk Trucks Bulk Rail Bulk Bags Small Bags – Paper and Plastic India Bulk Bags - ~ 1 Ton Small Bags – 20 kgs   </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;The final step in our process is the packaging of carbon black.  In some countries the carbon black is packaged in bulk trucks and rail cars for transport to large customers.  The use of these systems are dependent upon the infrastructures available in the region for transport such as roads and rails.  Also, the receiving facilities of the customer must be designed to handle these type of containers and volumes of carbon black.  In India, most of the carbon is delivered using bulk bags that are approximately one ton in weight and paper or polyethylene bags that are stacked for transport and normally weigh 20 kilograms each.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000025.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="26" xmlns="">
		<title>Packages and Transport to Customers</title>
		<content>Paper Bags Bulk Bags   Packages and Transport to Customers </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Our customer wants to have a carbon black product that can be handled in his plant with low carbon black emissions and clean conditions for his employees.  Also, the packaging must identify the product and any special health considerations for the employees that will be discharging the product and using the product in the customer’s process.  Our packaging systems will be world class since many of our products go to the export market and are shipped around the world.  Shown here are Himadri products in &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;25 kilogram weight paper bags &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;stacked on pallets and &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt;one ton bulk bags&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;.  In India, the packaged product is commonly shipped by truck to the customer.  For the export market, the packages may be moved to an export container where they will be transported by ship to external ports.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000026.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="27" xmlns="">
		<title>Carbon Black Process Unit Operations</title>
		<content>ReactionTransportDryingSeparationPackagingPelletizationHeat Exchange Carbon Black Process Unit Operations </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;In this module, we have introduced a common, simplified carbon black process used in the industry.  Other unit operations may be in a final plant design such as processes that include contamination or grit reduction, contaminate separation, pellet fines removal, pellet cooling, and energy systems such as boilers and electrical generators.  In this module, we introduced the carcass reactor and specialty reactors but did not discuss details.  Hopefully, the topics introduced here will encourage you to further explore this interesting chemical operation. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000027.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="28" xmlns="">
		<title>END</title>
		<content>END  </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;This is the end of Module 1.4 Introduction to Carbon Black Manufacturing.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000028.jpg"/>
	</section>
</document-metadata>
