<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<document-metadata version="1.0" xmlns="http://breeze.macromedia.com/">
	<document-info>
		<title>7.4 Wet Pelletization Part 2</title>
		<summary></summary>
		<author/>
		<keywords/>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000001.jpg"/>
		<view-link href="/viewer.swf?slide={{position}}" href-html5="/" href-swf="/viewer.swf?slide={{position}}"/>
	</document-info>
	<section type="slide" position="1" xmlns="">
		<title>7.4. Wet Pelletization</title>
		<content>7.4. Wet Pelletization Part 2 No Audio </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;This is the module 7.4. Wet&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; Pelletization: Part 2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000001.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="2" xmlns="">
		<title>Wet Pellet Quality Tests</title>
		<content>Fines Assesses the amount of unpelleted product Reported as a percentage of the total pellet stream tested Attrition Assesses the amount of pellet breakdown caused by handling Reported as a percentage of the total pellet stream tested Pellet Size Distribution  Shows uniformity in pellet size Pellets should be uniform in size Individual Pellet Hardness Tells how hard the pellets are for a uniform pellet size Given as the force required to crush a pellet Wet Pellet Quality Tests Pellet Tests Fines Attrition Pellet Size Distribution Individual Pellet Hardness Pour Density Heat Loss </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Pellet quality is assessed on our products as requested and agreed by our customers.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;In our plants, we normally use the following quality tests for evaluating the product prior to shipment to our customers:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Fines, Attrition, Pellet Size Distribution, Individual Pellet Hardness, Pour Density, And Heat Loss&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The fines test assesses the amount of &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;unpelleted&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; product, small pellets  or fractured pellets that are in the final product stream.  This test is reported as a percentage of the total pellet stream tested.  We normally would want the lowest valuable possible.  Fines can be examined microscopically to determine the state of the pellet development and destruction.  Fines are normally detrimental to a customer’s plant environment and product quality. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The attrition test assess the amount of pellet breakdown the pellets will incur due to abrasion and breakage during handling.  This value is also reported as a percentage of the total pellet stream tested. Attrition roughly predicts pellet breakdown in transport of a product which means the fines increase from our plant and prior to the customer’s use.  Usually, the customer would like to have a low value.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Pellet size distribution shows the uniformity of the pellet size.  The test separates the pellet into various size fractions.  Each fraction can be examined microscopically to learn more about the pelletization completion.  Normally, we would like to have as uniform pellet size as possible.  That means the standard deviation in size will be low.  A customer may want to have larger or smaller pellets in his process depending on the balance between ease of pellet dispersion in his product and transport properties.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Individual pellet hardness determines how hard the pellets are for a uniform pellet size in the product stream.  Further tests can be performed on different pellet sizes to assess how well the pellets may disperse in a customer’s product.  Again, we would like to have as uniform pellet hardness as possible. This test is reported as the force required to crush a pellet.  Lower values indicate softer pellets and higher values indicate harder pellets.  A customer may want to have soft or harder pellets in his process depending on the balance between ease of pellet dispersion in his product and transport properties.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000002.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="3" xmlns="">
		<title>Wet Pellet Quality Tests</title>
		<content>Pour Density  Individual Pellet Density Fixed volume of pelleted product is evaluated to determine the density of the pellet mass Want a high pellet density to have the lowest cost per unit volume for transport Heat Loss Assesses the amount of weight lost when the product is heated above the boiling point of water Testing the powder determines if water remains after the powder is formed Testing from the pelletizer can determine if the proper amount of water is used during pelletization Testing from the dryer can determine if pellets are adequately dried Wet Pellet Quality Tests  Pellet Tests( continued) </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Pour density is used to assess the mass pellet density.  A fixed volume of &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;pelleted&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; product is evaluated to determine the density of the pellet mass.  This test is usually directly related to the individual pellet density, but the pellet size can also influence this test since voids between the pellets are also measured.  Normally, we would want to have a high pellet density in order to have the lowest cost per unit volume of product for transport.  The pour density is directly related to the product carbon black structure or oil absorption number.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Heat loss assesses the amount of loss of weight of a product when heated above the boiling point of water.  This test is used to evaluate the amount of water retained in the product.  The customer does not want to have water in place of carbon black in his process.  In many of our customer’s processes, water is detrimental to the final product, even in quantities less than one percent of the weight of the carbon black product.  The heat loss test on the carbon black powder can determine if water has been carried from the process water sprays, has condensed in some vessel in our process, or has been absorbed from the atmosphere.  The source of high water content normally needs to be determined and corrected.  The heat loss test on the carbon black pellets from the pelletizer can determine if the proper water content for optimum pelletization has been added.  The heat loss test after the dryer can determine if the pellets have been adequately dried prior to shipment to the customer and have been adequately stored to prevent absorption of atmospheric moisture.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Manufacturing specifications for each of the above properties are defined for each product in our plant.  Individual customers may have particular specifications applicable for their process or products.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Suffice it to say, that before any tests are performed, a representative sample of the final product needs to be used for the assessment of those properties.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000003.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="4" xmlns="">
		<title>Pellet Images</title>
		<content>   Not Round &amp;amp; Rough Not Round &amp;amp; Smooth Round &amp;amp; Rough Round &amp;amp; Smooth   Pellet Images </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;In addition to the pellet quality tests mentioned before, the visual appearance of the pellets is also useful in evaluating the performance of the pellets. In general, pellets that are both round and smooth give the best properties of flowability for our customers end use.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The differences in these properties can be seen in the above photographs, taken using a microscope. The first picture has pellets that are not round and are rough, not smooth. The second picture shows pellets that are round and rough. The third picture shows pellets that are not round but smooth. The last picture shows pellets that are round and smooth.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Our goal is to produce these type of pellets: round and smooth.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000004.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="5" xmlns="">
		<title>Pellet Roundness and Production Rates</title>
		<content>Pellet Roundness and Production Rates    This is common to all pelletizers. If residence time is too short then pellet quality deteriorates    </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;This graph shows how the roundness of the pellet is affected by the throughput or residence time in the pelletizer. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;In this example, the roundness of the pellets deteriorates significantly after about 3000 liters (3000 kilograms) per hour of water. Therefore, this pelletizer design is not recommended for rates above 3000 kilograms per hour of water. If this throughput is exceeded, a second pelletizer should be installed in parallel in the process.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The high throughput can be due to the absolute amount of reactor carbon black production. However, it can also be the result of instability of the process with powder carbon black surging through the pelletizer. It is important that the carbon black feeding to the pelletizer be maintained at a constant rate for good pelletization.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;This phenomenon of throughput limitation is common to all pelletizer designs because of the importance of residence time in pellet formation.  If the residence time is too short, the pellet quality deteriorates.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000005.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="6" xmlns="">
		<title>Water Injection</title>
		<content>Water injection spray Tangential water spray shows good results  Water pressure Increase (up to a maximum) improves pellet properties  Water injection spray locations Multiple injection points causes Decreases pellet size uniformity Increases formation of lumps and fines Injection as close as possible to the carbon black inlet for normal production throughput Water Injection </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;The kind of water injector plays a crucial role in the wet pelletization process. The tangential spray has shown to produce smaller pellets and a narrower pellet size distribution.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;With increasing water pressure the droplet size is reduced producing more uniform wetting of the powder. Pellet size shifts to smaller pellets and the pellet size distribution narrows. However, too high water pressure could shift the pellet size distribution to larger sizes again.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The use of multiple water injection spray locations along the pelletizer leads to the formation of small pellets, lumps, and fines.  Multiple sprays also broadens the mean pellet size distribution so the pellet size is less uniform.  Pellets that have been wet with water are wet again, the pellets stick together and the remaining residence time in the pelletizer is not adequate to form uniform, round pellets. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;It has been established that, for design throughput, uniform injection of the water as close to the carbon black inlet of the pelletizer reduces fines, improves pellet roundness and produces more uniform pellet size. Further downstream water injection points may be used for low throughput (shorten the pelletizer effective length and, therefore the residence time).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000006.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="7" xmlns="">
		<title>Wet Pellet Optimum Pellet Moisture</title>
		<content>Wet Pellet Optimum Pellet Moisture OANOAN  All  cavities in the agglomerate are just filled with water Optimum moisture is 1% below capillary state  Higher OAN = higher water levels for pelletization   </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;The optimum pellet moisture on the wet pellets is defined by the oil absorption number or O-A-N of the carbon black as shown in the above graph. The capillary content is shown by the red line. This is the point where all the cavities in the carbon black agglomerate are just filled with water. By experimentation it has been found that the optimum moisture level is approximately 1% below the capillary state.  This level produces the smallest and hardest pellets. Higher oil absorption numbers on the carbon black require higher levels of water for good pelletization.  A carbon black with a pellet O-A-N of about 100 should have a water content of about 48 percent.   A carbon black with an O-A-N of 75 should have a water content of about 40 percent.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000007.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="8" xmlns="">
		<title>Wet Pellet Optimum Pellet Moisture</title>
		<content>Pellets with optimum pellet moisture appear dry Measure water content to achieve the optimum pelletization Multiple samples Larger and wetter pellets due to instability in the carbon black feed Safest way to prevent excursions is to keep the pellets wetter Ideal: Standard Deviation &amp;lt;0.4% water  Wet Pellet Optimum Pellet Moisture </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Pellets with optimum pellet moisture tend to appear relatively dry to our operators.  The best way to achieve the optimum pelletization moisture is to measure the water content of the pellets as they leave the pelletizer and adjust the pellet quality based on this measurement.  Multiple samples need to be measured prior to making adjustments to the water rate on the pelletizer to assure that the variation in water level is determined and an average value for the water rate can be determined.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Typically our operators make larger and wetter pellets than required due to instability in the pelletizer carbon black feed.  The safest way to operate to prevent excursions of the pelletizer quality is to keep the pellets wetter than desired.  In order to optimize pellet moisture on the wet pellets, the system must have stable carbon black feed to the pelletizer.   Ideally, we would like to have a standard deviation of the percent water of less than 0.4 percent.  This level is typically not possible with our current process design due to poor stability of the carbon black feed. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000008.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="9" xmlns="">
		<title>Pellet Size vs. Water Content </title>
		<content> Pellet Size vs. Water Content  Smaller pellets tend to be easier for customers to use Measure multiple samples of wet pellets Operators tend to make larger and wetter pellets Properly set the power setting on the motor   Pellet size increases as water content is increased  Carbon black powder flow rates should be consistent </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;As you see in this graph, pellet size increases as the water content is increased on the wet pellets.    By changing the water content of the wet pellets from 45.8% to 48.1% the average pellet size increased by about 50%.  Because of the instability in our carbon black feed our operators tend to make a wetter and larger pellet than desired.   As discussed in an earlier session, smaller pellets tend to be easier for our customer to disperse in his compound. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;We can control the percent moisture on the wet pellets by properly setting the power setting on the motor of the wet pelletizer and measuring multiple samples of the wet pellets for water content.  Carbon black powder flow rates must be consistent to control the content with the desired standard deviation of 0.4 percent.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000009.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="10" xmlns="">
		<title>Additives: Binders</title>
		<content>Binder Type Fixed by historical experience with the customers Changes are approved by a management of change then controlled experimentation Molasses from the sugar industry Some carbon black manufacturers use lignosulfonates from the paper industry  Corn syrup for purity of products Added at solid levels &amp;lt;1% by weight Too much binder can lead to dispersion problems Additives: Binders </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;The type of binder used in a pelletization process is normally fixed by historical experience with the customers of those products.  Changes to other binders are approved by a management of change and by controlled experimentation.  Our pellet binders are molasses from the sugar industry.  Many carbon black manufacturers use lignosulfonates from the paper industry or other sugar products as pellet binders.  In some cases, a product such as corn syrup&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;is used for specialty applications where purity is required.  These are approved raw materials.  The chemistry is discussed in a previous section.  Binders are typically added to the carbon black at solid levels less than 1% by weight.   The addition of a binder makes the pellet harder.  Too much binder can lead to dispersion problems for the customer and high ash content of the carbon black.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000010.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="11" xmlns="">
		<title>Other Additives: Hydrocarbons</title>
		<content>Hydrocarbons (diesel or kerosene) produce smaller, more spherical pellets Changes are approved by a management of change then controlled experimentation Only used in rare occasions when other methods have proven unsuccessful and approved by customer Occurs if the powder has residual oils from the reactor on the surface Other Additives: Hydrocarbons </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt; Some experiments have shown that the pellets are more spherical, smaller in size, and have less fines when a hydrocarbon liquid, such as kerosene or&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;diesel, is added in small quantities. The addition of a hydrocarbon liquid should be approved by a management of change and assured by experimentation on a product.  Hydrocarbons should only be used in rare occasions when achieving pellet quality by another means has been unsuccessful and when the product with such an additive is approved by the customer for that particular application. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Additionally carbon black powder which has residual oil from the reactor left on the surface, as evident by the toluene discoloration test, has the same effect of producing pellets that are more spherical, smaller in size and have less fines.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000011.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="12" xmlns="">
		<title>Pelletizer Variables - Temperatures</title>
		<content>Low Shell or Jacket Temperature Causes the formation of “cake” on the internal pelletizer surface Increases torque on the motor Cake lumps contaminate good pellets Carbon black temperature Higher temperatures make smaller, harder, and rounder pellets Pelletizing water temperature Higher temperatures make smaller, harder, and rounder pellets Pelletizer Variables - Temperatures </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Low jacket or shell temperature leads to the formation of a carbon black “cake” layer on the internal pelletizer surface.  The formation of this cake increases the torque on the motor and also produces vibration.  In an experimental control, for a jacket or shell temperature of 75 degrees Celsius, the motor power had to be increased by 25% to get the same pellet moisture and equivalent pellet quality.  A working point of 90 to 100 degrees Celsius is recommended for good pelletization with the temperature varying by no more than 5 degrees Celsius.  Cake formation in the pelletizer is also detrimental to good pellet quality because the cake breaks off the pelletizer during normal operation and shows up as lumps in the final pellet stream.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The temperature of the carbon black powder entering the pelletizer can influence the pellet size.  Higher temperatures tend to make smaller, harder, and rounder pellets.  It is important that the temperature of the carbon black be stable and maintained as high as possible with good insulation on the surge bin.  However, the upstream equipment such as the process bag filter and the pneumatic conveyor have a pronounced impact on the temperature of the carbon black and it is difficult to control this property in practice.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Higher pelletizing water temperatures have been shown to reduce pellet size and decrease fines and attrition.  However, at temperatures above 80 degrees Celsius, unwanted side effects including reduction of pellet hardness and reduction of mass pellet strength have been observed. The water temperature for good pelletization is usually determined during initial development of a product and remains constant thereafter.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000012.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="13" xmlns="">
		<title>Pelletizer Variables - Pressure</title>
		<content> Pressure or vacuum Maintained as neutral as possible Maintain a low differential between the pelletizer, surge bin, and dryer Differentials can influence gas flows that cause powder flows to be variable High air flows can cause powder to move too rapidly to be wetted properly Some plants install vacuums breaks Pelletizer Variables - Pressure </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Vacuum or pressure in the pelletizer should be maintained as nearly neutral as possible with a low differential pressure between the pelletizer and the surge bin and the pelletizer and dryer.  Pressure differential can influence gas flows in the pelletizer that can cause carbon black powder flow to be highly variable between the surge bin and the pelletizer.  Also, high gas flows in the pelletizer can cause powder to flow through the pelletizer to the dryer so rapidly that the carbon black is not wet properly with water.  The powder then becomes fines in the final product.  Some plants install vacuum breaks between the pelletizer and surge bin or between the pelletizer and dryer to avoid these type induced flows of the carbon black powder.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000013.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="14" xmlns="">
		<title>Quality Adjustments</title>
		<content>Quality Adjustments           Reduced at temperatures above 80oC       Higher surface area than desired Use the minimum required binder to achieve desired properties to reduce impact on other properties </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;If the process has been designed and set up properly, all sources of carbon black flow variation have been eliminated, and the pelletizing water flow and injection have been properly selected, three parameters remain for control of the pellet quality of the carbon black: the pelletizer rotational speed, the binder rate, and the pelletizing water temperature.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The chart shows how a change in these parameters affects the pellet property.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The pelletizer speed is normally established for each product to balance the final oil absorption number and the other pellet properties that it affects.   It is used primary for adjusting the mass pellet strength of the pellet and secondarily for adjusting the pellet size, pellet hardness and the pellet density.  It has been demonstrated that pellet fracture is promoted at very high speeds which decreases the pellet hardness.  The pelletizer speed is usually determined during initial development of a product and remains constant thereafter.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;As mentioned before, higher water temperatures reduces pellet size and decreases fines and attrition.  However, at temperatures above 80 degrees Celsius, unwanted side effects including reduction of pellet hardness and reduction of mass pellet strength have been observed. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Pelletizing binders&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span  fontWeight="bold"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;are used to achieve the desired pellet hardness and mass pellet strength of the carbon black pellets.  As a result, attrition of the pellets is reduced and less fines are observed in the final product.  Binders can impact the Iodine adsorption on the carbon black surface which is used to measure the surface area of the carbon black.   The Iodine number measurement on the final pelletized product is reduced as the binder on the carbon black is increased.  This results in the reactor product being produced at a higher surface area than desired.  This also affects other carbon black properties and reduces the carbon black yield.  It is important to use the minimum required binder needed to achieve the desired pellet properties to reduce impact of binders on other properties. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000014.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="15" xmlns="">
		<title>END</title>
		<content>END  </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;This is the &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;end of module &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;7.4. Wet&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; Pelletization: Part 2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000015.jpg"/>
	</section>
</document-metadata>
