<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<document-metadata version="1.0" xmlns="http://breeze.macromedia.com/">
	<document-info>
		<title>2.1 Carbon Black History</title>
		<summary></summary>
		<author/>
		<keywords/>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000001.jpg"/>
		<view-link href="/viewer.swf?slide={{position}}" href-html5="/" href-swf="/viewer.swf?slide={{position}}"/>
	</document-info>
	<section type="slide" position="1" xmlns="">
		<title>2.1 Carbon Black History</title>
		<content>2.1 Carbon Black History </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;This is the module&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; 2.1. C&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;arbon black history.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Carbon &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;black is one of the oldest manufactured products.  Today, you will find carbon black all around you - the print in newspapers, books and magazines, the reinforced rubber in your car tires and UV protected plastics in your home and work areas.  Let's now briefly explore the history of this fascinating substance.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000001.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="2" xmlns="">
		<title>First Use</title>
		<content>Cave Dwellers used Carbon Black as a black pigment in wall paintings at the beginning of recorded human history (30,000 BC).  First Use  </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;The art work that you are viewing is from the Chauvet-Pont-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;d'Arc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; (&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Showvay&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; Poon Doc&amp;quot;) cave in the southeastern part of France.  It is thought to be over 30,000 years old.  The primary pigment in this wall painting is carbon black.  This is one of the oldest drawings known and marks the beginning of recorded human history. Today, virtually all black and darker shades of color still contain carbon black as the pigment of choice.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000002.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="3" xmlns="">
		<title>First Known Production  Device </title>
		<content>The Chinese made carbon black before 3000 BC by burning vegetable oil in small lamps with ceramic covers. First Known Production &amp;#x0A;Device   Lampblack </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;The Chinese are known to have produced small quantities of carbon black before 3000 BC.  The ceramic lamp pictured was filled with vegetable oil then the sooty product from the flame was captured on a cool surface such as a ceramic bowl.  Later you will hear the term &amp;quot;lampblack&amp;quot; to describe a process that is still practiced today for production of carbon black.  The lamp pictured is the forerunner of that more modern process.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000003.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="4" xmlns="">
		<title>First Recorded Manufacture  of Lampblack</title>
		<content>Egyptian lampblack production process First Recorded Manufacture &amp;#x0A;of Lampblack  1600 BC Papyrus  Paper Papyrus + carbon black based water inks  Hand written records  Pulp-based paper  Printing press  </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;The ancient Egyptians actually set up a manufacturing facility and recorded the production of lampblack in this drawing.  The picture dates to around 1600 BC.  The paper that the Egyptians used was made from reeds and is called papyrus from which our modern term, paper, originates.  The papyrus with carbon black and water based inks formed the hand-written records for many hundreds of years until the advent of pulp-based paper and much later, the printing press.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000004.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="5" xmlns="">
		<title>Increases in Demand </title>
		<content>Prior to 1400 AD Few books Hand scribed  1439 AD - Gutenberg Printing Press Increases in Demand    Lampblack production became a wide-spread industry Carbon black  demand </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;In the early 1400's AD, there were very few books and most people could not read.   One of the best-known universities, Oxford in England, had only 122 books during this time.  They were so expensive that, if sold, one could have purchased a large farm with the proceeds.  The limited supply was in part due to each book having to be hand-scribed.  This ceased in 1439 AD when Gutenberg in Germany invented the printing press.  With this development came a dramatic increase in demand for carbon black.  Lampblack production became a wide-spread industry.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000005.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="6" xmlns="">
		<title>Reinforcement of Rubber</title>
		<content>Discovered in 1904 – carbon black reinforces rubber First used to reinforce tires in 1912 Took 10 more years for the American public to accept “black” tires versus white Amount of carbon black in rubber, especially in tires, dominates the huge volumes carbon black produced Reinforcement of Rubber   Carbon black  demand </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;The single most important event impacting the demand for carbon black came in 1904 with the discovery that carbon black reinforces rubber. Within eight years the first carbon black reinforced tires were being produced.  The service life of the tire was greatly increased with this addition of carbon black.  However, it took another ten years to convince a skeptical American public to change from a white tire to a black tire with all it's benefits.  The amount of carbon black in rubber and especially tires dominates the huge volumes of carbon black now produced throughout the world. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000006.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="7" xmlns="">
		<title>Early Manufacturing  Processes </title>
		<content>Prior to 1870 Only the Lampblack process is used to make carbon black Early Manufacturing &amp;#x0A;Processes  Collecting SystemAirOilModern Lampblack Process </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Before 1870, the lampblack process was the only one used to make carbon black.  The modern version of the lampblack process is illustrated here.  In this simple process, the carbon black is produced above a large pan of oil being burned in a slightly oxygen-starved flame.   A slight vacuum is pulled to suck the smoke into a collection system attached to a bag filter.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000007.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="8" xmlns="">
		<title>Progression of Technology</title>
		<content>1870 to 1943 – Channel process used Inefficient Conversion as low as 5% Environmentally unfriendly    Progression of Technology Channel Process  </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;In the late 1800's and until 1943, virtually all lampblack production was replaced by the channel process.  This process is based on burning natural gas under channels of iron filled with water to quench the reaction which causes the black to form.  To make large volumes of carbon black, the channel process required very many long buildings.  As you can tell from the drawing, the process was not cost efficient or environmentally friendly since much of the product escaped into the atmosphere.  Conversion of the carbon in the natural gas to carbon black ran as low as 5%.  There are no channel black production units left in the United States for these reasons. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000008.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="9" xmlns="">
		<title>Current Technology</title>
		<content> Furnace Process dominates production today This method produces 95% of carbon black world-wide Current Technology      70% Conversion rate70% conversion rate AIR Oil Gas or Fuel  </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;The method of manufacturing carbon black today is now dominated by the furnace process.  In many furnace reactors, such as the one shown here, a flame is generated by burning natural gas or a liquid fuel with preheated air.  In other furnace reactors, the oil is sprayed directly into the preheated air with part of the oil burning to provide the excess heat.  An oil is sprayed into the hot gases and the oil is “cracked” so the hydrocarbons separate into carbon black and hydrogen.  The smoke contains the carbon black and hydrogen along with the products of combustion: water, carbon monoxide, carbon dioxide and the non-reactive nitrogen.  It is estimated that at least 95% of all carbon black produced world-wide is by this method.  The system is flexible and efficient in converting the carbon in the oil to carbon black.  To enhance efficiency, the heat from the reaction is captured by preheating the air coming in for combustion.  Also, the low heat value off gases are used to fire boilers and dryers.  With these enhancements, the furnace process can convert at least 70% of the carbon going into the unit to carbon black - a far cry from the poorly performing channel process it replaced which had about 5% conversion.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000009.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="10" xmlns="">
		<title>END</title>
		<content>END </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;This is the end of module&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; 2.1. C&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;arbon black history.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000010.jpg"/>
	</section>
</document-metadata>
