<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<document-metadata version="1.0" xmlns="http://breeze.macromedia.com/">
	<document-info>
		<title>2.3 Surface Area</title>
		<summary></summary>
		<author/>
		<keywords/>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000001.jpg"/>
		<view-link href="/viewer.swf?slide={{position}}" href-html5="/" href-swf="/viewer.swf?slide={{position}}"/>
	</document-info>
	<section type="slide" position="1" xmlns="">
		<title>2.3 Surface Area</title>
		<content>2.3 Surface Area </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;This is the module 2.3. Surface Area.  We have already discussed structure and how it is one of the two most important properties measured for carbon black characterization.  Now we will discuss the other - surface area.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;You will see that an understanding of surface area builds on our understanding of carbon black's morphology discussed in the previous module.   &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000001.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="2" xmlns="">
		<title>Carbon Black Particle</title>
		<content> Carbon Black Particle  diameter Particle size directly impacts surface area  </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;The particle size of the carbon black directly impacts the surface area. We will explore this relationship later.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Note that the aggregate pictured has numerous particles fused together.  The average particle size is determined using many micrographs similar to the one here.  Many particles making up a representative population are measured for diameter.  This average diameter includes both very small and very large particles. Each type of carbon black has a characteristic average diameter of the particles and a related surface area. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000002.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="3" xmlns="">
		<title>Particle Size vs. Surface Area</title>
		<content>Particle Size vs. Surface Area N900N300N700N500N200N100 300 nm20 nm  5 m2/g150 m2/g Particle Size Surface Area Series Name   </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Illustrated graphically are the average diameters of several typical series of carbon blacks.  The diameters of the particles are drawn to scale so that you can visualize the size differences. In &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;a &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;another &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;module, we will cover how carbon blacks are named.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Note the two scales to the right of the particle drawings.  One scale is for the size of the particle and the other is the related surface area to that particle size.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Note the diameter range for typical, high volume carbon blacks is from 300 nm down to around 20 nm.  The surface area scale as measured by typical methods ranges from just over 5 m&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;/g up to 150 m&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;/g.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;On the next slide we will show mathematically the inverse relationship between particle size and surface area - a very important concept. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000003.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="4" xmlns="">
		<title>Surface Area is Inversely Proportional to Particle Size</title>
		<content>125,600 nm2  ___ spheres  Surface Area is Inversely Proportional to Particle Size Mathematical Proof:  Surface of a Sphere = πd2  Surface = (1 sphere) × π × (100 nm)2  Surface = (8 spheres) × π × (50 nm)2  Surface = 31,400 nm2 Surface = 62,800 nm2 100 nm   50 nm 25nm   ?  Surface =   62,800 × 2  64  </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;This is a practical course and we do not want to get too excited about a mathematical proof.  However, this example is being shown so that we clearly grasp the fact that particle size is inversely related to surface area.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Note the 100 nm sphere is illustrated as a circle in this two dimensional media.  This sphere would fit into a square box with the length, width and height each equaling 100 nm.  The calculated area on the surface of this sphere is 31, 400 nm&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Next, let's take a sphere half the diameter of the 100 nm sphere which is of course 50 nm.  The illustration shows how eight of these spheres fit in the same 100 nm box.  Calculating the surface of the eight spheres equals 62,800 nm&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;If we should carry this out one more time and half the sphere diameter again then how many spheres would fit in that same 100 nm box?  64 is the correct answer and the surface area doubles again.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;So, if you need to make an adjustment on a reactor to get lower surface area, do the particles need to be smaller or larger and what needs to happen to the temperature in the reactor?  Let's review this relationship.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000004.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="5" xmlns="">
		<title>Particle Size - a Function of Reaction Temperature</title>
		<content> Particle Size - a Function of Reaction Temperature   </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Simply stated, it is the reaction temperature that dictates the particle size (and surface area) as we see in the graph here.  As the temperature of reaction increases, the particle size decreases.  As the particle size decreases, we know that the surface area increases.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;How to control the process to make a certain particle size and surface area will be discussed in much more detail in later modules.  Let's briefly look at where the reaction takes place in a carbon black reactor.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000005.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="6" xmlns="">
		<title>Formation Zone Particle Size Controlled with Temperature</title>
		<content>Formation Zone Particle Size Controlled with Temperature  Formation Zone Oil is cracked and reforms to make aggregates Size and surface area are affected by the temperature in this zone Reactions occur in less than 1 second </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;The formation zone is where the oil (a hydrocarbon) is cracked by the high temperature and reforms into particles which collide together to make aggregates.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Again, the size of the particle and, inversely, the surface area depends on this formation zone temperature.   The reactions in the formation zone are completed very rapidly  - in much less than a second.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000006.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="7" xmlns="">
		<title>Surface Area Tests</title>
		<content>Iodine Test Estimates surface area by adsorption of iodine around each particle Nitrogen Test Estimates surface area by using pressure to coat each particle with nitrogen gas Surface Area Tests </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;There are two basic tests to determine the surface area of carbon black.  The Iodine Absorption is used in most carbon black plants around the world as a process control test.  This test is simply based on the amount of iodine absorbed on the surface.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The other major surface area test is nitrogen surface area.  It is similar to the Iodine test in that the nitrogen is used to coat the surface of the carbon black.  An area of coverage is calculated.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Now, let’s look at the Iodine test in more detail.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000007.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="8" xmlns="">
		<title>Iodine Adsorption milligrams/gram</title>
		<content>Iodine Adsorption&amp;#x0A;milligrams/gram Method (ASTM D1510): Equilibrate carbon black with standard solution of iodine Separate solution from carbon black by centrifugation Pipette aliquot and titrate excess iodine Calculate I2 Number </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;The first step in the test is to equilibrate carbon black with a standard solution of iodine.  The solution containing the excess iodine is separated from the carbon black and an aliquot of this solution is titrated with thiosulfate to determine the excess iodine.  The Iodine Number in mg/g is calculated from this information.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Note that the Iodine Number is not in surface area units but the mg/g does correspond closely to the m&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;/g obtained by the nitrogen surface area method.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000008.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="9" xmlns="">
		<title>Iodine Surface Area Test </title>
		<content>Iodine Surface Area Test&amp;#x0A; Iodine Number is reported in mg/g     1 2 3 Manual Titrator – Method A ASTM D 1510  Automatic Titrator – Method B More precise Test multiple samples Reduces human variation Safe. Automatic Titrator – Method B   </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;In ASTM D1510 there are two approved test methods for Iodine Absorption Number.  Method A is the original manual procedure currently used by Himadri.  Pictured on the left is the basic equipment used which includes an Iodine solution dispenser to measure the Iodine solution into the mixing bottles (1).  Once the carbon black is weighed and mixed with the Iodine solution, it is transferred to the shaker (2) to mix.  After mixing and centrifuging, a pipette is then used to measure the affected Iodine solution for final titration.  The Iodine solution is then titrated (3) with a sodium thiosulfate solution to determine the carbon black absorption of the Iodine.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Method B in ASTM D1510 is a system that uses automated equipment for separating the mixed Iodine solution and then automatically titrating the absorbed Iodine solution.  The basic equipment used is shown on the right.  The apparatus in the center is the &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;titrator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; which delivers very accurate amounts of the liquid sodium thiosulfate solution.   The rotating table to the right presents each Iodine solution sample to the electrodes, stirs the sample and is the point of addition for the sodium thiosulfate solution.  The electrodes respond very precisely to the concentration of Iodine.  Most global carbon companies and carbon black customers use this equipment because it is extremely precise, can test many samples at once, and reduces human variation from the test performance.  It is also safer for the laboratory employee who no longer has to pipette and &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;repeatably&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; handle the chemical  solutions.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;In both Methods A and B, the resulting titration value is then used to calculate the Iodine Number which is reported in milligrams Iodine absorption to grams of carbon black.  This number approximates the surface area of the carbon black.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000009.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="10" xmlns="">
		<title>Nitrogen Surface Area Test</title>
		<content>Method (ASTM D3037): Pressure is recorded as nitrogen gas is added to the sample chamber Nitrogen molecules coat the surface of the particle  The coating reduces the pressure of the nitrogen until the surface of the particle is just coated Calculations convert the amount of nitrogen coating the particle surface to an area of coverage Nitrogen Surface Area Test </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;Nitrogen surface area test relies on a monolayer coating of nitrogen on the surface of the carbon black and is measured by a precise pressure method.  The amount of nitrogen is known along with the area covered by each molecule.  From this the surface area is calculated.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000010.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="11" xmlns="">
		<title>Nitrogen Surface Area Analyzer</title>
		<content>Nitrogen Surface Area Analyzer   Heating and Surface area station Very high purity nitrogen Heat cleans surface of carbon black. Nitrogen introduced and instrument precisely measures nitrogen pressure. Pressure decreases as nitrogen adsorbed by carbon black surface. Final nitrogen adsorbed calculated and converted to carbon black surface area. </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;The nitrogen surface area system in this slide shows a heating station and a surface area station along with a cylinder of very high purity nitrogen.  The heating station is used to clean the surface of the carbon black before the analysis so that the nitrogen will stick to all the surface.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Though it cannot be seen behind the dark plastic, the surface area instrument requires a cryogenic storage &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;dewar&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; of liquid nitrogen in which to immerse the sample.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The instrument very precisely measures the pressure of nitrogen as this gas is added to the sample chamber.  The surface of the carbon black gets coated with the nitrogen molecules and this adsorption reduces the pressure of the nitrogen added until the surface is just covered.  The amount of nitrogen that covers the carbon black is then converted through calculations to an area.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;The nitrogen molecule is much smaller than iodine and can get into more crevices.  This will be illustrated in the next slide.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000011.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="12" xmlns="">
		<title>Surface Area Testing</title>
		<content>  Surface Area Testing                                                             Iodine Number and nitrogen surface area will always be different  There is no such thing as an absolute surface area!  </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;We will take just part of an aggregate to illustrate how iodine and nitrogen molecules coat the surface of the carbon black.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Iodine molecules represented as purple circles are so large that they cannot fit into the crevices of the aggregate.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;As nitrogen molecules represented by the small green circles cover the selected part of the aggregate, you can see how they do penetrate and cover much more of the crevice area than the Iodine.  These differences become significant as the particle size and, hence, the aggregate becomes smaller.  The implication of this is that the Iodine number must be different from the Nitrogen Surface Area especially with smaller particle carbon blacks.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;Also, keep in mind this fundamental concept.  There is no such thing as an absolute surface area.  It is dependent on the size of  the measuring stick that you use.  Therefore, Iodine number and Nitrogen Surface area may be similar in value but they are fundamentally different and can never equal each other unless forced mathematically to do so in a selected range.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;I hope that this module has been both interesting and helpful in your growing understanding of carbon black basic properties.  In the next module, we will explore surface chemistry.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000012.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="13" xmlns="">
		<title>END</title>
		<content>END </content>
		<related-content>&lt;TextFlow xmlns = "http://ns.adobe.com/textLayout/2008" fontFamily = "Verdana" fontSize = "9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span &gt;This is the end&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt; of module 2.3 Surface Area.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span &gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/TextFlow&gt;</related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000013.jpg"/>
	</section>
</document-metadata>
